in a quiet study in Switzerland 1939
Carl Jung wrote
something that would challenge everything we think
about who we are
after decades of treating patients
and exploring the depths of human consciousness
he encountered an ancient truth that seemed impossible
a 2500 year old teaching of the Buddha
that suggested the self he spent his life studying
might not exist at all
yet Jung wasn't deterred
instead he wrote...
most sensible and most direct of all religions
what did this giant of western psychology
see in Buddhist teachings
and more importantly what happens
when these two
profound perspectives on human consciousness collide
the tension between these ideas
holds the key to unlocking a deeper truth
hello I'm Peter from Buddha's wisdom
before we explore this profound paradox
let's set the stage
picture two moments in history
first beneath the Bodhi Tree in ancient India
where Siddhartha Gautama realizes the truth of no self
that our sense of a permanent
unchanging self is an illusion
this radical insight would become
one of Buddhism's core teachings
now fast forward to the early 20th century
Carl Jung
already famous for his work on the human psyche
sits in his study surrounded by eastern texts
he's developing his theory of the self
as the center of psychological wholeness
seemingly the exact opposite of Buddhist teaching
these two perspectives
shaped how millions understand themselves
but here's what makes this truly fascinating
both ideas work
both have helped countless people find peace
and healing
both are supported by modern research
how is this possible? we'll see
how Jung and Buddha develop
their revolutionary insights
their true meaning of self and no self
and the surprising ways
these ideas compliment each other
more than mere philosophy
this understanding holds practical power
to transform your daily life
let's turn back the clock
to understand the historical context
that shaped these revolutionary ideas
our story begins in the vibrant streets of 19th century
Germany
where a young philosopher named Arthur Schopenhauer
first introduced Buddhist ideas
to western intellectual circles
his work would later captivate a young Carl Jung
opening his eyes to eastern wisdom
Jung wrote in his memoirs
Schopenhauer was the first to speak of
the suffering of the world
which visibly and glaringly surrounds us
and of confusion passion evil
this connection deepened in 1909
when Jung encountered Richard Wilhelm
the renowned Chinese classics translator
through their friendship
Jung gained unprecedented access to eastern
philosophical texts marking a turning point
in his understanding of the psyche
this meeting marked a turning point for Jung
from 1909 to 1914 he immersed himself in eastern texts
spending three hours each morning studying Sanskrit
his letters from this period
reveal an increasing fascination
with Buddhist concepts particularly
their parallels with his patients experiences
by 1920
Jung had accumulated one of Europe's most comprehensive
private collections of Buddhist texts
including rare Tibetan manuscripts
twenty five centuries earlier
in the flourishing Gangetic Plain of ancient India
a different revelation unfolded
Prince Siddhartha Gautama  after years of searching
discovered a profound truth under the Bodie Tree
his insight into no self wasn't merely philosophical
it stemmed from direct experience
in the Anatta-lakkhana Sutta he proclaimed
this pivotal moment occurred around 485 BCE
when the 35 year old Siddhartha attained enlightenment
within weeks
he delivered the Dhammacakkappavattana Sutta at Sarnath
establishing the foundation of Buddhist thought
five years later his teaching of Anatta emerged
fully formed in the Anattalakkhana Sutta at Varanasi
the cultural exchange between east and west
accelerated dramatically during Jung's lifetime
as steamships and telegraphs connected continents
Buddhist texts reached Europe in unprecedented numbers
Jung's personal library in Küsnacht
filled with Sanskrit and Pali translations
eastern commentaries and philosophical treatises
but Jung wasn't just a passive reader
his analytical psychology emerged
during a time of profound
global change
while treating patients in his Swiss practice
he noticed patterns that
eerily matched Buddhist descriptions of consciousness
in his clinical notes from 1925
he observed
this convergence wasn't coincidental
both Jung and Buddha
confronted fundamental questions about human suffering
and its roots in our sense of self
their methods differed Jung  through psychoanalysis
Buddha through meditation
but their investigations led to
complementary insights about consciousness
even more fascinating is how Jung's personal crisis
documented in his Red Book
mirrored Buddha's period of intense questioning
both men emerged from their ordeals
with revolutionary understanding
Jung reflected
yet their cultural contexts
shaped how they express these insights
while Buddha taught in the language of dharma
and dependent origination
Jung spoke of archetypes
and the collective unconscious
these different vocabularies
sometimes mask their shared understanding
what exactly did Jung mean by the self
in his groundbreaking work Aion
published in 1951
Jung presents the self as something far more profound
than our everyday personality
he writes the self is not only the center
but also the whole circumference
which embraces both conscious and unconscious
it is the center of this totality
just as the ego is the center of consciousness
for Jung the ego
our conscious identity
is merely the tip of an immense psychological iceberg
through his work with patients
he discovered that beneath our conscious awareness
lies a vast reservoir of psychological material
this wasn't just personal memories
or repressed thoughts
Jung found evidence of universal patterns
he called archetypes
shared across cultures and time periods
in his personal journals
Jung documented numerous cases
where patients
with no knowledge of eastern spirituality
spontaneously produced mandalas
circular symbols
that he recognized as representations of the self
one particularly striking case involved a businessman
who dreamed of a luminous crystal
at the bottom of a deep well
Jung noted without any knowledge of eastern thought
my patient had discovered the symbol of the self
that Buddhist texts describe as the diamond body
but Jung's concept of self wasn't static
in psychology and alchemy
he describes it as a process rather than a fixed entity
the self is not a static entity
but a dynamic process of wholeness
this process which he called individuation
involves integrating unconscious aspects of the psyche
into consciousness
through clinical observation
Jung identified distinct stages
in this journey toward wholeness
patients first encountered their shadow
the rejected aspects of themselves
then came the anima or animus
their inner feminine or masculine counterparts
finally
they experienced what Jung termed self realization
a state remarkably similar to Buddhist enlightenment
Jung supported his theories with extensive research
into mythology religion and alchemy
in his clinical files
he recorded thousands of dreams and visions
that pointed to universal patterns in the human psyche
one patient's dream of a radiant center
surrounded by darkness
paralleled ancient Tibetan mandalas
despite the patient
having no exposure to Buddhist imagery
the self in Jung psychology
serves as both origin and destination
as he wrote in Memories
Dreams Reflections
yet this divine center
paradoxically contains all opposites
conscious and unconscious
good and evil spirit and matter
Jung's late writings reveal
an increasingly nuanced view of the self
one that began to bridge the gap with Buddhist thought
in his forward to D.T. Suzuki's work
he acknowledges
the Buddhist teaching of Anatta
or no self stands as
one of the most radical propositions in human thought
in the Anattalakkhana Sutta
his second discourse after Enlightenment
Buddha challenged
the prevailing notion of an unchanging soul
or self
modern Buddhist scholar Bhikkhu Bodhi explains
the Anatta doctrine
is not a mere philosophical opinion
but a strategy for seeing through the conceit of self
and thereby letting go of all attachment
this interpretation aligns with both classical
commentaries
and contemporary understanding of the teaching
to understand this profound teaching
we must first grasp what Buddha meant by self
in ancient India the dominant
Vedic tradition taught the existence of an eternal
unchanging soul called Atman
Buddha's direct experience
through meditation revealed something different
a dynamic flow of experience with no permanent center
the Buddha used a practical method
to demonstrate this truth
he broke down human experience into five aggregates
or skandhas
form feeling perception
mental formations and consciousness
through systematic examination
he showed that none of these components
alone or combined constitutes a permanent self
consider a simple example
Buddha often used a chariot
when we disassemble a chariot
into its wheels axle
body and reins
where is the chariotness
it exists only as a convenient label for these parts
working together
similarly our sense of self is a useful convention
but under scrutiny we find only changing processes
in the Milindapañha an ancient Buddhist text
we find a fascinating dialogue between the monk
Nagasena and King Melinda
when the king asks Nagasana his name the monk responds
Nagasena is just a designation
a term a concept
a name
no permanent person exists here
this perfectly captures Buddha's teaching on no self
the Visuddhimagga a cornerstone of Buddhist philosophy
presents another compelling perspective
through the metaphor of a lighting lamp
each flame appears continuous
yet is never the same from moment to moment
the text states the being of the present moment lives
but does not proceed to the next moment
this illustrates how our
apparent continuity of self exists
without requiring a permanent essence
the subtlety of this teaching becomes clear
in the Buddha's careful language
he never claimed there is no self
such a statement would simply replace one fixed view
with another
instead
he demonstrated that what we take to be a self
cannot be found when we look deeply
as recorded in the Samyutta Nikaya
this understanding transforms
our relationship with experience
the Dhammapada captures this shift
all conditioned things are impermanent
when one sees this with wisdom
one turns away from suffering
rather than creating despair
this insight liberates us from
the exhausting task of maintaining a fixed identity
the practice of seeing no self
appears throughout Buddhist traditions
Zen masters ask what was your original face
before your parents were born
Tibetan practitioners contemplate the question
who is it that thinks
these inquiries point directly to the experience
beyond our conceptual understanding of self
yet Buddha emphasized
that this teaching serves a practical purpose
the end of suffering
understanding no self naturally
dissolves our tendency to grasp and reject experience
based on a fictional fixed identity
what remains is the natural flow of phenomena
und distorted by the illusion of a permanent self
this inside carries profound implications
by seeing through the illusion of a fixed self
we naturally develop compassion for all beings
who share this fundamental condition
the teaching doesn't negate conventional identity
but reveals its constructed nature
allowing us to engage with life more freely
and authentically
at first glance Jung's concept of the self
and Buddha's teaching of no self appear irreconcilable
yet a deeper examination reveals surprising convergence
in his later writings
Jung himself hinted at this connection
the self
as a unifying principle within the human psyche
occupies the center of potential wholeness
at its core it's both everything and nothing
just as the Buddhists maintain
this apparent paradox resolves
when we understand both perspectives more deeply
Jung's clinical work revealed that
the more his patients approached self realization
the more their rigid ego structures dissolved
in his personal notes from 1938
he observed the experience of the self
brings a dissolution of the identity
we've always taken for granted
here we find the clearest convergence between
Jung and Buddha Jung
self realization and Buddha's liberation
both point to transcending the ego's limitations
while their languages differ
both discovered that freedom comes through releasing
rigid self concepts not strengthening them
what unites these perspectives
is their shared recognition
of the ego as both necessary and illusory
Jung believed that
the ego serves as a gateway to greater wholeness
just as Buddha acknowledged that conventional identity
is a useful tool for navigating daily life
yet both traditions
ultimately guide us beyond this limited sense of self
revealing a deeper reality
that transcends individuality
the Tibetan Book of the dead
particularly fascinated Jung
who wrote
extensive commentary on its psychological significance
he noted how its description of consciousness
dissolving into clear light
paralleled his patients experiences of ego dissolution
during profound psychological transformation
what Buddhism calls emptiness
he wrote
we might call the ultimate ground of psychic reality
a revealing example comes from Jung's own practice
during his confrontation with the unconscious
documented in the Red Book
Jung experienced states remarkably
similar to Buddhist descriptions of emptiness
he describes moments where his usual sense of self
completely dissolved
revealing what he called the pleroma
a state beyond all distinctions
both traditions recognize that our usual sense of self
causes suffering
while Buddhism directly points to the illusion of self
Jung's approach guides people through
the psychological structures that maintain this
illusion as he noted in a 1939 seminar
individualation leads to a paradoxical result
the more one becomes oneself
the more one realizes the universal quality of being
the role of suffering also bridges their teachings
for Buddha
suffering arises from clinging to impermanent phenomena
including the self
Jung similarly
observed that
psychological distress often stems from an inability
to integrate the unconscious
leading to fragmented identities
both approaches emphasize a path of transformation
Buddha through the Eightfold Path
and Jung through individualation
that resolves this inner tension
and fosters a deeper harmony
Jung's concept of archetypes offers another bridge
these universal patterns exist
independent of any individual ego
suggesting a reality beyond personal identity
similarly Buddhist teachings speak of dharma
the underlying patterns of reality that exist
whether or not we recognize them
the therapeutic practices of both traditions
often align in surprising ways
Jung's active imagination
parallels certain Buddhist visualization practices
both methods aim to loosen rigid ego structures
and allow deeper wisdom to emerge
as Jung wrote after studying Buddhist texts
the east has taught me another wider
more profound and higher understanding
understanding through life
this convergence becomes particularly clear
in their shared emphasis on direct experience
both Buddha and Jung insisted that intellectual
understanding alone
cannot transform consciousness
Jung stated
the patient must experience something that grips him
then he can learn to overcome his former attitudes
in the end
both Jung and Buddha teach that transformation begins
by facing ourselves not as static entities
but as fluid processes
through direct experience
in meditation analysis or daily reflection
we discover that freedom lies in
embracing the paradox of selfhood
it is both everything and nothing
an illusion and a gateway to wholeness
the synthesis of Jung psychology and Buddhist wisdom
offers profound tools for personal transformation
a vivid example appears in contemporary
therapeutic practices
where clinicians integrate both perspectives
one therapist documented a patient's breakthrough
when Sarah stopped trying to fix herself
and began to observe its fluid nature
her anxiety decreased dramatically
she discovered what Jung called the self
and Buddha pointed to as no self
not by seeking but by letting go
this integration manifests in concrete practices
take dream work for instance
Jung's approach to dreams
encourages us to engage with dream figures
as aspects of our psyche
when combined with Buddhist mindfulness
this practice becomes even more powerful
rather than identifying with
or rejecting dream experiences
we learn to observe them with spacious awareness
contemplative psychotherapy
demonstrates another practical application
here Jung's understanding of the shadow
meets Buddhist techniques
for working with difficult emotions
patients learn to welcome
all aspects of their experience
without identifying with them
one psychiatrist noted
when we stop fighting against parts of ourselves
integration happens naturally
the practice of active imagination
central to Jungian psychology
takes on new depth when paired with Buddhist insights
instead of seeking a stronger self
practitioners learn to move
fluidly between different aspects
of psyche
a long term meditator described this experience
I used to think I needed to become someone better
now I see there's no fixed self to improve
just an unfolding process to trust
this combined approach
particularly helps with chronic identity struggles
Jung's map of psychological development
enriched by Buddhist wisdom
shows how
our suffering often stems from rigid self concepts
one case study describes a businessman
who transformed his workaholism
understanding both perspectives
helped him see his drive for success
as neither self nor not self
but as a pattern he could relate to more wisely
even relationships benefit from this integrated
understanding
when we grasp neither at permanent selfhood
nor deny our relative existence
we can engage more authentically with others
a couple's therapist reported
partners
who understand both Jung and Buddha's insights
fight less about who's right
and connect more deeply with each other's
essential nature
beyond individual transformation and relationships
these insights have found their way into broader
social contacts in organizational settings
this synthesis has borne fruit
leadership programs incorporating both perspectives
help executives navigate power
without becoming inflated
or depleted
as one CEO reflected
understanding the self as both center and no center
paradoxically
made me both more effective and more humble
therapists and practitioners
keep finding fresh ways to blend these approaches
the key lies not in choosing between Jung and Buddha
but in allowing both perspectives to illuminate
our path toward wholeness
what began as a seeming contradiction
between Jung's integrated self
and Buddha's no self
reveals itself as a profound complimentary
their wisdom separated by millennia
yet united in purpose
offers us a richer understanding of human consciousness
and the path to psychological freedom
Jung wrote near the end of his life
the goal of eastern religious practice is
the same as that of western psychology
the shifting of the center of gravity
from the ego to the self
Buddha express the same truth through different words
like a water bubble like a mirage
one who regards the world in this way
death does not find
both remind us that our suffering stems
not from having or lacking a self
but from how we relate to our experience
by loosening our grip on fixed identity
we can embrace life with greater wisdom and compassion
Jung called this wholeness
Buddha termed it liberation
both paths lead to the same universal truth
freedom lies in
seeing beyond the illusion of separation
like the two wings of a bird
Jung's depth
psychology and Buddhist teachings work together
showing us that our struggles with identity
can become gateways to profound wisdom
now I leave you with a question to reflect on
what lies beyond the story you tell yourself
about who you are?
share your thoughts in the comments below
what resonated with you what challenged you
your perspective enriches this conversation
and if you haven't already
join our journey by subscribing
together we'll continue
exploring the profound questions that shape our lives
until next time may your journey be filled with clarity
courage and compassion see you in the next video