[Music]
what if I told you your worst fears are
nothing but Paper Tigers sounds crazy
right stick with me because by the end
of this video you might be laughing at
your
anxieties hey there fear facers it's
Matt your neighborhood Buddhist decoder
today we're diving into the wild world
of fear and anxiety but don't worry this
journey won't be nearly as scary as that
time you thought a ghost was in your
closet only to find out it was just a
shirt you never
wear no I'm not here to tell you to
Simply stop being afraid we all know
that works about as well as telling a
cat not to knock things off tables
instead we'll explore some ancient
wisdom so practical it might blow your
mind first let me ask you something have
you ever been so wrapped up in your
fears that you missed out on the good
stuff right in front of you like being
so worried about tripping during a dance
that you forgot to enjoy the music well
get ready because I've got a story
that's going to make you see fear in a
whole new light picture this a man is
running through a forest heart pounding
sweat
dripping why because there's a tiger
chasing him talk about a Bad Day right
but wait it gets worse he reaches the
edge of a cliff and in his Panic he
loses his footing and Falls luckily or
maybe not so luckily he manages to grab
onto a Vine hanging over the cliff
Edge now if you're thinking this story
couldn't possibly get any more intense
hold on to your meditation cushions our
unfortunate friend looks down only to
see another tiger pacing at the bottom
of the cliff looking up at him like he's
a tasty human snack and just when you
thought things couldn't get any worse he
notices two mice one black one white
gnawing away the vine he's clinging to
talk about being caught between a rock
and a hard place right or in this case
between two tigers in a very long fall
but here's where it gets interesting in
the midst of all this chaos and danger
our hero spots a wild strawberry growing
on The Cliff face and what does he do he
plucks it and Pops it into his mouth now
I know what you're thinking Matt my dude
what does this Bonker story have to do
with overcoming fear and and
anxiety well my friends that's exactly
what we're going to unpack today this
little tale is like a Swiss army knife
of Buddhist wisdom it's got all the
tools we need to start tackling our
fears so are you ready to turn your
paper tigers into playful kittens to
transform your Cliffs of Despair into
mole Hills of opportunity then let's
dive in and discover how the Buddha's
ancient wisdom can help us modern-day
anxious adventurers find a little peace
in our wild world
by the end of this video you'll be
savoring life's strawberries even when
it feels like everything's going
bananas now let's break down this wild
ride of a story our protagonist is
literally stuck between a rock and a
hard place or should I say between two
very hungry tigers and a very long fall
it's like the universe decided to play a
cosmic game of would you rather with
this poor guy's life but here's the
kicker in the middle of what's probably
the worst day of his life he takes a
moment to enjoy a strawberry a
strawberry can you imagine being in that
situation and thinking you know what
would make this better a snack but
that's exactly what he does this my
friends is what the Buddha was talking
about when he spoke of mindfulness and
living in the present moment our guy in
the story can't change his past he can't
unun into that forest or unfall off that
Cliff he also can't control his future
those Tigers aren't going anywhere and
those mice are determined to turn that
vine into dental floss but what he can
control is his present moment he can
choose to spend his last moments in
panic and regret or he can choose to
fully experience the sweetness of that
strawberry it's like he's saying well if
this is my last meal it might as well be
a good one now I'm not saying we should
all go out and put ourselves in
life-threatening situations just to
appreciate our snacks more but think
about it how often do we miss out on the
the strawberries in our own lives
because we're too busy worrying about
the
Tigers this brings us to another piece
of Buddha's wisdom that's perfect for
our fear busting toolkit the parable of
the two
arrows now don't worry we're not
actually going to be shooting any arrows
today this is more of a metaphorical
archery
lesson imagine this you're minding your
own business maybe scrolling through
social media or trying to figure out if
it's too late to start that load of
laundry when suddenly ouch you've been
hit by an arrow that's going to leave a
mark right now in this story that first
Arrow represents the unavoidable Pains
of life it could be anything a breakup
losing your job or realizing you're out
of coffee on a Monday morning these
things happen and they hurt that's just
part of Being Human but here's where it
gets interesting Buddha says that often
we end up shooting ourselves with a
second Arrow this second arrow is all
the extra suffering we pile on top of
the original pain it's the Y me the this
always happens the I'll never recover
from this thoughts that we torture
ourselves with it's like stubbing your
toe and then deciding to drop a brick on
it for good measure ouch right but
here's the kicker while we often can't
avoid the first Arrow the second one is
totally optional let's bring this back
to our fear and anxiety often the thing
we're afraid of is that first Arrow but
all the worrying the sleepless nights
the stress eating or is that just me
that's us repeatedly shooting ourselves
with that second Arrow before the first
one is even
[Music]
hit so how do we stop this archery
practice from Hell well my Fearless
friends it's time to introduce Buddha's
top three fear busting techniques think
of these as your spiritual Swiss army
knife handy tools to whip out whenever
fear and anxiety start creeping in first
up we've got mindfulness meditation now
I know what you're thinking
Matt Are you seriously telling me to sit
still and breathe when I'm freaking out
and the answer is kind of yeah but hear
me out mindfulness isn't about zoning
out or floating away on a cloud of
Tranquility it's about tuning in to
what's happening right now typically by
focusing on your breath or bodily
Sensations it's like putting your brain
through a car wash all those muddy
anxious thoughts get a good scrubbing
leaving you with a clearer
perspective and the best part you don't
need any fancy equipment or a
Mountaintop Retreat you can do it right
now wherever you are even if you're
hiding in the bathroom at work not that
I've ever done
that next on our fear busting Hit List
is the loving kindness practice this
one's all about cultivating feelings of
Goodwill towards yourself and others
it's like being your own best friend but
without the awkward small talk here's a
humorous example of loving kindness
selft talk instead of saying I'm such a
disaster try hey there you delightful
mess you're doing your best it's about
replacing that mean little voice in your
head with one that's a bit more well
kind and maybe has a sense of humor last
but not least we've got the impermanence
reflection this one's a real game
changer folks it's all about recognizing
that all things including our thoughts
and feelings are temporary and
constantly changing think of it like
that trending meme that's everywhere one
day and forgotten the next
your
anxiety same deal it might feel all
consuming right now but give it time and
it'll fade faster than last year's dance
craze remember the Harlem Shake
exactly now that we've got our fear
busting toolkit it's time to put it into
action are you ready to level up your
courage game then let me introduce you
to the fear fails challenge for the next
week I'm challenging you yes
you to face one small fear each day
don't worry I'm not asking you to go
skydiving or wrestle a bear unless
that's your thing in which case go for
it you magnificent
Daredevil we're talking about those
everyday fears that nag at us here's how
it works each day you'll tackle One Mini
fear using our Buddhist wisdom maybe
it's speaking up in a meeting trying
that exotic dish at the new restaurant
or finally cleaning out that scary space
under your bed whatever it is approach
it with mindfulness show yourself some
loving kindness and remember it's all
impermanent day one face the fear of
failure try something new and embrace
the possibility of messing up remember
even the Buddha probably tripped over
his robes a few times day two conquer
the fear of awkward silences
strike up a conversation with a stranger
who knows you might make a new friend or
at least have a funny story to
tell day three overcome the fear of
looking silly dance like nobody's
watching in a public place trust me it's
liberating day four battle the fear of
rejection ask for something you want
even if you think the answer might be no
remember the worst they can say is no or
sir
this is a
Wendy's day five tackle the fear of the
unknown take a different route to work
or try a new hobby who knows what
exciting Adventures
await day six confront the fear of
vulnerability share something personal
with a friend or loved one it might feel
scary but connection is worth it day
seven face your biggest fear within
reason of course whatever has been
holding you back today the day to look
it in the eye and say not today fear
I've got strawberries to
enjoy remember this challenge isn't
about being Fearless it's about learning
to dance with your fears rather than
letting them lead and hey if you stumble
along the way that's okay too we're all
just humans trying our best right so
who's ready to join me on this fear
busting Adventure share your experiences
in the comments below and let's create a
community of courageous strawberry
eaters
now here's where Buddha throws us a
curveball that will make M Knight
Shyamalan jealous what if I told you
that the goal isn't to eliminate fear
but to embrace it plot
twist that's right folks Buddha's Secret
Sauce isn't about becoming Fearless it's
about becoming fear friendly it's like
inviting that annoying neighbor over for
dinner instead of hiding behind the
couch when they knock except in this
case the annoying neighbor is your own
mind fun times right but here's the
thing fear when we look at it closely is
often just trying to protect us it's
like that overzealous bodyguard who
tackles you to the ground when someone
sneezes nearby a bit extra sure but its
heart's in the right place let me share
a personal story a while back I was
terrified of public speaking the thought
of standing in front of a crowd made me
want to hide in a cave and become a
Hermit but instead of running away I
decided to lean into it
I joined a local Toast Masters Club and
let me tell you that first speech was a
disaster I was shaking like a leaf in a
hurricane and I'm pretty sure I invented
a new language with all my stuttering
but here's the kicker I didn't die the
world didn't end and believe it or not
some people even said they enjoyed it
though they might have just been being
nice by facing my fear headon I learned
that it wasn't as scary as I'd built it
up to be in my head that's the beauty of
embracing
fear when we stop running from it and
start listening to it we often find that
it has something valuable to teach us
maybe it's showing us where we need to
grow or what's really important to us or
maybe it's just reminding us that we're
alive and human so the next time fear
comes knocking instead of slamming the
door in its face try inviting it in for
a cup of tea you might be surprised at
the conversation that follows who knows
that fear might just become your newest
weirdest friend and let's face it we
could all use a few more weird friends
right now I know what you're thinking
that's all well and good Matt but what
about when anxiety hits me like a ton of
bricks and I can't even remember my own
name let alone some fancy Buddhist
wisdom don't worry I've got you covered
let's talk about some practical tips for
those anxiety prone moments when your
brain decides to throw a panic party and
forgot to invite your rational
thinking first up we've got the good old
5 4 3 2 1 grounding technique it's like
playing I spy but with your anxiety name
five things you can see four things you
can touch three things you can hear two
things you can smell and one thing you
can taste before you know it you're back
in the present moment and your anxiety
is wondering where the party
went next try some box breathing imagine
drawing a square in the air with your
finger as you trace each side breathe in
for four counts hold for four breathe
out for four and hold for four it's like
giving your nervous system a
timeout plus if anyone asks what you're
doing you can just say you're practicing
to be a mime
winwin here's a fun one the worry versus
witty game when an anxious thought pops
up try to come up with the most
ridiculous over-the-top outcome possible
worried about that
presentation imagine tripping and
accidentally discovering a new dance
move that becomes a worldwide sensation
it's hard to stay anxious when you're
trying not to laugh and don't forget the
power of distraction keep a list of
quick engaging tasks on hand it could be
anything from solving a Rubik's Cube to
naming all 50 states in alphabetical
order by the time you remember that
Wyoming exists your anxiety might have
decid decided to take a hike lastly
never underestimate the power of a good
oldfashioned self hug Wrap Your Arms
Around yourself and give a gentle
squeeze it's like your body's way of
saying hey we've got this plus it's a
lot less awkward than trying to hug
yourself in public trust me on that one
remember these tips aren't about making
your anxiety Disappear Completely
they're about giving you a moment to
catch your breath to remember remember
that you're more than your anxious
thoughts it's like pressing the pause
button on your worry marathon and
sometimes that little pause is all we
need to realize that we're stronger than
we
[Music]
think so there you have it folks
Buddha's guide to overcoming fear and
anxiety served with a side of humor and
a Sprinkle of modern-day wisdom we've
journeyed from man-eating Tigers to
embracing our fears and hopefully picked
up some handy tools along the way let's
recap our fear busting tool kit one
mindfulness meditation giving your brain
that much needed Car Wash Two Loving
kindness practice becoming your own best
friend minus the awkward small talk
three impermanence reflection remember
this too shall pass like that
embarrassing haircut from high
school four the fear fails challenge
your 7-Day ticket to courage
Ville five embracing fear turn turning
your enemy into a weird but insightful
friend six practical tips for anxiety
prone moments because sometimes you need
a quick fix now I've got a challenge for
you my Fearless friends I want you to
pick one of these tools and try it out
this
week maybe it's the fear fails challenge
or perhaps you'll start each day with a
mini mindfulness session whatever you
choose give it a go and see what happens
but don't keep all this newfound wisdom
to yourself share your experiences in
the comments below did you have an epic
fail that turned into an unexpected win
did you discover a hidden talent for
mime inspired breathing exercises we
want to hear about it all and hey if you
found this video helpful don't forget to
give it a thumbs up and hit that
subscribe button it's like giving the
algorithm a high five and who doesn't
love a good high five stay tuned for our
next video where we'll be diving into
well I don't want to spoil the surprise
but let's just say it involves
meditation
memes and possibly a rubber
chicken trust me you won't want to miss
it remember Life's too short to let fear
and anxiety call all the shots so go out
there face those Paper Tigers and don't
forget to savor the strawberries along
the way this is Matt your friendly
neighborhood Buddhist decoder signing
off stay curious stay wise and most
importantly stay wonderfully weird