[Music]
hi I'm Matt from Buddha's wisdom today's
video is different we'll read the first
three chapters of the dapada pure and
uninterrupted just as Buddhist monks
have done for over 2,000 years these
verses contain the Buddha's direct
teachings about the Mind happiness and
wisdom I invite you to Simply listen or
read along with the text on screen in
our next video Peter and I will break
down every meaning symbol and practical
application but for now let these
ancient words speak for themselves take
a deep breath and let's
begin chapter 1 the pairs introduces the
Cornerstone of the Buddha's teachings
the power of the mind it highlights the
Dual nature of our thoughts how impure
thoughts lead to suffering and pure
thoughts lead to happiness these verses
emphasize the Eternal law of cause and
effect urging us to tame the mind to
transform Our
Lives mind precedes all mental States
mind is their Chief they are all mind
rought if with an impure mind a person
speaks or acts suffering follows him
like the wheel that follows the foot of
the
ox mind precedes all mental States
mind is their Chief they are all mind
rought if with a pure mind a person
speaks or acts happiness follows him
like his never departing
Shadow he abused me he struck me he
overpowered me he robbed me those who
Harbor such thoughts do not still their
hatred he abused me he struck me he
overpowered me he robbed me those who do
not Harbor such thoughts still their
hatred hatred is Never appeased by
hatred In This World by nonh hatred
alone is hatred
appeased this is an eternal
law there are those who do not realize
that one day we all must die but those
who do realize this settle their
quarrels just as the wind sweeps away a
weak tree so Mara sweeps away the person
who lives for pleasure UNC controlled in
senses immoderate in eating lazy and
weak just as the wind cannot shake a
mountain so Mara can never shake the
person who lives meditating on the
impurities controlled in senses moderate
in eating and filled with faith and
Earnest
effort whoever being depraved devoid of
self-control and truthfulness should
Dawn the yellow robe they surely are not
worthy of it
but whoever is purged of depravity well
established in virtues filled with
self-control and truthfulness they
indeed are worthy of the yellow
robe those who imagine truth in untruth
and see untruth in truth never arrive at
truth but follow vain
desires those who know truth is truth
and untruth is untruth arrive at truth
and follow true desires
just as rain breaks through an ill
thatched house so passion penetrates an
undeveloped
mind just as rain does not break through
a well thatched house so passion never
penetrates a well-developed
mind here one Grieves Hereafter one
Grieves in both States the evildoer
Grieves one Grieves one suffers seeing
one's own defiled
Deeds here one rejoices Hereafter one
rejoices in both States the well doer
rejoices one rejoices one exalts seeing
one's own pure
Deeds here one suffers Hereafter one
suffers in both States the evildoer
suffers evil have I done thus one
suffers furthermore one suffers having
gone to a woeful
state here one is Happy Hereafter one is
happy in both States the well doer is
happy
good have I done thus one is Happy
furthermore one is Happy having gone to
a blissful
State much though one recites the sacred
texts but acts not accordingly that
heedless one is like a cow herd who
counts others cows one does not partake
of the benefits of the Holy
life little though one recites the
sacred texts but puts the teaching into
practice forsaking lust hatred and
delusion with tr true wisdom and
emancipated mind clinging to nothing of
this or any other world one indeed
partakes of the benefits of the Holy
life chapter 2 heedfulness is a call to
mindfulness and vigilance the Buddha
teaches us that heedfulness is the path
to Liberation while heedlessness leads
to spiritual Decay this chapter inspires
us to cultivate mindfulness as our
greatest treasure and to see it as the
key to nibana
heedfulness is the path to the deathless
heedlessness is the path to death the
heedful die not the heedless are as if
dead
already distinctly understanding this
the wise in heedfulness rejoice
delighting in the realm of the noble
ones the wise ones ever meditative and
steadfastly
persevering experience nibana the
Supreme security from bondage
ever grows the glory of one who is
energetic and mindful pure in conduct
considerate self-controlled righteous in
life and
diligent by effort and heedfulness
discipline and self-mastery let the Wise
One make for oneself an island which no
flood can
overwhelm the foolish and ignorant
indulge in heedlessness but the Wise One
keeps their mindfulness as their
greatest
treasure do not indulge in heedlessness
nor sink into sensual pleasure the
mindful one through meditation achieves
abundant
happiness when the Wise One drives away
heedlessness by mindfulness having
ascended the Palace of wisdom sorrowless
they behold The Sorrowing crowd as a
wise mountain climber beholds the
ignorant on the
ground mindful among the heedless Wide
Awake among the sleeping the Wise One
advances like a swift horse leaving the
weak behind
through mindfulness mavan Indra gained
Supremacy among the gods mindfulness is
ever praised heedlessness is ever
despised the monk who Delights in
mindfulness and regards heedlessness
with fear advances like fire burning all
Fetters small and
large the monk who Delights in
mindfulness and regards heedlessness
with fear is not liable to fall away
they are close to nibana
[Music]
Chapter 3 The Mind delves into the
complexity and subtlety of our inner
world the Buddha Likens the mind to a
Restless fish or a Fletcher's Arrow
difficult to control but powerful when
tamed these verses remind us to guard
our minds and see it as the gateway to
freedom from
suffering the flickering fickle mind
difficult to guard difficult to control
the wise person straightens as a
Fletcher straightens an arrow
like a fish that is drawn from its
watery Abode and thrown upon land even
so does this mind
flutter hence should the realm of the
passions be
shunned the mind is hard to control
Swift and flighty it alights where it
wishes good is it to tame the mind for a
tamed mind brings
happiness the mind is very hard to
perceive extremely subtle a lights
wherever it wishes let the wise person
guard it a guarded mind brings
happiness wandering far dwelling alone
Bess lying in a cave is the Mind those
who subdue it are freed from Mara's
bonds for one whose mind is unsteady who
knows not the true teaching whose Faith
wavers wisdom does not
mature there is no fear for one whose
mind is not filled with desires whose
mind is not Afflicted who has gone
beyond both Merit and
demerit realizing that this body is
fragile like a clay pot and fortifying
this mind like a well fortified City
fight out Mara with the sword of wisdom
then guard your Conquest remaining free
from
attachment before long aless this body
will lie upon the Earth unheated and
lifeless like a useless
log whatever harm an enemy may do to an
enemy or a hater to a hater an
ill-directed mind inflicts on oneself
even greater
harm what neither mother nor father nor
any other relative can do a
well-directed mind does even
[Music]
better chapter 4 flowers uses vivid
imagery to teach about the fleeting
nature of life and the importance of
virtuous actions like a Garland maker
crafting a masterpiece we are encouraged
to shape our lives with good deeds and
wisdom creating Beauty amidst
impermanence who shall overcome this
Earth this realm of Yama and this sphere
of men and gods who shall bring to
Perfection the well-taught path of
wisdom as an expert Garland maker would
his floral
design a striver on the path shall
overcome this Earth this realm of Yama
and this sphere of men and gods the
striver on the path shall bring to
perfection Perfection the well taught
path of wisdom as an expert Garland
maker would his Floral
Design realizing that this body is like
froth penetrating its mirage-like nature
and plucking out Mara's flower tipped
arrows of sensuality go beyond sight of
the king of
death as a mighty flood sweeps away the
sleeping Village so death carries away
the person of distracted mind who only
plucks the flowers of
pleasure the D Royer brings under his
sway the person of distracted mind who
insatiate in sense desires only plucks
the flowers of
pleasure as a Bee gathers nectar and
departs without harming the flower its
color or fragrance so let the sage go
about in the
village let none find fault with others
let none see the omissions and
commissions of others but let one see
one's own acte done and
undone like a beautiful flower full of
color but without fragrance even so
fruitless are the fair words of one who
does not practice
them like a beautiful flower full of
color and also fragrant even so fruitful
are the fair words of one who practices
them as from a heap of flowers many
Garland strands can be made even so
should many Good Deeds be done by one
born
Immortal not the sweet smell of flowers
not even the fragrance an of sandal
tagura or Jasmine blows Against the Wind
but the fragrance of The Virtuous blows
Against the
Wind truly the virtuous man pervades all
directions with the fragrance of his
virtue of all the fragrances sandal
tagra Blue Lotus and
Jasmine the fragrance of virtue is the
sweetest faint is the frag of tagara and
sandal but excellent is the fragrance of
The Virtuous wafting even amongst the
gods Mara never finds the path of the
truly virtuous who abide in heedfulness
and are freed by Perfect
knowledge as a sweet smelling Lotus
rises from a heap of rubbish thrown on
the highway so does a disciple of the
fully enlightened one shine resplendant
with wisdom amidst the rubbish heap of
blind worldlings
[Music]
chapter 5 the fool is a cautionary tale
about ignorance and its consequences the
Buddha warns against Foolish Pride
desire for recognition and attachment to
worldly gains instead he urges us to
pursue wisdom humility and Detachment
from fleeting
honors long is the night to the
sleepless long is the league to the
weary long is samsara to fools who know
not the sublime truth
if as the disciple fares along he meets
no companion who is better or equal let
him firmly pursue his solitary career
there is no fellowship with the
fool the fool worries thinking I have
sons I have
wealth indeed when he himself is not his
own when are Sons whence Is
wealth a fool who knows his foolishness
is wise at least to that extent but a
fool who thinks himself wise is a fool
indeed though all his life a fool
Associates with a wise man he no more
comprehends the truth than a spoon
tastes the flavor of the
soup though only for a moment a
Discerning person Associates with a wise
man quickly he comprehends the truth
just as the tongue tastes the flavor of
the
soup fools of little wit are enemies
unto themselves as they move about doing
evil Deeds
the fruits of which are
bitter ill done is that action of doing
which one repents later and the fruit of
which one weeping reaps with
tears well done is that action of doing
which one repents not later and the
fruit of which one reaps with delight
and
happiness so long as an evil deed has
not ripened the fool thinks it as sweet
as honey but when the evil deed ripens
the fool comes to
grief month after month a fool may eat
his food with the tip tip of a blade of
grass but he still is not worth a 16th
part of the those who have comprehended
the
truth truly an evil deed committed does
not immediately bear fruit like milk
that does not turn sour all at once but
smoldering it follows the fool like fire
covered by
Ashes to his own ruin the fool gains
knowledge for it Cleaves his head and
destroys his innate
goodness the fool seeks undeserved
reputation precedence among monks
authority over monasteries and honor
among
householders let both laymen and monks
think that it was done by me in every
work great and small let them follow me
such is the ambition of the fool thus
his desire and pride
increase one is the Quest for worldly
gain and quite another is the path to
nibana clearly understanding this let
not the monk the disciple of the Buddha
be carried away by worldly Acclaim but
develop Detachment
instead you've just experienced five
chapters of the dapada containing some
of buddhism's most essential teachings
about the Mind wisdom and the path to
peace take a moment to let these words
settle this is just the start of our
dhma po jour Journey there are 26
chapters in total and I'm excited to
share every single one with you think of
it as your weekly dose of ancient wisdom
coming up next week Peter and I will
break down everything we just read
making it super relevant for your daily
life plus I'll be back with more
chapters of pure dap readings hit
subscribe and the notification Bell to
stay in the loop I'd love to hear which
verse hit home for you drop your
thoughts in the comments below
subscribe and tap the notification Bell
to ensure you don't miss our analysis
video and if any verse particularly
resonated with you share your thoughts
in the comments
below thanks for being here with me
today this is Matt from Buddha's wisdom
and I'll catch you in the next one