imagine waking up tomorrow and you don't exist anymore
not your body that's still there
not your awareness you're still conscious
but the you that you think you are completely gone
your personality your life story
your insecurities your grudges all vanished
according to Buddha
this isn't just some philosophical thought experiment
it's the doorway to the greatest freedom
you'll ever experience
what's up wisdom seekers Matt here
today we're diving into Buddhism's most mind bending
teaching one that flips everything you think
you know about yourself upside down
we've touched on non self in previous videos
but today we're going all in on the big question
think about it every day
you wake up thinking
you're the same person you were yesterday
you have this story about who you are
maybe you're the funny one
the responsible one the anxious one
whatever you protect this identity at all costs
when someone criticizes you
it hurts
because they're attacking the self you've built
but what if this solid
unchanging you doesn't actually exist
what if it's more like a character in a play
that you've been performing so long
you forgot you were acting
the Buddha discovered something radical 2,500 years ago
that modern neuroscience is only now confirming
this sense of a permanent
separate self is actually an illusion
created by our brains and when this illusion falls away
something absolutely incredible happens
now this teaching of non self
or anatta in Pali
is one of Buddhism's three marks of existence
alongside impermanence anicca and suffering dukkha
these three insights form
the foundation of the Buddha's
revolutionary understanding of reality
while other spiritual traditions
were busy describing the eternal soul
or unchanging self
the Buddha turned this idea on its head
he taught that seeing
through the illusion of a permanent self
was the key to liberation from suffering
so for the next 20 minutes
I invite you to hold your sense of self
a little more lightly
we're about to explore what shifts
what opens up
and what becomes possible when you don't exist
and trust me it's way more exciting than it is scary
let's start with what actually happens
in those rare moments
when your sense of self temporarily vanishes
have you ever been so absorbed in something
maybe playing music or being in nature
or even just watching a sunset
that you completely forgot about yourself
no thoughts about how you look
what you need to do later or who you are
just pure experience with no you at the center of it
as the Zen master Dogen said
these are glimpses of non self
and they happen more often than you might think
take Alex
a surfer from California who described his experience
I caught this perfect wave and suddenly there was no me
surfing anymore
there was just surfing happening
complete oneness with the wave
it was the most peaceful and alive I've ever felt
this isn't just random neuroscientists have found that
during these flow states
activity in the part of your brain
responsible for self referential thinking
actually drops significantly
your brain literally stops generating the sense of you
for a while the Buddha put it simply
what's fascinating is
what people consistently report
feeling in these moments profound peace
unexpected joy and a sense of connection to everything
not the jittery happiness we usually chase
like a dog after its tail
but something deeper like
finally remembering a name
that's been on the tip of your tongue
your entire life
as the famous Zen saying goes
but the difference is there's no you doing the chopping
the Buddha taught that
these aren't just nice experiences
they're actually glimpses of our natural state
when the illusion of a separate self
temporarily drops away
so what's actually happening in these moments
when you disappear
time perception changes
everything feels like it's happening in an eternal now
boundaries dissolve
the line between you and everything else
gets very blurry
fear vanishes
because there's no separate self to protect
effort drops
things just seem to happen effortlessly through you
rather than by you
the contemporary Buddhist teacher
Adyashanti describes it perfectly
but here's where it gets really interesting
what if these weren't just fleeting moments
what if this was available as a more stable realization
what if you could function in daily life
from this place of no solid self
this is exactly what the Buddhist path is pointing
toward not just glimpses
but a fundamental shift in how you experience reality
so now that we know what these moments feel like
let's explore the freedom that comes
when the prison of self begins to dissolve
think about how much of your life is spent defending
maintaining
and worrying about this self you think you are
when someone criticizes you
it hurts because they're attacking your self image
when you compare yourself to others
you're measuring yourself against theirs
when you replay embarrassing moments from years ago
at 3:00am
you're protecting the story of who you think you are
the Buddha called this constant maintenance dukkha
commonly translated as suffering
but it's more like a persistent unease
a background anxiety that never fully goes away
as long as there's a you to protect
so what happens when this self disappears
freedom happens
as Thich Nhat Hanh beautifully put it
last year I was hiking in the mountains
completely absorbed in work problems
then a bird call snapped me into the present moment
in that instant
Matt with all his problems vanished
there was just awareness
experiencing the mountain
the sky
the sound
no separation
just life happening
the relief was incredible
like putting down a heavy backpack
I didn't even realize I was carrying
this is what the Buddha was pointing to
when the self disappears
the constant inner critic finally shuts up
because there's no you to criticize
embarrassment fades away
because there's no reputation to protect
the need to be special vanishes
because there's no you that needs to stand out
the fear of failure dissolves
because there is no you that can fail
the 12th century Zen master Dogen wrote
and your place is precisely where the separate self
ends
one participant in our meditation retreat
described it this way
it was like I'd been holding my breath my entire life
and finally exhaled I realized that what I called me
was actually just a collection of thoughts
I was desperately clinging to
neuroscience gives us some interesting insights here
too studies of experienced meditators
show reduced activity in the areas of the brain
associated with self referential thinking
and increased
activity in areas associated with awareness
and present moment attention
in other words as the self construct weakens
awareness actually expands
but here's an important point
this
freedom doesn't mean you become an emotional zombie
or lose your personality
actually quite the opposite
when you're not constantly maintaining
a rigid sense of self you become more spontaneous
more authentic more alive
without a fixed self to defend
you're free to respond to each moment freshly
without the burden of how I should be
or what others expect of me
the Zen teacher Shunryu Suzuki explained it perfectly
so if there's no solid 'me' behind the wheel
what happens when you grab coffee with friends
or argue with your partner
that's where things get really interesting
now let's talk about something we all care about
relationships
what happens to your connections with others
when you don't exist
think about the last argument you had
with someone close to you
chances are it revolved around defending your position
your feelings your perspective
you hurt me you don't understand my needs
you don't appreciate what I do for you
what if all those 'me's and 'my's
were suddenly not so solid
when non self is realized
relationships transform in remarkable ways
as the Buddha taught
first comparison and competition naturally fade away
when there's no solid you to compare with others
the exhausting game of one-upmanship ends
you no longer need to be prettier
smarter wealthier
or more successful than others
because there's no separate you that needs to win
Jason a longtime meditator
shared this experience
after years of fighting with my brother
over who was more successful
something shifted during one family gathering
I realized
there was no me that needed to prove anything
our whole rivalry just dissolved
now we're closer than ever
second genuine empathy naturally arises
without the barrier of a separate self
you directly experience others joy and suffering
as not separate from your own
compassion becomes less of an effort
and more of a natural response
the Dalai Lama explains it this way
third relationships become less needy
when you're not looking to others
to complete your sense of self
or validate your existence
connections become more authentic and less burdened
think about this
how many of your relationship problems
stem from seeking validation
recognition or completion from others
what if you approached relationships
without needing anything from them
just showing up fully present
research in psychology confirms this
studies show that the strongest relationships
aren't based on dependency
or completing each other
but on two whole people choosing to share their journey
fourth conflicts transform when there's no me to defend
disagreements stop being personal
you can disagree with someone without making them wrong
and you right you can even incorporate
their perspective into your understanding
creating something new together
as Thich Nhat Hanh reminds us in true dialogue
both sides are willing to change
this doesn't mean you become a doormat
or lose your boundaries actually
boundaries become clearer and healthier
because they're no longer emotionally charged
defenses of a fragile self
they're just practical parameters for interaction
but wait if there's no me running the show
who's going to remember to pick up the dry cleaning
who's going to show up for work on Monday
let's get practical about this whole no self business
now I know what you're thinking
this all sounds nice in theory Matt
but how does this actually work in real life
who gets up and goes to work if there's no me
who makes decisions who takes responsibility
these are great questions
and they bring us to the practical side of non self
the common misconception is that without a self
you just sit around doing nothing
or float aimlessly through life with no direction
but that's not at all what happens
as the Zen master Linji put it
the profound
simplicity of this teaching points to action
without the complication of a self centered narrative
the difference is in the who that's doing the action
or more accurately the absence of a who
so
what does this actually look like on a Tuesday morning
when you're stuck in traffic
your life continues
but without that extra layer of 'me-ness'
clogging everything up decisions still happen
but they arise from wisdom and conditions rather
than ego preferences
responsibilities are still fulfilled
often more effectively
because there's no self centered resistance to them
goals can still be pursued
but without the desperate attachment to outcomes
the Buddha himself
was incredibly active after his Enlightenment
teaching for 45 years establishing a monastic order
traveling extensively
clearly function doesn't stop when self dissolves
neuroscience gives us interesting insights here too
studies show that
when experienced meditators perform tasks
from a state of non self
their performance often improves
there's less second guessing
less performance anxiety
and more direct engagement with the task at hand
think about athletes in the zone
or musicians who become one with their instrument
they're functioning at their peak
precisely when the self steps out of the way
as the legendary basketball coach Phil Jackson
who incorporated Zen teachings into his coaching said
but what about morality if there's no me
what prevents harmful actions
this is where many people misunderstand non self
the realization of non self doesn't eliminate ethics
it transforms them
when you don't see yourself as separate from others
causing harm makes less and less sense
compassionate action emerges naturally
not because you should be good
but because you directly experience others suffering
as not separate from your own
The 8th century Buddhist master
Shantideva put it beautifully
so in practical terms
living from non self might look like working diligently
but without identifying as the hard working one
loving deeply but without possessiveness or need
creating art or music but without needing recognition
helping others
without seeing them as separate from yourself
it's not that personality disappears
it's more that you hold it lightly
like a costume
you can wear wholeheartedly without forgetting
you can take it off
you see your personality in the mirror of everyday life
but you no longer mistake the reflection
for who's doing the looking
you wear your identity
like an interesting mask at a party
fully engaged in the character
but secretly smiling at the game of it all
okay so we can still function without a solid me
great but the Buddha wasn't teaching this
just so we could be more effective at our jobs
he was pointing to something much bigger
we've talked about glimpses of non self
the freedom it brings how it transforms relationships
and how it works practically
but now let's explore what the Buddha considered
the ultimate purpose of this teaching
complete liberation
the Buddha didn't teach non self as an interesting
philosophical concept he taught it as medicine
for the fundamental disease of human existence
suffering
he recognized that at the root of all our suffering
lies this mistaken belief in a separate
permanent self
and when this illusion is completely seen through
something profound happens
in Buddhist terminology
this complete liberation is called Nirvana
literally meaning
blowing out like a flame being extinguished
but what's being extinguished isn't you
it's the illusion of a separate self
it's like
you've been wearing noise cancelling headphones
your entire life and suddenly they're removed
the world explodes into symphonic clarity
that was always there
as the Buddha said
so what actually changes
when this ultimate liberation occurs
first fear
especially fear of death dramatically transforms
when you deeply realize
there was never a permanent you to begin with
the terror of losing this you naturally subsides
death is still respected
but it's seen more as a transition than an end
the Tibetan Buddhist master
Dilgo Khyentse Rinpoche explained
second
suffering takes on a completely different quality
the Buddha never claimed that physical pain
would disappear with enlightenment
but he did teach that the mental suffering
we add to our experience the resistance
the aversion the craving
can completely cease
imagine experiencing life's challenges
without the added layer of
why is this happening to me
I don't deserve this
Doctor Mark Epstein a psychiatrist
who integrates Buddhist thinking with psychology
describes it as the freedom to be nobody
there's an incredible lightness
in not having to be somebody special all the time
third a natural joy emerges
not the excited grasping happiness we usually chase
but a profound contentment that's always available
regardless of external circumstances
the Thai Forest master Ajahn Chah
called it the peace that comes from letting go
fourth perception itself fundamentally shifts
the world doesn't change
but how you experience it transforms completely
instead of seeing separate objects and people
you directly perceive the interconnected
nature of everything
boundaries become permeable fluid
more like convenient designations
than ultimate realities
the contemporary teacher
Adyashanti describes it as the end of your world
not in an apocalyptic sense
but in the sense that the world
as you've constructed it falls away
revealing what was always here
but perhaps the most significant shift is this
the seeking finally stops
the constant feeling that something is missing
that you need to become something more
that fulfillment is around the next corner
comes to an end as the ancient Chan master Linji said
this doesn't mean you become passive or complacent
quite the opposite without the self centered filters
you're able to respond to life directly
spontaneously compassionately
without the hesitation and confusion that
comes from self concern
so what does all this mean for you
watching this right now
it means that this freedom
this peace
this clarity isn't something distant or theoretical
it's your birthright it's what you already are
when the illusion of a separate self falls away
as the Buddha said in his final teaching
so now let's wrap this all up with a mystery
that might just change everything
so we've explored what happens when you don't exist
we've seen how the self is more like a process
than a thing
how freedom emerges when this illusion is seen
through how relationships transform
how we can function practically
and the ultimate liberation this points toward
but here's the cosmic joke that the Buddha discovered
under the Bodhi Tree
the self spends its entire existence
desperately trying to
protect itself from something that never happens
because that self never truly existed
in the first place
it's like spending your life
afraid of monsters under the bed
and then one day finally looking underneath
only to discover there was never anything there
this leaves us with a profound mystery
if you're not who you think you are
then what's really living this life
if you're not your thoughts
they come and go while awareness remains
if you're not your emotions
they change constantly while awareness watches
if you're not your body
every cell is replaced over time
if you're not your memories or life story
which change and fade
then what are you the answer can't be put into words
because words and concepts are tools of the thinking
mind and this mystery lies beyond thinking
it can only be discovered through direct experience
by looking
deeply into the nature of your own awareness
as the great Zen master Huineng said
this isn't nihilism it's not saying nothing exists
it's pointing to a profound reality
beyond our conceptual frameworks
beyond the stories we tell about ourselves
the invitation of Buddhism isn't to believe in non
self as a concept
but to investigate your direct experience right now
to look deeply into this sense of I
and see what's really there
the Zen tradition calls this the great death
not the death of the body
but the death of the illusion of a separate self
and what's discovered through this great death
is what some traditions call
your original face what you were before you were born
what you've always been
beneath the costumes and masks of identity
I invite you to get curious about this
to wonder
to investigate not intellectually but experientially
what if you didn't have to wait for enlightenment
to experience freedom
what if you could taste it right now
by simply pausing and noticing that awareness
which is already present already complete
already free of a separate self
because when the illusion of you falls away
you stop surviving and start being
you stop performing and start living
as the contemporary teacher Rupert Spira puts it
I invite you to sit quietly for a moment
close your eyes if you're comfortable doing so
and simply notice
who or what is aware of your current experience
not what you're aware of
but what is this awareness itself
and I'll leave you with that question
to explore in your own time
because that exploration
is the heart of the Buddhist path
have you ever experienced a moment when you disappeared
share in the comments below
I read every single one
and would love to hear about your experiences
and remember the next time you find yourself stressed
anxious or caught in self concern
just pause and ask yourself
what happens when I don't exist
you might be surprised at the freedom
that question opens up
until next time stay curious
stay wise and remember
you might be less you than you think
and that's the best news you'll ever receive