[Music]
the teachings of epicus a former Roman
slave turned stoic philosopher and the
Buddha the founder of one of the world's
great religions may seem Worlds Apart at
first
glance but when we explore their
teachings we find surprising similarity
these two thinkers separated by time and
culture reached remarkably similar
conclusions about the human condition
and the path to Inner
Peace ever wondered what a Roman slave
and a prince born in Nepal might agree
on you know it's funny how life
sometimes brings together the most
unlikely pairs like peanut butter and
jelly or in this case a Roman slave and
an Indian prince who would have thought
could epicus be the stoic Buddha in this
video we'll explore the wisdom shared by
epicus and the Buddha we'll discover how
epictetus's stoic principles can serve
as a bridge for westerners to better
understand and appreciate Buddhist
teachings and how both Traditions offer
practical guidance for navigating life's
challenges with greater Clarity
resilience and
equinity as we compare the teachings of
these two great minds we find a wisdom
that is is timeless and
Universal their insights into desire
mental discipline and inner peace are
just as applicable today as they were
centuries
ago the eastwest
divide the notion of an unbridgeable
Chasm separating eastern and western
thought has long been a common
assumption westerners often point to
towering intellects like Socrates Plato
and Aristotle celebrating their emphasis
on reason logic and the Relentless
pursuit of knowledge the east in turn is
frequently characterized by its Rich
spiritual Traditions with Buddhism taism
and Hinduism all placing great emphasis
on intuition mindfulness and the
cultivation of inner
wisdom rard Kipling once wrote East is
East and West is West and never the
twain shall meet but what if I told you
that Kipling's geography teacher got it
wrong let's see how epicus and the
Buddha challenged this
notion this presumed dichotomy has led
many to conclude that the teachings of
eastern and western thinkers are
fundamentally
incompatible with little insight to
offer one another the wisdom of the
Buddha some might argue has no place in
the intellectual discourse of the West
while the logical arguments of Greek
philosophers seem ill suited to the
introspective practices of the
East however as we examine the lives and
ideas of epicus and the Buddha this
stark eastwest contrast begins to break
down their teachings reveal a shared
understanding of the human condition
that transcends cultural and Geographic
boundaries suggesting that the perceived
divide between eastern and western
thought thought may be more a product of
our own preconceptions than a reflection
of
reality slave and sage epicus and the
Buddha though separated by centuries and
cultures epicus and the Buddha shared a
journey from hardship to
wisdom epicus started as a slave in
ancient Rome while sidartha gatama the
future Buddha was born a prince in nepo
all despite their different Beginnings
both underwent profound transformations
to become two of history's most
influential
thinkers epicus whose very name means
acquired in Greek spent much of his
early life as the property of a wealthy
Roman Freedman yet even in the face of
the immense challenges and indignities
of slavery epicus discovered a path to
Inner Freedom through the study of stoic
philosophy he learned that true Liberty
lay not in external
circumstances but in one's ability to
master one's own mind and
emotions epicus once said it is
difficulties that show what men are
discourses
1.4.1 his own challenges as a slave
undoubtedly shaped his philosophy and
his emphasis on inner Freedom the Buddha
born sedara Gama lived a life of luxury
and ease as a young prince shielded from
the reality of human suffering however a
series of encounters with an old man a
sick man a corpse and a Wandering
aesthetic sparked a profound spiritual
crisis determined to find a solution to
the problem of suffering sidarthur
renounced his royal title and set out on
a path of aestheticism and
meditation both epicus and the Buddha
ultimately found Liberation through the
power of their own minds epicus
though he remained a slave for much of
his life discovered that true Freedom
lay in the cultivation of wisdom and
virtue the Buddha after years of
struggle and searching attained
Enlightenment under the bod tree
realizing the true nature of the mind
and the path to the cessation of
suffering Divergence and
Confluence epicus and the Buddha despite
their shared insights into The Human
Condition came came from different
philosophical and cultural
backgrounds stoicism epictetus's school
of thought is a Greek philosophy that
stresses reason logic and living in
harmony with
nature Buddhism on the other hand
originated in India and centers on the
nature of the Mind the roots of
suffering and the path to spiritual
Freedom stoic and Buddhist thoughts
differ in their metaphysical beliefs
stoics see the universe as a single
Divine entity governed by rational logos
while Buddhists emphasize impermanence
and reject the idea of a Supreme
Being I guess you could say that for
stoics the glass is half full with
Divine reason while for Buddhists the
glass is just a temporary vessel bound
to break someday but hey at least they
both agree that getting too attach to
the glass is a recipe for
disappointment yet despite these
different
epicus and the Buddha converged in their
understanding of the fundamental
challenges of human existence both
recognized the suffering that arises
from attachment to impermanent things
and the futility of seeking happiness in
external
circumstances they taught that true
peace and contentment can only be found
within through the cultivation of wisdom
self-discipline and
attachment in their teachings on the
nature of of Desire epic tetus and the
Buddha offer strikingly similar advice
both stress the significance of
distinguishing between what we can and
cannot control and focusing our energy
on the former they told us to let go of
our attachments to external outcomes and
cultivate inner contentment recognizing
that true happiness comes from
within governing desire skillful and
unskillful cognition
Central to the teachings of epicus and
the Buddha is the idea that our desires
and thoughts have a profound impact on
our happiness and
well-being both thinkers recognize that
not all desires are created equal and
that learning to distinguish between
skillful and unskillful desires is
essential to finding inner peace and
contentment the Buddha taught desire is
the root of suffering dapada
359 he recognized that our cravings and
aversions are often the source of our
discontent in Buddhist thought the term
tanha is often used to describe the kind
of craving or thirst that leads to
suffering but as the Buddhist scholar
Robert Morrison points out tanha is not
a condemnation of all desire but rather
a recognition of the fundamental human
condition of dissatisfaction that arises
from attachment to impermanent things
the Buddha explained that by learning to
recognize and and let go of unskillful
desires we can find Freedom from
suffering the same epicus taught that
our desires should be grounded in reason
and virtue rather than in the pursuit of
external Pleasures or
rewards he counseled his students to
focus their efforts on what is within
their control such as their own thoughts
and actions rather than on things
outside their control such as the
opinions of others or the vagaries of
Fortune
by cultivating wisdom and
self-discipline epic tetus believed that
we can learn to govern our desires and
find true
contentment epicus and the Buddha
acknowledged that cultivating skillful
desire and wise cognition is challenging
it demands persistent mindfulness
introspection and a Readiness to
confront our ingrained thought and
behavior patterns nevertheless both
philosophers provided practical methods
and tools for developing wisd wisdom and
inner peace such as the stoic practice
of
self-examination and the Buddhist
mindfulness of breathing
meditation bhist skillfulness and epican
internals one of the most striking
parallels between the teachings of
epicus and the Buddha lies in their
emphasis on the importance of
distinguishing between what is within
our control and what is not for epicus
this distinction was encapsulated in the
concept of internals and externals the
idea that our thoughts beliefs and
actions are within our power while
external events and the opinions of
others are ultimately beyond our control
epic tetus reminds us the chief task in
life is simply this to identify and
separate matters so that I can say
clearly to myself which are externals
not under my control and which have to
do with the choices I actually control
discourses
2.5.4 to
5 epic T is said that by focusing our
efforts on what is within our control we
can cultivate inner peace and Equanimity
even in the face of life's challenges
and
uncertainties he advised his students to
let go of their attachment to external
outcomes and instead focus on developing
wisdom virtue and self-mastery
epicus believed that we can become truly
free even if our external circumstances
remain
unchanged equally the Buddha taught that
true happiness and Liberation come from
within rather than from external
sources he emphasized the importance of
cultivating skillful mental States and
letting go of unskillful ones such as
greed hatred and delusion by developing
mindfulness compassion and wisdom the
Buddha believed that we can free
ourselves from the cycle of of suffering
and find lasting peace and
happiness the parallels between
epictetus's concept of internals and the
Buddha's emphasis on skillful mental
states are striking both thinkers
recognize that our happiness and
well-being ultimately depend on our own
minds rather than on external
circumstances they taught that by
cultivating inner peace wisdom and
self-discipline we can find Freedom
and
contentment even in the face of life's
challenges and
uncertainties the inward
turn epicus and the Buddha recognize
that the path to inner peace and
happiness begins with an inward turn a
shift in focus from the external world
to the inner landscape of our own
minds they taught that by cultivating
self-awareness introspection and mental
discipline we can begin to free
ourselves from the tyranny of our own
thoughts and emotions for epicus this
inward turn was encapsulated in the idea
of focusing on what is within our
control our own thoughts beliefs and
actions as explained just before epicus
believed that we can find true freedom
and happiness regardless of our external
circumstances it's like when you're
lying in bed at night and suddenly your
mind starts replaying that embarrassing
in thing you said in fifth grade epic
tetus and the Buddha would be the first
to tell you hey that's not in your
control anymore let it go and focus on
the
present in the same way the Buddha
taught that the key to Liberation from
suffering lies in understanding the
nature of our own
minds he encouraged his followers to
cultivate mindfulness to observe their
thoughts and emotions with Detachment
and clarity and to let go of unhealthy
mental States like craving and
aversion through this practice of
self-awareness and mental discipline the
Buddha believ that we can begin to see
through the illusions of the self and
find true Peace and Freedom both epicus
and the Buddha recognize that this
inward turn is not always easy it
requires courage honesty and a
willingness to confront the darker
aspects of our own minds yet both things
thinkers also emphasized that the
rewards of this inner work are
immeasurable a deeper sense of Peace
purpose and connection to ourselves and
others as we've explored the teachings
of epicus and the Buddha we've seen that
these two great thinkers though
separated by time and culture shared a
profound understanding of The Human
Condition both recognized that the path
to inner peace and happiness lies not in
external
circumstances but in the cultivation of
wisdom self-discipline and mental
clarity as the Buddha said Peace comes
from within do not seek it without
dapada
154 epicus echoed this sentiment when he
wrote it is not events that disturb
people it is their judgments concerning
them and cidian 5 their wisdom reminds
us that true happiness and peace lie
with within our own minds and hearts
comparing stoic and Buddhist thought
helps us Bridge the apparent divide
between eastern and western
traditions we can see that the
fundamental challenges of The Human
Experience the desire for happiness the
struggle with suffering the search for
meaning and purpose transcend cultural
and historical
boundaries in the teachings of epicus
and the Buddha we find a Timeless wisdom
that speaks to the heart of The Human
Condition
take the wisdom of epicus and the Buddha
into your life observe your thoughts and
emotions mindfully and clearly notice
when you fall into unhealthy patterns of
Desire or aversion and practice Letting
Go cultivate gratitude compassion and
equinity and watch your inner World
transform the journey toward inner peace
and happiness is is an ongoing process
not a final
destination it requires patience
perseverance and a willingness to keep
showing up even when things get
difficult but with the guidance of great
thinkers like epic tius and the Buddha
and the support of a community of fellow
Seekers we can all take steps towards a
more meaningful fulfilling and awakened
life
if you discovered something valuable in
this exploration of epicus the Buddha
and the parallels between stoicism and
Buddhism please share this video with
others who may be searching for wisdom
and
guidance and be sure to check out our
other videos where Matt and I explore
more fascinating topics related to
mindfulness personal growth and the Art
of Living
wisely leave a comment below to share
your own insights and exper experiences
and subscribe to Buddha's wisdom for
more content on mindfulness personal
growth and the Art of Living
wisely together we can learn from the
great minds of the past and create a
more compassionate awakened
future until next time stay present stay
resilient and keep seeking the wisdom
within namaste