[Music]
have you ever wished you could read
people's minds imagine the power of
knowing exactly what someone is thinking
well what if I told you that the Buddha
himself had techniques for doing just
that okay maybe not literally reading
minds but the Buddha did teach ways to
gain deep insight into the human mind
and behavior want to learn his secrets
I'm Matt and this is Buddha's wisdom
where ancient teachings meet modern
living
today we're going to explore a powerful
Buddhist tale about the Buddha's top
three techniques for understanding the
minds of others and our
own once upon a time in a small village
nestled at the foot of the Himalayas
there lived a young farmer named
Sanjay he was known throughout the
village for his diligence and his prized
possession a strong healthy Ox that
helped him plow his Fields One Day
sanj's neighbor Ravi came to him with a
request Sanjay my friend I hate to to
ask but my own Ox has fallen ill could I
please borrow yours for a few days to
plow my field I promis to return it
unharmed Sanji being a Kind and Generous
man agreed of course Ravi we're
neighbors after all just please take
good care of him Ravi greatfully took
the ox and set to work on his field but
after a few hours he noticed the ox
limping and refusing to pull the plow
worried Ravi returned the ox to Sanjay
immediately when Sanjay saw his beloved
Ox injured he was Furious he accused
Ravi of mistreating the animal and
demanded compensation for the Lost work
in Veterinary bills Ravi equally upset
denied any wrongdoing he insisted that
the ox must have already been hurt and
Sanjay was just looking for someone to
blame their argument grew heated drawing
the attention of the whole village each
Man became more entrenched in his own
perspective unable to see the situation
from the other's point of view just then
the Buddha was passing through the
village on his track travel s seeing the
commotion he approached the arguing men
with curiosity and compassion the Buddha
listened patiently observing the
situation with mindfulness he noticed
the anger and fear beneath sanj's
accusations and the defensiveness and
guilt behind ravi's denials with empathy
the Buddha imagined himself in each
man's position he felt sanj's
frustration at potentially losing his
livelihood and ravi's shame at being
accused of something he didn't do
finally
the Buddha spoke my friends I sense that
there is more to this story than meets
the eye Sanjay I can feel your worry
about providing for your family without
your ox and Ravi I can understand the
pain of being blamed for something
unfairly both men paused surprised at
the Buddha's Insight the Buddha
continued What If instead of arguing
about who is right and wrong we focused
on finding a solution that helps you
both sanj
what do you really need in this
situation Sanjay thought for a moment I
suppose I just need my Ox to be healthy
so I can work my land and feed my family
the Buddha nodded and turned to Ravi and
Ravi what do you truly want Ravi sighed
I don't want to be seen as a liar or a
thief I borrowed the ox in good faith
and returned it as soon as I noticed it
was
injured the Buddha smiled it seems to me
that you both want the same thing to be
seen as good honest men who are doing
your best to survive what if Ravi helps
Sanjay care for the ox until it heals
and in exchange Sanjay allows Ravi to
use the ox for his field once it
recovers that way you both get what you
need and no one is Accused
unfairly Sanjay and Ravi looked at each
other their anger slowly melting into
understanding they agreed to the
Buddha's suggestion and thanked him for
his wise
counsel as the Buddha continued on his
journey he reflected on the power of
mindfulness empathy and non-judgment to
transform conflicts and reveal the
Hidden Truths of the human heart by
simply being present and seeing Beyond
surface appearances he was able to guide
the two men from opposition to
cooperation and that my friends is the
essence of the Buddha's mind reading
techniques not some Supernatural power
but the profound ability to observe
without
judgment understand with compassion and
respond with
wisdom now let's look deeper at how the
Buddha used his mindreading techniques
of mindfulness empathy and non-judgment
to untangle this conflict when the
Buddha first approached Sanji and Ravi
he didn't immediately jump to
conclusions or take sides instead he
listened mindfully giving his full
attention to each man's words and the
emotions behind
them with Sanjay he noticed the anger
and accusation in his tone but also the
underlying fear Sanjay was worried about
his livelihood his ability to provide
for his loved ones his Ox was more than
just an animal to him it was his partner
in survival and with Ravi the Buddha
picked up on the defensiveness and the
hint of guilt Ravi truly believed he had
done nothing wrong but he also carried
the weight of being seen as a bad
neighbor a man whose word couldn't be
trusted the Buddha held these
observations without judgment he didn't
get caught up in deciding who was right
or wrong instead he looked deeper to the
root of the conflict too scared proud
men who both wanted to be seen as good
and
honorable with this understanding the
Buddha could tap into empathy he
imagined himself in each man's Place
feeling the sting of a threat to his
reputation the desperation of
potentially losing his source of income
he recognized that beneath the surface
these men were more alike than different
from this place of empathetic wisdom the
solution arose naturally to find a way
to meet both men's deeper needs by
suggesting that Ravi helped care for the
injured ox and then borrow it again once
it healed the buddha showed the men a
path where they could both get what they
wanted without shame or blame in the end
it was mindfulness that allowed the
Buddha to see clearly empathy that
allowed him to understand deeply and
nonjudgment that allowed him to craft a
wise and compassionate
solution we can all learn from the
Buddha's example in our own conflicts
and relationships we can practice
pausing and observing before reacting
we can ask ourselves what's really going
on beneath the surface here what is this
person feeling and needing and we can
challenge ourselves to let go of
simplistic judgments and instead embrace
the complex messy beautiful human
reality in front of
us I remember a time in my own life when
I was locked in a bitter argument with a
friend we were both so convinced that we
were right and the other was wrong it
felt like an impossible impass but then
I remembered the Buddha's teachings I
took a step back and just observed my
own feelings and thoughts without
judgment I tried to imagine what my
friend must be feeling too and suddenly
The Way Forward became clear I realized
that beneath our disagreement we both
just wanted to feel respected and
understood by shifting my focus to
meeting those deeper needs we were able
to find a resolution that worked for
both of
us that's the power of these mind
reading techniques they're not about
magically knowing exactly what someone
is thinking
they're about learning to look beneath
the surface to understand with
compassion and to respond with wisdom
and the best part these are skills
anyone can learn with practice you can
become a master of understanding
yourself and others imagine how that
could transform your relationships your
career your entire life you'd be like a
Buddha in the modern world spreading
peace and understanding wherever you go
so my friends that's the tale of the
Buddha the feuding farmers and the path
to profound understanding I hope this
story and its lessons inspire you to
cultivate your own inner
Buddha remember mindfulness allows you
to see clearly empathy allows you to
understand deeply and non-judgment
allows you to respond wisely these are
the keys to unlock the mysteries of the
human mind and
heart if you enjoyed this deep dive into
the Buddha's wisdom hit that like button
and share this video with someone who
could use a fresh perspective on the art
of understanding
and don't forget to subscribe for more
enlightening content every
week thank you for joining me on this
journey of Discovery as always I'm
honored to be your guide on the path of
wisdom and Awakening until next time may
you meet every moment with mindfulness
may you see every being with compassion
and may you touch every life with the
light of your understanding be well my
friends and be the
light for