[Music]
all right folks riddle me this what do a
prince an old man and a corpse have in
common no it's not the start of a bad
joke these are actually the key players
in the incredible story of how one man
went from living in the lap of luxury to
becoming the Buddha the awakened one as
the Buddha himself said the mind is
everything what you think you
become so grab a cushion cross your legs
and let's dive into the life of the
Buddha and the mind blowing events that
transformed him from a sheltered Prince
to a spiritual
superhero our story kicks off in lumini
Nepal around the fifth or 6th Century
bcee Prince sidartha Gama was born into
a life of privilege thanks to his doting
dad King
sudana The King was determined to keep
his son from experiencing any kind of
suffering so he basically bubble wrapped
the prince's life with every luxury
imaginable shielding him from the
realities of Aging illness and
death but at the ripe old age of 29
sidartha decided it was time to pop that
bubble and see what the real world had
to
offer and boy did he get a reality
check on his eye-opening adventures
outside the palace sidartha had a front
row seat to the harsh truths of Life
known as the four sights first he met an
elderly man bent with age then he saw a
sick person their body ravaged by
disease next he stumbled Upon A corpse a
blunt reminder of life's
impermanence finally he encountered an
aesthetic a Wandering holy man who had
renounced worldly possessions in search
of spiritual truth as the Buddha later
reflected the root of suffering is
attachment these experiences hit
sidartha like a ton of karma shattering
his Rose tinted glasses and setting him
on a quest to find a way out of
suffering faced with these hard truths
sidartha made a decision that would make
even the most adventurous of us think
twice at 29 he left behind his plush
Palace his gorgeous wife and his
adorable baby boy to become a Wandering
Monk on a mission to unlock the secrets
of the universe talk about a midlife
crisis for the next 6 years sidartha
threw himself into the world of extreme
asceticism he sought out the most
renowned spiritual teachers of his time
hoping to find the key to
Liberation first he studied with Alara k
a master of meditation who taught him
how to reach deep states of
concentration known as the sphere of
nothingness but even in these profound
meditative States sidartha realized that
true freedom from suffering eluded him
next he apprenticed with udaka raputa
who guided him to an even more refined
level of meditation called the sphere of
neither perception nor nonp
perception this was a state of such
subtlety that it was hard to even
describe yet despite mastering these
Advanced Techniques sidartha still felt
a gnawing sense that he had not reached
the end of the
path frustrated but determined sidhartha
left these teachers and set out on his
own pushing himself to the brink of
starvation and subjecting himself to
intense physical hardships as he would
later teach to enjoy good health to
bring true happiness to one's family to
bring peace to all one must first
discipline and control one's own
mind at his lowest point sidhartha was a
mere shadow of his former self he had
pushed himself to the very edge of human
endurance but still the answers he
sought eluded him it was in this moment
of utter desolation that a memory from
his childhood surfaced a memory of
naturally falling into a state of deep
meditation
as he recalled the peace and Clarity he
had experienced a profound realization
dawned on him the path to Enlightenment
was not to be found in the extremes of
indulgence or deprivation but in the
middle way a balanced approach that
avoided both excess and
asceticism with this understanding
sidartha mustered his last ounce of
strength and set out to find a quiet
place to meditate determined to give his
Quest For Truth one final chance
for 49 days and nights sidartha sat
beneath the bod tree locked in an
intense Battle of the mind he faced down
Mara the demon of Illusion and desire
and met each of his attacks with the
shield of mindfulness and the sword of
wisdom on the 49th day as the morning
star appeared in the sky sidartha
finally attained complete and perfect
Enlightenment becoming the Buddha the
awakened one his mind was liberated from
the shackles of suffering his heart
filled with boundless compassion for all
beings and that my friends was just the
beginning for the next 45 years the
Buddha traveled far and wide sharing his
teachings on the path to Liberation with
anyone who would listen he taught the
four noble truths the essence of his
wisdom that life is suffering that
suffering arises from attachment that
it's possible to end suffering and that
the the path to Freedom is the
eight-fold path of right understanding
thought speech action livelihood effort
mindfulness and
concentration he championed the
middleway encouraging his followers to
find balance and avoid extremes and he
created a community of monks and nuns
the S to carry on his teachings after he
was
gone as the Buddha famously said
thousands of candles can be lighted from
a single candle and the life of the
candle will not be shortened happiness
never decreases by being
shared now you might be thinking wait a
minute Matt was sidartha Gama the only
Buddha great
question the short answer is no but the
full story is a bit more complex you see
the word Buddha means awakened one and
it refers to anyone who has attained
full Enlightenment and broken free from
the cycle of rebirth
Buddhist scriptures tell us that there
have been many Buddhas in the past and
that there will be many more in the
future in fact Buddhists believe that a
future Buddha named mraa will appear
when sidartha Gama's teachings have
faded from memory and in Mahayana
Buddhism there's even a whole path
dedicated to becoming a Buddha called
The bodhisatwa
Path but why is sidartha gotama the most
famous Buddha well it's because his life
story and teachings have been the most
well preserved and WID ly spread he's
the one who set The Wheel of Dharma in
motion for our current age and his
insights have profoundly influenced the
lives of countless people over the
centuries but hey the tale of past and
future Buddhas is a story for another
[Music]
day we'll be diving into that
mind-bending topic in a future video so
make sure to stay tuned and hit that
subscribe button to join us on that
Journey for now just remember that while
sidartha gotama may be the most
well-known Buddha he's part of a much
larger tapestry of Awakened
beings his story is a powerful reminder
that each of us has the potential to
awaken to our true nature and find
lasting freedom and who knows maybe one
day countless eons from now you and I
might just become Buddhas
ourselves you know folks learning about
the Buddha's life and teachings has had
a profound impact on my own Journey
there was a time in my life when I felt
like I was stuck in a rut chasing after
one fleeting pleasure after another but
never feeling truly fulfilled it was
like I was on a hamster wheel of stress
and dissatisfaction and I didn't know
how to get off but then I stumbled upon
the Buddha's story and it was like a
light bulb went off in my head his
message of finding balance letting go of
attachments and cultivating mindfulness
resonated with me on a deep level I
started incorporating meditation into my
daily routine and slowly but surely I
began to feel a shift in my
perspective instead of constantly
grasping for more I learned to
appreciate the simple joys in life I
became more present in my relationships
more compassionate towards myself and
others and more resilient in the face of
challenges and while I'm still a work in
progress I can honestly say that the
Buddha's teachings have helped me find a
greater sense of Peace purpose and
happiness in fact this channel Buddha's
wisdom was was born out of my own
transformative experience with the
Buddha's
teachings my good friend Peter and I
both felt so inspired by the Dharma that
we wanted to share it with as many
people as possible we knew that there
were countless others out there who like
us were searching for a deeper sense of
meaning and connection in their lives so
we decided to create this channel as a
way to spread the Buddha's Timeless
wisdom in a way that's both entertaining
and
accessible our hope is that through our
videos we can help Spark Mark a similar
journey of Awakening in our viewers and
create a community of like-minded
seekers who can support and Inspire each
other along the way so my wise friends
if you're feeling stuck lost or
unfulfilled know that you're not
alone the Buddha's teachings have the
power to transform lives just as they've
transformed mine and Peter's and we're
here to walk that path with you every
step of the way I encourage you to
explore the Buddha's story and teachings
for yourself dive into our videos
meditate with us and share your own
insights and experiences in the
comments together we can create a ripple
effect of wisdom and compassion that
extends far beyond our individual
lives and if you want to be a part of
this growing community of seekers be
sure to hit that subscribe button and
join us on this epic adventure of
Awakening trust me your future self will
thank you so until next time my friends
stay curious stay compassionate and keep
walking the path to Liberation and
remember as the Buddha said with our
thoughts we make the world let's make it
a world of wisdom love and endless
possibility
[Music]