[Music]
Hey, what's up wisdom seekers? Matt here
from Buddha's Wisdom and we're back with
another pure reading from the
Dharmapata.
We've covered chapters 1- 10 and today
we're continuing with chapters 11- 15.
These next five chapters cover aging,
the self, the world, the Buddha, and
happiness.
Like before, I'll read these verses
uninterrupted, letting this ancient
wisdom speak directly to you. You can
follow along with the text on screen or
simply listen. Peter will break down
everything we cover today in next week's
video, and I'll be back soon with more
chapters from this incredible text.
So, find a quiet spot, take a deep
breath, and let's begin.
[Music]
Chapter 11. Old age faces the reality of
aging and impermanence. The Buddha shows
us how understanding our mortality can
lead to greater wisdom and freedom.
What laughter, what pleasure is there
when the world is ablaze, shrouded in
darkness. Will you not seek a lamp?
Look upon this beautified body, a mass
of soores, a heaped up lump, diseased,
much thought of in which nothing lasts,
nothing persists.
This body is worn out, a nest of disease
and fragile. This foul mass breaks up
for death is the end of life.
What delight is there for one who sees
these dove-led bones that are cast away
like gourds in the autumn.
Of bones is this house made plastered
over with flesh and blood. Herein are
stored decay and death, pride and
hypocrisy.
Even the gorgeous royal chariots wear
out. And indeed this body too wears out,
but the dhamma of the good does not wear
out. Thus the good proclaim it to the
good.
The person of little learning grows old
like a bull. His bulk increases but his
wisdom does not grow.
Through many a birth I wandered in
samsara, seeking but not finding the
builder of this house. Painful is birth
again and again.
Oh housebuilder, you are seen. You will
not build this house again. All your
rafters are broken. Your ridge pole is
shattered. The mind has attained the
unconditioned. Achieved is the end of
craving.
Those who have not practiced celibacy
and have not acquired wealth in their
youth perish like old herands in a lake
without fish.
Those
who have not practiced celibacy and have
not acquired wealth in their youth lie
like worn out arrows sighing over the
past.
[Music]
Chapter 12. Self teaches us about
personal responsibility and
self-control.
The Buddha shows that we are our own
refuge and that real change comes from
mastering ourselves.
If one holds oneself dear, one should
diligently watch oneself. Let the wise
person keep vigil during any of the
three watches.
One should first establish oneself in
what is proper. Then only should one
instruct others. Such a wise person will
not be reproached.
If one would do as one teaches others,
then being well controlled oneself, one
could control others. Indeed,
self-control is difficult.
One is one's own refuge. Who else could
be the refuge? With oneself fully
controlled, one obtains a refuge which
is hard to obtain.
The evil done by oneself, born of
oneself, produced by oneself, crushes
the foolish one, as a diamond breaks a
hard gem.
One whose evil conduct is very extensive
spreads over oneself like a creeping
vine spreads over a tree. Easy
to do are things that are bad and
harmful to oneself. What is beneficial
and good is extremely difficult to do.
The foolish person who scorns the rule
of the venerable ones, of the noble ones
who live according to the dharma, and
follows false doctrine, fruits like the
bamboo, to its own destruction.
By oneself is evil done. By oneself is
one defiled. By oneself is evil left
undone. By oneself is one made pure.
Purity and impurity depended on oneself.
No one can purify another.
Let one not neglect one's own welfare
for the sake of anothers. However great,
clearly understanding one's own welfare,
let one be intent upon the good.
[Music]
Chapter 13. The world teaches us how to
live wisely while engaging with the
world around us. The Buddha shows us how
to see through appearances and avoid
being trapped by illusions.
Do not follow ignoble ways. Do not live
in heedlessness. Do not follow false
views. Do not be a friend of the world.
Arise. Do not be heedless.
Follow the righteous way of life. He who
practices righteousness lives happily
both in this world and the next.
Follow the righteous way of life. Do not
follow that which is unrighteous. The
righteous live happily both in this
world and the next.
One who regards this world as a bubble,
as a mirage, one who looks upon the
world in this way, the king of death
does not see.
Come, look at this world which is like a
decorated royal chariot. Here fools
flounder, but for the wise there is no
attachment.
Whoever having been heedless is heedless
no longer illuminates this world like
the moon when freed from clouds.
Whoever by a good deed covers the evil
done illuminates this world like the
moon when freed from clouds.
This world is blind. Few are those who
clearly see. Like birds escaping from
the net. Few go to realms of bliss.
Swans fly on the path of the sun. Men
with psychic powers travel through
space. The wise are led away from the
world. Having conquered Mara and his
host.
For a liar who has violated the one law,
who holds in scorn the world beyond,
there is no evil he will not do.
The miserly do not go to the realm of
the gods. Fools indeed do not praise
generosity, but the wise person delights
in generosity and through it becomes
blissful in the other world.
Better than soul sovereignty over the
earth, better than going to heaven,
better than even lordship over all the
worlds, is the super mundane fruition of
stream entrance.
[Music]
Chapter 14. The Buddha describes the
qualities of one who has reached
complete awakening. These verses show us
what becomes possible when someone
achieves full liberation.
One whose victory cannot be turned into
defeat. Whom none of the conquered in
this world can follow. By what track can
you trace that Buddha, the awakened, the
omnisient, the trackless?
One who has no craving, the stream that
drags one along to trap him. By what
track can you trace that Buddha, the
awakened, the omnisient, the trackless?
Those wise ones who are devoted to
meditation, who delight in the calm of
renunciation, such mindful, perfect
Buddhas even the gods hold dear.
Hard is it to be born a human being.
Hard is the life of mortals. Hard is it
to gain access to the true dharma and
hard to encounter is the arising of the
Buddhas.
To avoid all evil, to cultivate good and
to cleanse one's mind. This is the
teaching of the Buddhas.
Patient endurance is the supreme
austerity.
Nibbana is supreme. Say the Buddhas. He
is not a true monk who harms another nor
a true renunciate who oppresses others.
Not insulting, not harming. Restraint
according to the fundamental precepts.
Moderation in food, dwelling in
solitude, devotion to meditation. This
is the teaching of the Buddhas.
Not by a shower of gold coins can
sensual desires be satisfied. Sensual
desires are of little sweetness and much
pain. Knowing this, the wise man
finds no delight even in heavenly
pleasures. The disciple of the supreme
Buddha delights in the destruction of
craving.
Driven only by fear, men go for refuge
to many places, to hills, woods, groves,
trees, and shrines.
Such indeed is no safe refuge. Such is
not the refuge supreme. Not by resorting
to such a refuge is one released from
all suffering.
He who has gone for refuge to the
Buddha, the teaching and his order,
penetrates with transcendental wisdom
the four noble truths.
The suffering, the cause of suffering,
the sessation of suffering, and the
noble eight-fold path leading to the
sessation of suffering.
This indeed is the safe refuge. This is
the refuge supreme. Having gone to such
a refuge, one is released from all
suffering.
Hard to find is the thoroughbred man. He
is not born everywhere. Where such a
wise one is born, that clan thrives
happily.
Blessed is the birth of the Buddhas.
Blessed is the enunciation of the sacred
teaching. Blessed is the harmony and the
order. And blessed is the spiritual
pursuit of the united truth seeker.
He who pays homage to such as have
transcended all and crossed the flood,
whose passions are extinguished, and for
whom there is no more rebirth.
The merit gained by such homage cannot
be measured by anyone.
Chapter 15. Happiness reveals the
Buddha's teaching on true contentment.
These verses show us that real happiness
comes from inner peace rather than
external circumstances.
Let us live happily then, not hating
those who hate us. Among those who hate,
let us dwell free from hatred.
Let us live happily then, free from
ailments among the ailing. Among those
who are ailing, let us dwell free from
ailments.
Let us live happily then, free from
attachment among those who are attached.
Among those who are attached, let us
dwell free from attachment.
Let us live happily then, though we call
nothing our own. We shall be like the
bright gods feeding on happiness.
Victory breeds hatred for the conquered
is unhappy. He who has given up both
victory and defeat, he the contented is
happy.
There is no fire like greed, no crime
like hatred, no sorrow like separation,
no happiness like peace.
Health is the greatest gift, contentment
the greatest wealth, faithfulness the
best relationship. Nibbana is the
greatest happiness.
Having tasted the sweetness of solitude
and peace, one becomes free from fear
and sin, while drinking the sweetness of
the joy of truth.
It is good to see noble ones, to live
with them as always happiness. If one
does not see fools, one will be
continually happy.
Indeed, he who moves in the company of
fools grieavves for longing. Association
with fools is always painful, like
partnership with an enemy. But
association with the wise is joyful,
like meeting with kinfolk.
Therefore, one ought to follow the wise,
the intelligent, the learned, the much
enduring, the dutiful, the noble ones.
One ought to follow a good and wise
person as the moon follows the path of
the stars.
There you have it. Five more chapters
from the Dharmapata covering aging,
self-mastery, navigating the world,
understanding awakening, and finding
true happiness.
Peter will be back next week to break
down the deeper meanings and practical
applications of everything we covered
today. I'll be back soon with more
chapters from this incredible text.
We're only halfway through the complete
Dharmapata.
If any of these verses resonated with
you, drop a comment below and let me
know which one hit home.
This is Matt from Buddha's Wisdom.
Thanks for taking this journey through
these timeless teachings with me. Stay
curious. Stay wise.