Have you ever had the sneaking suspicion
that everything you thought was real
might just be an illusion? What if I
told you that your sense of self, the
objects you interact with, and even the
very nature of experience itself, are
all empty of inherent existence?
It sounds like the plot of a sci-fi
movie, but it's actually one of the most
profound insights of Buddhist
philosophy. Get ready to have your mind
blown as we explore the concept of
emptiness and how it can transform your
entire world view.
Hey there fellow wisdom seekers. It's
your favorite truth exploring buddy Matt
back with another mindexpanding video.
Today we're tackling one of the most
fascinating and challenging ideas in all
of Buddhism. Shunyata or emptiness. Now
before you start thinking this is some
bleak nihilistic philosophy, let me
assure you that emptiness is far from
meaningless. In fact, understanding
shunyata can be a liberating experience
that frees you from the mental traps
that keep you stuck in suffering.
Throughout the history of Buddhist
thought, there have been at least five
distinct meanings of emptiness. each one
building upon the last to create a
comprehensive view of reality that will
shatter your assumptions and open up new
possibilities for awakening.
In this video, we'll explore each of
these five aspects of Shunya in depth
using vivid examples and thought
experiments to help you grasp these
mindbending concepts. So, grab your
favorite beverage, settle in, and get
ready to have your reality turned upside
down.
Chapter 1. No subject.
Our journey begins with the teachings of
the Buddha himself. In the Sunny Suda,
he drops a bombshell on his unsuspecting
audience. The world, he says, is empty
of self and anything belonging to self.
Let that sink in for a moment.
The very sense of eye that we cling to
so tightly, that feels so solid and
real, is actually nowhere to be found in
our experience.
To illustrate this point, the Buddha
uses the analogy of a musical
performance. When you listen to music,
there's the musician, the instrument,
and the sound itself. These three
elements come together to create the
experience of music. But can you find a
separate independent self that's making
it all happen? Try as you might, you
won't be able to locate it. The music
arises from a complex web of causes and
conditions, not from some unchanging
essence. The same is true for our
experience of the world. When we examine
it closely, we find that there's no
solid permanent self at the center of it
all. Our thoughts, feelings, and
perceptions are constantly changing,
arising and passing away based on
various conditions. The self we cling to
so tightly is really just a convenient
fiction, a way of organizing experience
that has no ultimate reality. To further
illustrate this idea, let's use the
metaphor of a rainbow. When you see a
beautiful rainbow stretching across the
sky, it appears to be a solid
independent thing. But when you try to
locate the rainbow, you'll find that
it's not actually there in any fixed
permanent sense. It's an appearance that
arises due to specific causes and
conditions like sunlight, water
droplets, and the position of the
observer. The rainbow is empty of
inherent existence, just like the self.
Another example is the character in a
dream. When you're dreaming, the you in
the dream appears to be real and solid.
But upon waking, you realize that this
dream self was just a temporary
appearance, a product of your sleeping
mind.
In the same way, our waking sense of
self is a kind of dream, an appearance
that arises due to various causes and
conditions, but lacks any ultimate
independent reality.
This might sound unsettling at first,
but it's actually a liberating insight.
When we start to see through the
illusion of a separate self, we can let
go of a lot of the anxiety, attachment,
and aversion that comes with it. we can
start to experience life in a more open,
fluid, and compassionate way.
Chapter 2, no object.
But the Buddha's teachings on emptiness
don't stop at the self.
The great Buddhist philosopher Nagarjuna
takes things a step further, pointing
out that even the objects of our
experience are empty of inherent
existence. Let's use this very video as
an example. As you watch it, you might
assume that you're perceiving a distinct
independent thing called this video. But
if we start to examine it more closely,
we'll see that it's actually a complex
web of interconnected phenomena.
There's the script I'm reading from, the
pixels on your screen, the sound waves
coming out of your speakers, the
concepts and ideas being conveyed, the
platform it's hosted on, the device
you're watching it on, and even the vast
network of causes and conditions that
led to its creation, like the invention
of language, the development of digital
technology, and the entire history of
human culture. When we really dig into
it, we find that there's no solid
independent thing called this video that
exists apart from everything else. It's
all a fluid, everchanging process, a
dance of interdependent elements that we
label and conceptualize for convenience.
The same is true for any object of our
experience, from the simplest sensation
to the most complex abstract idea. To
understand this emptiness of objects
more concretely, think of a delicious
meal at a restaurant. When you're eating
the meal, it appears to be a distinct
independent thing. The pasta, the sauce,
the flavors all seem to exist in and of
themselves. But if you start to look
more closely, you'll see that the meal
is actually a complex web of
interconnected phenomena. The
ingredients that were grown and
harvested, the chef who prepared the
dish, the cultural traditions that
shaped the recipe, the economic systems
that allowed the restaurant to exist,
and so on. The meal, like any object, is
empty of inherent existence, dependent
on an infinite network of causes and
conditions.
This might sound a bit abstract, but it
has profound implications for how we
relate to the world. When we start to
see the emptiness of things, we can let
go of a lot of the grasping and aversion
that comes from taking them too
seriously. We can appreciate the fluid,
interconnected nature of reality and
find a sense of ease and freedom in the
midst of constant change.
[Music]
Chapter 3. No subject and object. So
far, we've seen how both the subject and
object of experience are empty of
inherent existence. But the Yoga School
of Buddhism takes things even further,
pointing out that the very distinction
between subject and object is itself an
illusion.
Think about the experience of perceiving
the color red. In our ordinary way of
thinking, there's a separate you who is
seeing an independent redness out there.
But the yoga argue that this dualistic
way of framing experience is
fundamentally mistaken.
In reality, the redness and the seeing
of redness are completely
interdependent, arising together as a
single seamless experience. It's like
two sides of the same coin. You can't
have a coin with only heads or only
tails. The two sides depend on each
other for their very existence. In the
same way, you can't have a perceiver
without something perceived or an object
of perception without a perceiving
consciousness. The two are mutually
dependent, arising together in a single
indivisible moment of experience. To
illustrate this nonduality of subject
and object, imagine you're walking in a
beautiful forest. In the traditional way
of thinking, there's a separate you who
is experiencing the forest as a separate
object. But in the moment of direct
experience, is there really a separation
between you and the forest? The colors,
sounds, and smells of the forest are
arising in your consciousness, and your
consciousness is taking the shape of the
forest. The two are interpenetrating and
defining each other, like a dance in
which the dancer and the dance are one.
Or think of the experience of falling in
love. When you're in love, the
traditional boundaries between self and
others seem to dissolve. You feel a
sense of union and intimacy with your
beloved, as if your two hearts and minds
were merging into one. This is a taste
of the non-dual nature of experience in
which the rigid separation between
subject and object softens and yields to
a more fluid interconnected way of
being. This non-dual view of experience
has some mindbending implications. It
means that the fundamental nature of
reality is not some collection of
separate independent things but rather a
fluid seamless hole in which all the
elements interpenetrate and define each
other. So when we talk about emptiness
in the context of Buddha nature we're
pointing to the inherent freedom and
wholeness of our true being.
We're not separate isolated entities but
rather expressions of the vast open
awareness that is the very nature of
reality itself.
And just as the images on a movie screen
are temporary appearances that arise and
pass away, our sense of being a separate
self is also a kind of projection, a
convincing illusion created by the mind.
When we start to see through this
illusion and touch the luminous
awareness that we truly are, we discover
a profound sense of liberation and inner
peace. This isn't something that we need
to achieve or create. It's the very
nature of what we are beneath the layers
of confusion and conditioning.
And by learning to rest in this pure
awareness, we gradually dissolve the
false sense of separation between
ourselves and the world and awaken to
the unity and interdependence of all
things. Of course, this doesn't mean
that we bypass or ignore the challenges
and complexities of life. Rather, it
means that we meet them from a place of
greater wisdom, openness, and
compassion.
We still engage fully with the world,
but we do so with a sense of lightness
and flexibility, knowing that all
experiences are fleeting expressions of
the endlessly creative dance of
awareness.
Chapter 5. No views. Now, just when you
thought you had a handle on emptiness,
Buddhism throws one final curveball. The
idea that all views, even the most
profound spiritual insights, are
themselves empty of inherent existence.
This is the radical claim of the
emptiness of views teachings which
suggests that any conceptual framework
or belief system we use to understand
reality is ultimately just a provisional
tool not the final truth. Even the
Buddha's own teachings as profound and
transformative as they may be are empty
of inherent existence mere fingers
pointing at the moon of ultimate
reality.
The danger of getting attached to views,
even Buddhist ones, is that it can lead
to dogmatism, closed-mindedness, and a
kind of spiritual materialism where we
use our beliefs to bolster the ego
rather than dissolve it. We might start
to identify with being a Buddhist or a
meditator and use that identity to feel
superior to others or avoid the messy
unpredictable reality of life as it
actually is. To illustrate the emptiness
of views, consider again the metaphor of
the movie screen. The teachings and
concepts we use to understand reality
are like the images projected onto the
screen. They can be informative,
inspiring, or thoughtprovoking, but they
are not the screen itself. They are
temporary appearances, useful tools for
guiding us towards a direct experience
of the ultimate nature of reality. Just
as we wouldn't confuse a map for the
actual territory it represents, we must
be careful not to mistake our views and
beliefs for reality itself, even the
most sublime spiritual teachings are
ultimately empty of inherent existence,
mere fingers pointing at the moon of
truth. This might sound a bit
disorienting at first, as if we're
pulling the rug out from under all our
cherished beliefs and assumptions. But
the emptiness of views is actually a
profoundly liberating teaching, one that
frees us from the tyranny of dogma and
fixed ideas. When we recognize that all
views are empty, we can engage with them
more playfully and flexibly, using them
as tools for awakening rather than as
fixed positions to defend.
We can appreciate the relative truth of
different perspectives without getting
trapped in any one of them. and we can
rest more easily in the groundlessness
of our own being, trusting the inherent
wisdom and compassion of our Buddha
nature to guide us through the
complexities of life. Ultimately, the
emptiness of views points us back to the
simplicity and immediiacy of our own
direct experience. It invites us to let
go of our reliance on conceptual
frameworks and trust the intelligence of
the present moment. And it reminds us
that the ultimate truth is always right
here in the midst of the everanging
dance of appearances, waiting for us to
recognize it as our own true nature.
We've covered a lot of ground in this
video, exploring the five main aspects
of emptiness in Buddhism. The lack of an
inherent self, the emptiness of objects,
the nonduality of subject and object,
the Buddha nature within us, and the
emptiness of all views.
It's a lot to take in and it can be
pretty mind-bending at first, but I hope
this exploration has given you a taste
of the profound implications of
emptiness for our understanding of
ourselves and the world. Emptiness isn't
about nihilism or meaninglessness. It's
about seeing through our limited,
conditioned ways of perceiving reality
and awakening to the fluid,
interconnected, and ultimately
inconceivable nature of things. It's a
teaching that can transform our
relationship to ourselves, others, and
the world, opening up new possibilities
for wisdom, compassion, and freedom. But
don't take my word for it. The real
power of these teachings lies in
exploring them for yourself in your own
direct experience. The Buddha himself
encouraged us to be lamps unto
ourselves, to test out the teachings and
see if they hold up in the laboratory of
our own lives. So, I invite you to take
these ideas and run with them, to play
with them in your own experience and see
what new insights and awakenings emerge.
As we navigate the ups and downs of
life, we can use these teachings as a
kind of compass, guiding us back to the
spaciousness and clarity of our true
nature. When we get caught up in the
solidity and drama of our thoughts and
emotions, we can remember the rainbow
and the clouds and let them dissolve
into the open sky of awareness. When we
feel isolated and disconnected, we can
remember the pasta and the music and
feel our deep interbeing with all
things. And when we get attached to our
ideas and opinions, we can remember the
movie screen and the projector and hold
our views more lightly. Ultimately, the
teachings on emptiness are an invitation
to let go of our limited conditioned
ways of seeing and being and to relax
into the vast, open, and luminous nature
of reality itself. It's a journey of
discovery and awakening that we're all
on together. A dance of wisdom and
compassion that has no beginning or end.
So keep exploring, keep questioning, and
keep opening to the incredible mystery
and beauty of this life. And remember,
the truth you seek is always right here,
shining in the heart of your own
awareness.
It's not something distant or abstract,
but the very ground of your being, the
source and substance of all that you
experience. If this journey into the
heart of emptiness has inspired you, I
invite you to like this video, subscribe
to our channel, and share this teaching
with anyone who might be ready for a
radical shift in perspective.
Thank you for joining me on this wild
and wonderful ride through the world of
Shunyata. May these teachings be of
benefit to you and all beings. And may
they help us to awaken to the clear,
boundless, and radiant nature of our own
true being. And remember, whatever you
do, don't mistake the finger for the
moon. Keep looking beyond the concepts
and beliefs and trust the innate wisdom
of your own awakened heart.
Until next time, my friends, may you
rest in the vast open space of yours.
[Music]