six months after my father died
my mother found something
hidden behind books in his study
a worn meditation cushion and a small notebook
my father was a practical engineer
who built bridges and calculated stress loads
he never spoke of any interest in spirituality
at least not to us yet
here were pages showing he'd been secretly studying
Buddhist teachings about consciousness and death
trying to understand
one tradition's vision of what might happen
after the body stops functioning
his investigation led him to Tibet's most detailed
contemplative map of the afterlife
a tradition that describes a 49-day journey
through states
where consciousness navigates self created experiences
before choosing its next existence
tonight we explore
what my father discovered about this Buddhist
vision of death and what it reveals
about how one ancient culture approached
humanity's deepest mystery
I'm Peter and we're about to examine
one of Buddhism's most elaborate attempts
to map what happens after we die
we've explored the Tibetan Book of the dead before
on this channel covering the six bardos
if you haven't seen that episode
watch it first for foundational understanding
tonight we focus specifically
on how Tibetan Buddhism
envisions the three post death bardos
their contemplative description of consciousness
during the 49 days after death
while the title might suggest universal truth
we're exploring one tradition's vision
of post death consciousness
not claiming it represents objective reality
different Buddhist traditions
offer completely different visions
of death
many Theravada teachers describe immediate rebirth
based on the final mind moment
pure land Buddhism
emphasizes instant transition to Amitabha's realm
through devotion Zen
traditions
focus on recognizing that there's ultimately
no permanent self to die or be reborn
Tibetan Buddhism developed one of the most elaborate
contemplative visions of intermediate consciousness
states
as contemporary Tibetan teacher
Tenzin Wangyal Rinpoche notes
in traditional practice
these teachings aren't studied casually
they require years of preliminary training
under qualified lamas including 100,000 prostrations
visualization practices and devotional preparation
we are encountering them
outside this traditional framework
which offers insights
but also creates significant limitations
in our understanding
these teachings trace back to texts
compiled by Yeshe Tsogyal
and revealed by Karma Lingpa in the 14th century
preserved within Tibetan culture
for those engaging with their approach
to consciousness exploration
modern neuroscience
offers different perspectives on consciousness
and death
but these ancient contemplative visions
remain fascinating examples of how human cultures
have attempted to map the unmappable
according to Tibetan Buddhist teaching
the first phase begins at the moment of death
what they call the clear light
when consciousness supposedly separates from the body
The Bardo Thödol contains this instruction
a cryptic reference to consciousness
encountering what they consider its essential nature
this represents the Chikhai Bardo in their framework
lasting from the moment of death
through roughly the first day
the tradition teaches that consciousness encounters
what they consider its own fundamental nature
without thoughts or emotions overlaying it
traditional Tibetan teachers describe this as awareness
recognizing awareness itself
though what this actually means
requires extensive contemplative training
to understand
most practitioners according to this tradition
find this overwhelming and "faint" into unconsciousness
missing what they consider
the ultimate liberation opportunity
then consciousness
supposedly moves into what they call the Chönyi Bardo
where peaceful deities begin manifesting
over the following days
Avalokiteshvara appears as overwhelming compassion
within this contemplative vision
but Tibetan Buddhism teaches
these aren't external beings
they represent consciousness
meeting its own unlimited capacities in symbolic form
if consciousness doesn't recognize
the peaceful manifestations
as its own projections according to this teaching
they begin appearing in wrathful forms
Yamantaka manifests as a terrifying destroyer figure
representing what the tradition sees
as wisdom's power to eliminate the illusion
of permanent selfhood
whether these deity encounters represent literal
post death experiences
or sophisticated psychological symbolism
developed within Tibetan culture
cannot be determined from our position
but they reveal remarkable
contemplative creativity in approaching death
have you ever wondered what it would mean to recognize
awareness itself
not thoughts or emotions
but the knowing quality that observes them
the phase that most challenges our understanding
comes in what Tibetan Buddhism calls
the Sidpa Bardo the Bardo of becoming
supposedly lasting from day 15 through day 49
according to this tradition
consciousness creates experienced reality
through thought and emotion
during this phase though
this obviously
represents claims beyond current verification
let me pause here
because this is where my father's engineering mind
really struggled with these teachings
during his final month
instead of avoiding talk about dying
he began asking his doctors
detailed questions about the dying process
he started meditating daily
and told my mother he felt curious
rather than terrified about what came next
his notebook showed attempts to understand
these reality creation claims
according to their psychology
every action word
and thought creates karmic imprints
stored in consciousness
during this phase these patterns
supposedly activate and project as experiences
the tradition describes several categories
life review not judgment by external beings
but the natural consequences of actions playing out
emotional environments their teaching claims
emotional states generate corresponding realms
anger creating hell realms of conflict
love manifesting pure lands of beauty
confusion generating shifting landscapes
whether this literally occurs after death
cannot be verified
but the tradition developed these descriptions
through centuries of contemplative investigation
within their cultural framework
he realized these teachings
weren't asking him to believe specific
post death scenarios
but to understand consciousness as more creative
and malleable than he'd assumed
this shift transformed his final weeks
approaching death as a transition
requiring awareness
rather than something to simply endure
the final stage in Tibetan Buddhist teaching
involves consciousness
approaching six colored doorways
each
supposedly leading to different realms of existence
traditional texts describe
this moment with characteristic symbolic language
but the psychological insights within this framework
offer interesting perspectives on human motivation
patterns
according to their tradition
though color realm associations vary significantly
across different Tibetan lineages
white light supposedly leads to god
realms of pleasure and comfort
yellow light opens to demigod
realms of competition and power
red light attracts to hungry ghost
realms of insatiable craving
green light leads to animal
realms of instinctual existence
blue light offers human realms
balancing pleasure and pain
smoky gray light leads to hell
realms of intense suffering
what stands out here isn't whether consciousness
literally chooses post death destinations
but how this framework maps different ways
awareness can organize experience
based on dominant psychological patterns
do you typically choose comfort over growth
competition over cooperation
wanting over appreciation
the tradition teaches that these same patterns
supposedly determine post death attraction
but more immediately
we can observe how they operate in daily choices
understanding these specific teachings suggests
three unique practices clear light
practice
daily awareness of the moment between sleep and waking
when consciousness transitions between states
projection practice recognizing when emotional states
create entire narratives about situations
noticing the difference between what's happening
and the story you're creating about it
attraction practice during stress
notice
which of the six psychological realms you default to
comfort seeking competition craving confusion
balanced awareness or suffering
my father never solved every question in his notebook
but his search taught me something crucial
about approaching mystery
he'd written near the end
during his final week something remarkable happened
after learning about the clear light teaching
he started paying
attention to the moment between sleep and waking
saying it felt like practice for the big transition
but I need to be honest some days
I convinced myself
these teachings had genuinely helped him
other days
I worried I was romanticizing his final months
to avoid facing the randomness of death
instead of the anxiety and denial we'd expected
he demonstrated genuine curiosity
about the dying process
he asked to have the Bardo Thodol read to him
not because he believed it literally
but because he found the contemplative framework
helpful for maintaining awareness during transition
when pain medications made him confused
he would practice the simple recognition of awareness
itself
the same principle these death teachings emphasize
his approach to dying changed completely
from something happening to him
to something he could participate in consciously
these teachings represent Tibetan
Buddhism's attempt to provide detailed guidance
for navigating death consciously
developed within their specific
cultural and religious context
over many centuries
whether consciousness actually continues after death
in the ways these teachings describe
remains beyond current verification
but their frameworks
offer sophisticated approaches to mortality
that emphasize awareness rather than denial
the practices didn't eliminate grief
they gave me a framework for working with it
consciously instead of being completely overwhelmed
years later
I still don't know if his transformation was genuine
spiritual insight or psychological coping mechanism
maybe both
3 breath practice from the 49 day tradition
take three slow breaths
between each breath
notice the brief pause where no thought is present
according to this tradition
that pause represents the same awareness
these death teachings point toward
consciousness
recognizing its own nature without mental overlay
we've explored Tibetan
Buddhism's most detailed vision of your consciousness
after death from day one's clear light recognition
through days two to fourteen's deity encounters
to days 15 to 49's reality
creation and rebirth selection
these teachings represent
one tradition's elaborate attempt
to map what remains unmappable
developed through centuries of contemplative
investigation within their cultural framework
my father's search reminded me that approaching
ultimate questions with honest curiosity
can transform how we live
even without definitive answers
about what happens after death
science may describe consciousness as brain events
but Tibet frame them as awareness maps
for navigating the ultimate transition
each approach offers different insights
into the mystery of what we are
this is how Tibetan Buddhism explains
your consciousness after death
a 49 day journey through recognition
projection and choice
but here's where our exploration takes an unexpected
turn
these Tibetan teachings describe your consciousness
transforming over 49 days after death
what if similar death and renewal processes happen
continuously in daily life
what if you're already navigating
micro versions of these same transitions every moment
next week we'll explore why you've died 1,000 times
and how every cell in your body
undergoes constant death and regeneration
how your consciousness dissolves and recreates itself
moment by moment how understanding micro deaths
transforms your relationship with macro death
what we'll discover
suggest that these ancient insights about transition
and renewal apply to processes happening continuously
throughout life
making death less foreign and more familiar
than you typically imagine
if tonight's exploration sparked your curiosity
about how different cultures approach mortality
subscribe and activate notifications
share this with anyone interested
in contemplative approaches to consciousness and death
tell us in the comments
which aspect of the Tibetan vision most intrigues you
have you noticed attraction patterns
similar to the Six Realms
operating in your own experience
remember while we can't verify
claims about post death consciousness
we can learn from how contemplative traditions
have approached these ultimate questions
with sophisticated frameworks developed over centuries
until next time stay curious stay wise