what if I told you
the greatest yogi in Tibet was trained by a man who
some accounts say made him build and destroy a tower
not once not twice
but as many as 12 times
here's what you're about to witness
bleeding hands broken dreams
and a teacher who smiles while watching you demolish
months of work with your bare hands
start over he says
this time make it perfect
this isn't your peaceful meditation retreat
this is Marpa the translator
the farmer mystic
who brought esoteric teachings from India
and turned spiritual training
into the ultimate test of human endurance
today we meet the teacher
who believed the only way to save a killer's soul
was to break everything else first
can you shatter someone so completely
that enlightenment grows from the pieces
welcome back to Buddha's wisdom
I'm Matt and we're continuing
the wildest redemption story in Buddhist history
and here's the crazy part
so many of you have been asking
can someone who's done terrible things actually change
well you're about to get your answer
last episode ended with Milarepa
standing in the ruins of his magical revenge
35 wedding guests dead his sister asking
what have you become he discovered the answer
a monster
who needed to die before anything good could be born
remember our Monkey King series
Sun Wukong's ego was massive
but at least he didn't murder entire families
Milarepa's transformation
required something way more extreme
than breathing exercises and positive thinking
he needed a teacher willing to destroy him
and get this he found one
over the next 25 minutes
you'll witness spiritual training
that makes any modern military training look gentle
by comparison we're talking years of manual labor
that wrecks your body
cave meditation that literally turns you green
and a final demon battle that could kill you
but here's what makes this absolutely insane
it actually works by the end
you'll see whether someone who's committed mass murder
can actually claw their way back to the light
the method more suffering than you can imagine
after the massacre
Milarepa wandered Tibet's mountains for months
carrying guilt that felt heavier than stone
searching for someone who could teach him
to undo what he'd done
local monks took one look at this pale
haunted figure and slammed their monastery doors
nobody wanted the wedding killer as a student
then he heard stories about Marpa
the translator
and this guy's backstory is absolutely wild
accounts describe him as stocky and bearded
with a booming laugh and farmer's hands
more villager than mystic
but those deep set
intense eyes seem to see straight through your soul
now imagine this farmer
hearing about incredible Buddhist teachings
available in India
but getting there means crossing mountain passes
that locals call death's gateway
walking through territories
controlled by hostile armies
and somehow
surviving months of travel that would kill most people
most sane individuals would say
forget it Marpa said
I'm going anyway
three times
three separate expeditions to India
each time collecting more advanced tantric practices
than most Tibetans would ever see
secret teachings from masters
who only shared them with their closest disciples
then he'd return to his valley
and go back to farming barley
like he'd been on vacation
when Milarepa finally found him
Marpa was plowing a field in the Lodrak Valley
cursing at stubborn oxen covered in mud
looking like any frustrated farmer
this was the man who would transform a killer
into someone later known as Jetsun Milarepa
Venerable Master Milarepa
one of Tibet's greatest yogis
are you the great teacher Marpa
Milarepa asked nervously
Marpa stopped
looked at this desperate young man with haunted eyes
and burst out laughing teacher
I'm trying to plant barley before winter kills
everything you want
the master he's probably drinking tea up at the house
I'm nobody special
can you imagine the confusion
you're expecting some mystical guru on a throne
and instead you get a farmer
who pretends he's never heard of himself
for hours Marpa played this game
fed Milarepa dinner
listened to his confession about mass murder
and black magic
all while acting like he had no idea where this famous
teacher might be hiding
and here's the thing this wasn't cruelty
this was testing
real masters don't accept students immediately
they check for desperation humility
willingness to be treated like dirt
if that's what transformation requires
when Marpa finally revealed his identity
Milarepa collapsed and begged to become a student
I've killed 35 innocent people with sorcery
he confessed
I need Dharma teachings to purify this karma
I'll do anything you ask
Marpa studied this broken young man
then quoted something his own teacher
Naropa had told him in the caves of India
the dharma is not bought with gold
but with the marrow of your bones
then
he smiled in a way that should have terrified Milarepa
perfect I specialize in hopeless cases
but understand this
my methods will make your sorcery training
look like a pleasant afternoon
Milarepa nodded eagerly
he had no idea he'd signed up for years of torture
because Marpa wasn't planning to teach him Buddhism
he was planning to kill everything
Milarepa thought he was
build me a tower Marpa said
the next morning
handing milarepa a pile of stones nine stories tall
perfect stonework no help from anyone
Milarepa thought this was symbolic
some kind of patience lesson
before getting real teachings
he was dead wrong Marpa literally wanted a tower
for months milarepa hauled stones up that hill
each rock had to be shaped by hand
every level precisely aligned
his hands split and bled from the rough granite
his back screamed constantly
ever had a boss who made impossible demands
Marpa made them look merciful
the other students watched with growing concern
a young monk named Tsultrim whispered to his friend
this isn't spiritual training
this is punishment for a crime we don't understand
slowly painfully
a magnificent nine story tower rose from the Hillside
architectural masterpiece
something that would stand for generations
when Milarepa placed the final stone
exhausted but genuinely proud he ran to get Marpa
master come see what I've built
Marpa climbed the hill like a building inspector
examined every level
with infuriating attention to detail
walked around the structure three times
then nodded thoughtfully
interesting work he said
now tear it down
Milarapa stared I'm sorry what
tear it down every stone
the foundation was wrong from the beginning
start over
pause and think about this for a second
you've poured
months of your life into something beautiful
and your teacher casually tells you to demolish it
because of some technical flaw you never understood
most people would quit storm off
demand an explanation
but Milarepa
remembered the 35 wedding guests he'd murdered
maybe he deserved
exactly this kind of meaningless torment
the sound of stones crashing down the Hillside
echoed through the valley
like thunder other students winced with each impact
tower No. 2 took even longer
better materials flawless construction
good work Marpa said after his inspection
now tear it down these stones are the wrong colour
and here's where it gets insane
traditional accounts vary
but some sources say this happened not once
not twice but tower after tower after tower
each one more perfect than the last
each demolition more devastating
after demolishing
what might have been his seventh attempt
Milarepa finally broke down sobbing
that's when Marpa did something unexpected
he sat down next to his student
and for a moment his farmer's mask slipped away
you think I'm being cruel
he said quietly but look at your hands
Milarepa looked the scars told a story
months of suffering years of dedication
those hands once summoned death with magic
Marpa continued now they create beauty from stone
that's karma in action
the same hands that caused suffering
now carving the path to awakening
for the first time
Milarepa began to understand this wasn't punishment
this was surgery removing the spiritual disease
that had created a killer
every tower represented everything
Milarepa thought he deserved
every demolition taught him that he deserved nothing
the person who had Learned sorcery for revenge
who had demanded justice through violence
that person was dying one demolished tower at a time
after years of tower building
had shattered every expectation
Marpa finally spoke
the words Milarepa had been desperately waiting for
you're ready for meditation instruction
he handed milarepa a worn scroll
covered in Sanskrit text
advanced practices for working with subtle energy
techniques for recognizing the nature of consciousness
itself methods that normally required constant guidance
go to that cave
don't come out until you've mastered everything
written here
the cave was barely large enough for one person
cold as winter night dark as the bottom of a well
so isolated that even bird songs couldn't reach inside
how long should I stay milarepa asked
until you're done Marpa replied
three years three years
in what felt more like a tomb than a meditation hall
the food Marpa provided
just enough barley flour to avoid starvation
when even that ran out milarepa faced a choice
leave the cave and admit failure
or find another way to survive
the mountains were covered in stinging nettles
touching them felt like being burned alive
eating them was torture
the bitter taste would make you vomit
but they would keep you alive
for months then years
Milarepa survived on nothing except these cursed weeds
and here's where it gets absolutely wild
the transformation was horrifying
his body wasted away
until every bone showed through paper thin skin
the chlorophyll turned him green skin hair
even his nails
when villagers occasionally glimpsed this skeletal
green figure moving through the forest like a ghost
children ran screaming to their mothers
adults whispered Protection mantras
and made signs against evil spirits
they thought they were seeing a hungry ghost
a spirit of someone who had died with terrible karma
and couldn't find peace in a way
they were absolutely right
but something incredible was happening inside that cave
his meditation deepened as his body disappeared
with nowhere to go nothing to distract him
no comfort to cling to his consciousness had no choice
except to expand beyond normal human limitations
the guilt over 35 murders was dissolving
like salt in water
not because he'd forgotten what he'd done
but because the he who had committed those crimes
was starving to death in that cave
during the deepest meditation states
when the boundary between his mind and infinite space
began dissolving completely
Milarepa experienced something that would later
become one of his most famous songs
I have no food I have no clothes
but I am rich in the dharma
the person who had demanded material justice
was learning to find wealth in emptiness itself
when he finally emerged after three years
skeletal and green as a mountain spirit
even his own reflection in streams
looked alien and frightening
the killer was almost dead
what would replace him remained to be seen
but the final test was coming
one person couldn't stand
watching this gradual destruction
Dagmema Marpa's wife
had witnessed the scarred hands from Tower Building
the growing desperation
now she occasionally glimpsed this green
skeletal figure during his rare appearances
and her heart shattered
this has gone too far
she told Marpa one evening as they sat by their fire
that boy is dying up there
good Marpa replied
without looking up from his tea
the boy who killed 35 people needs to die
some versions of the story say
Dagmema secretly helped Milarepa
during these cave years others claim
she simply begged her husband to show mercy
what's certain is this her compassion
created a crisis that threatened everything
when Marpa traveled to teach other students
in distant valleys
Dagmema made a decision that would change everything
she climbed to the cave with food
warm clothes and most dangerously
human kindness
what she found horrified her
this skeletal figure
so weak he could barely lift his head
still sitting in meditation posture
with fierce determination burning in his sunken eyes
my husband is testing your resolve
she whispered but I can see you've endured enough
surely the dharma allows for mercy
for the first time in years
Milarepa felt someone cared whether he lived or died
when Marpa returned from his teaching tour weeks later
he immediately sensed the change
his student's desperate edge had been softened
by comfort
who helped you he demanded
Milarepa confessed about Dagmema's visits
what followed wasn't an explosion of shouting
something far more terrifying
Marpa went completely silent
when he finally spoke
his voice was cold as mountain winter
my own wife
undermining everything I've worked to achieve
his farmer's warmth had vanished completely
do you understand what kindness does to someone
trying to transcend ego
Dagmema tried to defend her actions
he's endured enough surely the dharma allows for mercy
mercy
Marpa's quiet fury was more frightening than any scream
a mass murderer receives exactly what karma provides
nothing more
nothing less
the argument that followed
threatened to destroy their marriage
Milarepa realized he'd caused this crisis
through his weakness his need for comfort
his inability to face the full weight of what he'd done
there's only one way to resolve this
Marpa declared with finality
final test tonight
either you achieve complete realization
or you die with your karma unresolved
the look in his deep
set eyes suggested death was the more likely outcome
everything had been leading to this moment
sit there Marpa commanded
pointing to an isolated meditation area
far from the house far from any help
face everything you've done
every person you've killed
every family you've destroyed
achieve enlightenment tonight or die trying
milarepa skeletal and green from years of nettle eating
nodded and sat in meditation posture one final time
in Buddhist thought karma is inescapable
but it can be transformed
tonight would determine whether
Milarepa could turn the poison of his past
into the medicine of awakening
he closed his eyes
went deeper into awareness than ever before
and entered the space where all his guilt lived
at first the profound stillness
he'd Learned during three years of cave meditation
then something shifted in the darkness
the air grew thick as storm clouds
shadows began moving without any light to cast them
the temperature dropped
until his breath became visible mist
a presence materialized
that made every survival instinct scream in terror
massive eyes like molten metal
fangs that dripped with accumulated darkness
traditional accounts describe Milarepa
facing terrifying demons during his retreats
but imagine for someone who'd committed mass murder
those demons might have worn the faces of his victims
so it said in a voice
like grinding bones and screaming wind
the killer thinks meditation erases murder
behind the demon
figures began appearing in the darkness
wedding guests children
innocent relatives people
whose lives he'd stolen with supernatural vengeance
you think sitting in caves makes you pure
the demon continued
you think suffering pays for what you've done to us
terror
beyond anything he'd experienced with black magic
this wasn't some meditation vision
this felt real as stone
solid as death itself
the accumulated weight of his karma
manifesting
as something that could destroy him completely
for a moment he almost fled
screaming into the night then
he remembered something the Buddha had once said
when facing his own demons
I see you Mara
I know who you are
Milarepa opened his eyes
looked directly at this manifestation
of everything he'd done wrong
and made a choice
that would determine whether redemption was real
or beautiful lie
he stood up his skeletal frame shook with exhaustion
his green skin showed every bone
yet when he spoke
his voice carried strength that surprised even him
you're absolutely right
he said to the demon and the faces of the dead
I am a killer I did murder innocent people
the demon smiled sensing victory was within reach
Milarepa took a step forward toward the nightmare
but watch
the demon lunged forward claws extended like knives
ready to tear apart this skeletal figure
who dared face the weight of mass murder
the faces of the dead began screaming for justice
for revenge for the very blood payment
that Milarepa had once demanded for himself
and milarepa broken and green from years of suffering
stood at the moment that determines every human life
can someone who has committed terrible acts
truly transform
or are we forever prisoners of our worst decisions
one day
this broken figure would be called Jetsun Milarepa
and his voice would shake mountains
with songs of enlightenment
that are still sung in Tibetan valleys today
but right now it trembled before the demons of his past
what happens next determines everything
in Part 3 we'll witness the most intense
spiritual battle ever recorded
the final test of whether light can truly emerge
from the deepest darkness
how many of you have done something you deeply regret
something that made you question
whether you could ever be forgiven
because what Milarepa does in this moment
will challenge everything
you think you know about redemption
if you're following this impossible journey
from killer to realized master
hit subscribe and stay with us
for the conclusion
that will redefine how you think about redemption
the ending of Milarepa's journey
is unlike anything you expect
and it still sung in Tibet a thousand years later
to be continued in part 3 the singing yogi