what if I told you
that one of Buddhism's greatest saints
was once a mass murderer
a young man so consumed by rage
that he calls down a supernatural storm
that crushes a house during a wedding Celebration
35 people die crushed under collapsing beams and stone
but no one expected that this same killer
would one day be revered as a saint
a master
whose songs are still sung in Tibetan valleys today
how does someone go from taking lives to saving souls
how do you come back from that kind of darkness
today we're telling the most shocking redemption story
in Buddhist history
the tale of Milarepa
the boy who learned sorcery and became a saint
I'm warning you right now
this story gets dark before it gets light
really dark
are you ready to meet the saint who was once a killer
welcome back to Buddha's wisdom
I'm Matt
and today we're starting something completely different
you know how we recently
explored the Monkey King's battle with Buddha
well if you thought Sun Wukong had anger issues
Milarepa makes him look like a meditation teacher
most Buddhist stories follow a predictable pattern
someone seeks wisdom finds a teacher
practices meditation achieves peace
nice and tidy Milarepa's story
it starts with revenge blood and supernatural murder
then it gets worse here's why his story matters
especially
if you've ever done something you deeply regret
Milarepa proves that no mistake is too big
no darkness too deep
and no past too violent for transformation
his own life shows
that even a murderer can become a Buddha
his journey shows us that redemption
isn't about being perfect
it's about what you do after you completely mess up
Milarepa's mistake
was beyond anything you can imagine
over the next three episodes
we'll follow his path from sorcerer to saint
Today we're covering the darkness
the family betrayal that created a killer
and the moment everything changed
by the end of this episode
you'll understand how someone becomes so angry
they're willing to murder dozens of people with magic
but you'll also see the first spark of hope
that could become enlightenment
it all started with a boy
born into material prosperity and familial bliss
that's about to be destroyed forever
our story begins in the mid 11th century
in a place called Gungthang
a prosperous region of western Tibet
near the border with Nepal
here lived a boy named Mila Thöpaga
which means a joy to hear
his early life was exactly that
pure joy
his father Sherab Gyaltsen
wasn't your average Tibetan farmer
this guy was a successful merchant
the kind of man who owned vast fields
herds of yaks and sheep
and a three story stone mansion with carved
wooden balconies
we're talking serious money here
the kind that makes you village royalty
his mother Nyangtsa Kargyen
was known throughout the region
for her intelligence and beauty
she came from an influential family herself
so this marriage combined two powerhouses
Young Mila had everything a child could want
loving parents a beautiful home
and a little sister named Peta Gönkyi
who followed him everywhere with sparkling eyes
in Tibet household
wealth and honor were everything
losing both meant not just poverty
it meant shame that stuck to your name for generations
but here's what made this family special
they weren't wealthy jerks
Sherab Gyaltsen was respected
because he was fair and generous
he helped struggling farmers through harsh winters
settled disputes
with wisdom that impressed village elders
and was considered a pillar of the community
the villagers would nod respectfully
when the family passed
children would bow to Mila's father
merchants would seek his advice on trade routes
and fair prices
for seven years Mila lived in this bubble of security
he thought this was how life worked
you had family you had wealth
you had respect
he had no idea that life could be cruel
but then everything changed
in a single devastating week
Sherab Gyaltsen fell ill
with a fever that wouldn't break
his strong body which had survived mountain winters
and dangerous trade expeditions
began to waste away before their eyes
in those days there were no hospitals
no medicine
no way to fight whatever was consuming him from within
as he lay dying knowing his time was running out
Sherab Gyaltsen
made a decision that would doom his family
he called his brother and sister in law to his bedside
promise me he whispered
with his final breaths
you'll protect my wife and children
guard my wealth for my son until he comes of age
treat them as you would your own family
his brother clasped his hand and swore sacred oaths
his sister in law wept
and promised faithfully to honor his wishes
they looked him in the eye and lied
when Sherab Gyaltsen died 7 year old
Mila
thought his uncle and aunt would keep their promise
he was about to learn that some people will do anything
for money even destroy a family
the transformation began the day after the funeral
Mila's uncle and aunt didn't waste time
the uncle moved into the family mansion
like he owned it because suddenly he did
we need to manage the estate properly
the uncle announced to the gathered villagers
for the boy's own good of course
the villagers nodded it seemed reasonable
responsible even
what the villagers didn't see
was what happened behind closed doors
first the uncle took control of the fields
then the livestock then the servants
within weeks everything that belonged to Mila's family
now belonged to his uncle
but here's the truly evil part
the uncle and aunt didn't kick the family out
that would have been too obvious
instead the uncle turned Mila
his mother and little sister Peta
into servants in their own home
when I first heard this story
I couldn't believe it yesterday
you're the son of the richest man in the village
today you're
scrubbing floors
for the people who stole everything from you
Mila's mother went from being the lady of the house
to washing clothes by the river
this proud intelligent woman was forced to bow her head
and serve the very people who destroyed her life
little Peta went from playing with silk dolls
to hauling water buckets
that were too heavy for her small hands
the light slowly faded from her eyes
as she watched her family's dignity crumble
as for Mila himself
years later he described it like this
our food was food for dogs
our work was work for donkeys
forced to toil without rest
our limbs became cracked and raw
with only poor food and clothing
we became pale and emaciated
it's impossible to imagine your own relatives
making you live like an animal
but the worst part wasn't the physical suffering
it was the humiliation every day
villagers would see this once proud family
reduced to beggars in their own home
and slowly
the villagers sympathy turned to indifference
people have their own problems
family disputes become uncomfortable
it's easier to look away
meanwhile
Mila's uncle and aunt threw parties with stolen money
wore fine clothes bought with stolen wealth
and acted like generous benefactors to the community
for three years Nyangtsa Kargyen
tried to reclaim what belonged to her family
she appealed to village elders
she showed them her husband's will
she begged for justice but
corrupt people are often very good at covering their
tracks the uncle
had convinced everyone that he was managing the estate
responsibly
that Mila was too young to handle such wealth
nobody wanted to get involved
especially when the uncle had all the money
and all the power
with each rejection Nyangtsa Kargyen's heart grew darker
then came the final humiliation
one market day after her latest appeal was dismissed
Nyangtsa Kargyen gathered her courage
and confronted her brother in law publicly
in front of the entire village
she demanded he return what he had stolen
you promised my dying husband
she cried you swore to protect his children
the uncle's response he laughed
actually laughed in her face
then he had her dragged away and thrown into the dirt
like garbage
as Mila watched his mother lying in the dust
his sister crying
and the villagers turning away in embarrassment
the boy he had been died
his childhood was over his innocence was dead
and in its place a terrible anger began to grow
that night would change everything
that evening after being humiliated
in front of everyone she had once called friends
Nyangtsa Kargyen sat in the corner of their borrowed hut
her hands were dirty her clothes torn
her pride shattered
but her eyes burned with a dangerous desperation
she looked at her teenage son
this boy who had once been destined for greatness
now reduced to rags and shame
Mila she said quietly
I have tried everything every legal path
every appeal
every plea for justice
her voice grew harder with each word
your father's brother has stolen our life
our dignity our future
and the law has abandoned us
Mila had never heard his mother speak like this before
it frightened him
she continued revenge
now you have to understand
this wasn't some movie moment
where the hero decides to learn martial arts
this was medieval Tibet
when people talked about revenge
they meant darker arts they meant magic
black magic
I want you to learn sorcery his mother said
I want you to study the dark arts
until you can destroy our enemies completely
little Peta
who had been quietly mending clothes in the corner
gasped mother no
she whispered this isn't who we are
father would never want this
but Nyangtsa Kargyen
was past caring
what her dead husband would have wanted
if you refuse she said
staring directly into her son's eyes
if you won't avenge your family
then don't call me mother anymore
the ultimatum hit like a physical blow
your mother
the person who's supposed to guide you toward goodness
demanding that you become a killer
and if you fail she added
if you're too weak to master the magic
needed to destroy them
I will kill myself
I would rather die than live one more day
in this humiliation
Mila felt the world spinning
on one side sat his little sister
tears streaming down her face
silently begging him not to do this terrible thing
on the other side sat his mother
consumed by rage and shame
demanding that he choose between becoming a murderer
or losing his family forever
it's impossible to imagine making that choice
you're a teenager your family has lost everything
the legal system has failed you
your mother is threatening suicide if you don't act
and deep down aren't you angry too
don't you want to see the people
who destroyed your life suffer the way you've suffered
Mila looked at his sister's tears
then at his mother's burning eyes
he thought about scrubbing floors in his own home
of eating scraps
while his uncle feasted on stolen wealth
of watching villagers look away
when they saw his family's shame
the decision tore him apart
but in the end he was still his mother's son
I'll do it he whispered
Peta collapsed in sobs
but Nyangtsa Kargyen smiled for the first time in years
there's a sorcerer named Yungton Trogyel
she said he's known throughout the region
as a master of the dark arts
go to him learn everything he can teach you
she paused and her voice became deadly serious
and when you return I want our family's enemies to pay
for every day they've made us suffer
Mila nodded his childhood was officially over
he was about to become a weapon
so Mila left everything he had ever known
and set out to find the most dangerous man in Tibet
some say the black arts he would study
came not from Buddhism
but from Bon Tibet's ancient shamanic tradition
here death wasn't feared it was a power to be summoned
when he finally reached Yungton's dwelling
it looked ordinary enough
a simple stone house in a remote valley
but there was an aura of wrongness about the place
the air was too still birds didn't sing nearby
Yungton Trogyel was a small
quiet man
with eyes that seemed to look right through you
he listened to Mila's story without interruption
the stolen inheritance the public humiliation
the mother's ultimatum
when Mila finished
Yungton was silent for a long moment
you wanna learn sorcery for revenge
he finally said do you understand what that means
Mila nodded though honestly
he had no idea real magic isn't about waving your hands
and making things happen
real magic is about making bargains
with forces beyond human understanding
and those forces always demand payment
Mila asked what kind of payment
sometimes your health sometimes your sanity
sometimes
pieces of your soul that you'll never get back
Yungton studied this desperate young man
and spoke words that felt ancient
when you deal in curses boy
know that you must wear them home
but Mila was past caring about the cost
every night he thought about his mother's threat
about his sister's tears
about the humiliation that demanded justice
so his education in darkness began
for months he studied forbidden texts
written in languages that predated Buddhism's arrival
in Tibet
he learned to draw protective circles with chalk
made from bones
he memorized incantations that made his throat burn
but this wasn't like learning history or poetry
every lesson felt like it was changing his core being
the rituals required him to embrace hatred
to nurture anger to feed the darkest parts of his soul
he practiced on small animals
first mice then birds
then larger creatures
each death came easier than the last
and slowly terrifyingly
he began to understand how much power he was gaining
the spirits responded to his calls
the protective circles
held against forces that could drive men insane
his teacher watched with a mixture of pride and fear
finally the night came for the ultimate test
Mila stood in the center of a circle
drawn with ash from cremated criminals
around him were symbols that hurt to look at directly
in his hands
was a ritual dagger that seemed to absorb light
for hours he chanted incantations in the ancient tongue
he called upon spirits
whose names cannot be spoken in daylight
he offered pieces of his own life force
as payment for what he was about to unleash
and then an entity answered
the air became thick as water
shadows moved independently of their sources
and Mila felt a presence so alien and hungry
that every instinct screamed at him to run
but he didn't run instead
he made his bargain with darkness
when the ritual ended
Yungton looked at his student with genuine fear
you now possess the power to summon death itself
he whispered but remember the forces you now command
don't distinguish between guilty and innocent
once you unleash them
they will devour everything in their path
Mila gathered his few possessions
and began the journey back to his village
he was no longer the broken boy who had left months ago
he was a weapon and he was going home
when Mila returned to his village after months away
nobody recognized him at first
the magic had changed him
his eyes were colder his face was thinner
his skin had a greyish pallor
and there was an aura about his presence
that made people instinctively step away
even little Peta when she first saw him whispered
brother what have they done to you
but he wasn't there for reunions
he was there to complete a promise
and fate or maybe darker forces
had given him the perfect opportunity
his uncle's son was getting married
the entire
extended family had gathered for a massive Celebration
35 people crowded into the house
that had once belonged to Mila's father
eating food bought with stolen money
celebrating with wine purchased through stolen wealth
the uncle and aunt had no
idea that death was watching them
from the shadows
Mila found a secluded spot on the Hillside
overlooking the house he could hear their laughter
their songs their joy
for a moment he hesitated
these weren't all evil people
some were relatives who had come for a wedding
children who had done nothing wrong
young couples starting their lives together
but then he remembered his mother's ultimatum
the public humiliation the stolen inheritance
the promise he had made
and any mercy he might have felt died
he began the ritual first
he drew the protective circle with ash
he had carried from Yungton's lair
then he placed the cursed objects at specific points
each one consecrated with blood and hatred
as the sun set behind the mountains
he began to chant
the words that came from his mouth
weren't human language
they were sounds that predated civilization
syllables that existed in the spaces between nightmares
with each verse the air around him grew thicker
darker
and then
he called upon the entity he had bargained with
I offer you this feast
he whispered in the ancient tongue
35 souls in exchange for the justice
that was denied to my family
for a moment nothing happened
then the temperature dropped 20 degrees in seconds
inside the house the Celebration suddenly went quiet
someone screamed that the walls were moving
others pointed at shadows crawling across the ceiling
like living things but that was only the beginning
Mila raised his ritual dagger toward the sky
and spoke the final words of the spell
what happened next defied every law of nature
the clear evening sky suddenly boiled with black clouds
wind that hadn't existed moments before began howling
and from those impossible clouds came hail
but this wasn't ordinary hail
these were massive chunks of ice
the size of human skulls
each one fell with impossible force
guided by supernatural hatred
the first hailstone smashed through the roof
like it was made of paper
the second crushed a supporting beam
the third and fourth and dozens more
began systematically destroying the house
the sound was indescribable
cracking wood screaming wind
human voices raised in terror
inside
35 people who had been celebrating moments before
were now trapped in a nightmare
some tried to run others hid under tables
nothing mattered the supernatural storm was methodical
relentless and standing in his ritual circle
Mila watched it all with cold satisfaction
this was justice
this was what his family's enemies deserved
the storm lasted exactly as long as the ritual required
when Mila spoke the final word
the wind stopped the clouds vanished
the hail ceased falling and in the sudden silence
nothing moved in what had once been a house
35 people gone
only two figures emerged from the wreckage
his uncle and aunt somehow
spared by forces that Mila would never understand
perhaps the spirits wanted them to live with the loss
perhaps
their suffering was more valuable than their deaths
the uncle and aunt staggered through the ruins
calling out names of family members
who would never answer
some say it was supernatural
others believe a natural storm
struck at the worst possible moment
but what matters is this in the hearts of villagers
it became a curse and Milarepa its architect
but as Mila stood there watching his uncle
and aunt weep over the destruction
he felt no satisfaction he felt empty
when he returned to their small hut
his mother was waiting
did you do it she asked he nodded
for three days she reveled in their enemy's destruction
but then she saw a young woman
weeping over the ruins where her new husband had died
a husband
whose only crime was being related to the wrong family
that's when the reality hit her
they hadn't punished the guilty
they had slaughtered innocence
the days after the massacre
were the longest of Mila's life
he had expected to feel victorious
satisfied complete
instead he felt hollow
like his essential self had been carved out
and could never be replaced
the village was in mourning
35 families had lost loved ones in a single night
children cried for parents who would never come home
parents wept over children
who had died for someone else's crimes
and Mila the architect of all this suffering
found that revenge tasted like ashes
one evening as Mila sat staring at nothing
his little sister Peta approached him
her eyes were red from crying not for the dead
but for what her brother had become
what have you become she whispered
the question hit him like a physical blow
what had he become he had started as a victim
a boy
whose family had been destroyed by greed and cruelty
someone deserving of sympathy and justice
but somewhere along the path of revenge
he had transformed into a destroyer
a killer a destroyer of families
someone who had caused more suffering
than had ever been inflicted
on him that night
alone in the darkness Mila
finally allowed himself
to feel the full weight of what he had done
35 people gone forever because of him
families destroyed because of his magic
a community traumatized
because of his thirst for vengeance
in Buddhism karma isn't moral accounting
it's momentum
and Mila's momentum was now deadly
rolling fast toward an even darker fate
he thought destroying the house would bring peace
but he had been chasing illusions
shadows that only deepened his pain
as Mila stood
in the ruins of what his anger had created
as he felt the weight of 35 deaths
crushing down on his soul
he looked up at the stars
and whispered words
that would later echo in his teachings
in the sky of mind the storm clouds gather
but beyond them the moon still shines
he paused
and asked the question that would change everything
can someone who has fallen this far into darkness
ever find their way back to the light
unknown to Mila his question had already been heard
in the distance a figure watched from the mountain path
an old monk with kind eyes
who had been traveling these valleys for many years
searching for students
ready to learn the hardest lessons of all
the monk had witnessed the supernatural storm
had seen the destruction
had felt the young man's anguish
rippling through the spiritual realm like waves
most teachers would have turned away from such darkness
but this monk understood a truth that few others did
that sometimes
the deepest enlightenment comes from the deepest fall
his name was Marpa and he had been waiting for someone
exactly like Milarepa
the path to redemption was about to begin
can someone who has committed terrible acts
ever find redemption can a killer become a saint
that's the question we'll explore in Part 2
when Mila
meets the most demanding teacher in Buddhist history
a master who will break him down completely
before building him into something extraordinary
but I want to know
have you ever done something you deeply regret
something that made you question who you really are
leave a comment below
sometimes the path to healing starts with admitting
we need it
if Milarepa's story resonates with you
if you believe that redemption is possible
even for the worst among us
then subscribe and stay with us on this path
because the light is coming
but not before more darkness