picture this
medieval Europe 1099
Christian knights storm Jerusalem's walls shouting
god wills it blood flows through streets
as citizens fall to the sword
meanwhile in ancient Asia
Buddhist monks walked from village to village
with nothing but robes and a bowl
they didn't conquer they didn't convert
they just listened
in one part of the world
men slaughtered each other shouting
god wills it in another
men sat in silence
conquering nothing but their own minds
why this stark difference
why did Christianity Islam
and other religions raise armies for their gods
while Buddhism spread across continents
without a single holy war
Buddhism operates differently
from belief based religions
it offers a testable system for understanding your mind
this distinction matters
when we talk about why people fight holy wars
before we dive deeper a quick note
this video explores
historical patterns of religious spread
and violence
my intention isn't to criticize any faith tradition
but to understand
Buddhism's unique approach to sharing ideas
every tradition contains both peaceful
and violent elements I'm simply examining why
Buddhism's spread followed a distinctive pattern
armies empires
and kings
embraced Buddhist teachings and put down their swords
not because someone forced them to
but because the logic was just that convincing
and when I tell you about the bloodthirsty emperor
who killed 99% of his family to gain power
but then became Buddhism's greatest champion
you'll understand why
this system of thought never needed holy wars
to become a global force
but here's the twist
there are Buddhist extremists today
so what went wrong
this is the untold story of how ideas
not armies conquered half the world
Buddhism doesn't fit neatly into western categories
this distinction matters
especially when we talk about holy wars
we might argue Buddhism had no holy wars
because it's not really a religion
but this misses the point
Buddhism has all the elements
we associate with religion
monks temples
rituals scriptures
cosmology and supernatural elements like rebirth
millions of people worship the Buddha
and pray to bodhisattvas for assistance
no the absence of Buddhist holy wars
can't be explained away
that simply there's something deeper at work
what's fascinating
is that the Buddha never intended to start a religion
at all
when asked if his was the only path to liberation
he responded with the parable of the raft
his revolutionary point spiritual teachings
are tools for crossing the river of suffering
not dogmas to be defended
the Buddha said do not believe anything
simply because you have heard it
or because it is written in your religious books
but after observation and analysis
when you find that anything agrees with reason
and is conducive to good
then accept it and live up to it
this differs radically from traditions
where questioning core beliefs
might be considered heresy
when
you don't need others to accept your claims on faith
you don't need to force them to believe
compare this to Christianity spread through Europe
while Christianity
initially expanded through persuasion
during Roman persecution
after Constantine's conversion in 312 CE
imperial power became a primary vehicle for its growth
by the late 4th century
Christian emperors were outlawing pagan practices
and destroying temples
similarly Islam's early expansion
combined preaching with military conquest
creating vast empires
where non Muslims paid special taxes
and faced various restrictions
Buddhism's different approach
emphasizing personal verification over belief
created fundamentally different patterns of expansion
throughout history
religious conflicts have shaped our world
burning through civilizations
redrawing borders and claiming countless lives
the Crusades stand as perhaps the most famous example
Pope Urban
II launched the First Crusade in 1095
with a simple call god wills it
Christian knights
marched thousands of miles to reclaim Jerusalem
from Muslim rule
when they finally breached Jerusalem's walls in 1099
the Crusaders slaughtered Muslims
Jews and even eastern Christians
one crusader Raymond of Aguilers wrote
in the temple of Solomon
men rode in blood up to their knees in bridle reins
but Christianity holds no monopoly on holy wars
Islamic expansion brought its own religious conflicts
the concept of jihad
though primarily meaning spiritual struggle
also justified military campaigns
early caliphates expanded rapidly across North Africa
the Middle Eastern parts of Europe
converting populations and establishing Islamic rule
in Europe the Thirty Years War
1618 to 1648 pitted Catholics against Protestants
in a devastating conflict
that killed nearly a third of Germany's population
all because they interpreted the same holy book
differently
even Hinduism often portrayed as peaceful
has its warriors
the Mahabharata describes a righteous war
where the god Krishna tells the warrior Arjuna
if you will not fight this righteous war
then you will fail in your duty
lose your reputation and incur sin
so what drives people to kill in the name of god
the human toll of these conflicts is staggering
the Crusades killed perhaps
1 to 3 million people over two centuries
the 30 years War caused around 8 million deaths
the Pakistani Indian partition in 1947
driven partly by religious differences
displaced 14 million people and killed up to 2 million
religious wars typically share key ingredients
exclusive truth claims divine authorization
and cosmic dualism
dividing the world into forces of good and evil
religious warriors don't see themselves as killers
but as saviors they're not conquering
they're liberating they're not murdering
they're saving souls
holy wars aren't just about territory or resources
they're existential battles for cosmic order
the stakes couldn't be higher
eternal salvation or damnation
so how did Buddhism avoid this pattern
let's examine how
Buddhism's unique approach to truth and practice
made it fundamentally different
at Buddhism's core lies ahimsa non violence
not just a nice suggestion
but a fundamental principle
the very first precept that every Buddhist accepts is
I undertake the training rule to abstain from killing
this isn't just about avoiding murder
it extends to daily choices about causing harm
a monk carefully watches his step
to avoid crushing insects
a Buddhist lay person
considers how their consumption affects other beings
this comprehensive approach to nonviolence
permeates every aspect of life
according to Buddhist teachings
all beings tremble before danger
all fear death when a man considers this
he does not kill or cause to kill
the Buddha rejected violence even in his own life
born Prince Siddhartha
he abandoned the warrior caste and military training
that was his birthright
when his own clan faced annihilation
he attempted to prevent the slaughter
through peaceful intervention
standing between opposing armies
what makes Buddhism different
is its relationship to truth and conversion
while most religions operate on faith and revelations
Buddhism operates on testing hypotheses about suffering
the Buddha claimed his teachings came from
direct observation of how the mind works
as the Buddha expressed it
just as the wise test gold by burning
cutting and rubbing it
so are you to test my words by examining them
Buddhism also introduced concepts like emptiness
sunyata not nothingness
but the understanding that nothing exists
independently or permanently
imagine a wooden table
is it really a table or is it wood
which came from a tree which came from soil
sunlight and water
everything is interconnected with no separate
permanent self
this realization dissolves
the very logic that fuels religious conflict
if there's no permanent self to defend
and no essential difference between us and them
what exactly are we fighting for
but could such simple principles
non violence and inquiry
truly transform the heart of a killer
and change the fate of an empire
history provides us a stunning answer
in the form of one of humanity's most dramatic
transformations
to appreciate Ashoka's transformation
understand the man he was before Buddhism
court chronicles describe him as Chandashoka
Ashoka the cruel for good reason
he reportedly burned enemies alive
built a torture chamber called Ashoka's Hell
and eliminated 99 of his brothers to secure the throne
his armies were feared across the subcontinent
for their brutality
eight years into his reign
Ashoka launched his most ambitious conquest yet
against Kalinga
a prosperous independent kingdom in eastern India
The Kalinga War was particularly savage
Ashoka's own edicts record 150,000 people were deported
100,000 were killed and many more died
imagine the scene fields of corpses
villages burning families torn apart
all to satisfy one man's imperial ambition
then something remarkable happened
as Ashoka toured the battlefield afterward
the sight of corpses scattered across the land
the wailing of widows and orphans
the devastation of a once thriving region
it broke something in the Conqueror
standing amid the carnage he'd created
this ruthless emperor faced the ultimate question
was this power or merely destruction
in his own words carved into rock for posterity
after the Kalinga War the beloved of the gods
Ashoka began to follow Dharma
to love dharma and to give instruction
in dharma now the beloved of the gods
feels remorse for having conquered Kalinga
this remorse wasn't just a passing emotion
it triggered the most dramatic
royal transformation in history
Ashoka embraced Buddhism
and completely reversed his imperial policy
he abandoned conquest
and dedicated his reign to spreading
Buddhist principles through non
violent means instead of sending armies
he sent monks instead of building fortresses
he built hospitals
instead of imposing military rule
he carved ethical principles into stone pillars
across his vast empire
the Ashoka pillars and rock edicts still visible today
proclaimed revolutionary ideas
one edict stated all religions should reside everywhere
for all of them desire self control and purity of heart
this might be the earliest declaration
of religious tolerance by a major ruler in history
Ashoka demonstrated that Buddhist principles
could transform not just individuals
but entire empires
and he created a model for how Buddhism could spread
through ethical example rather than military might
Ashoka's conversion showed Buddhism could transform
even the most violent ruler
but can a philosophy spread across continents
without armies carrying it
the answer lies in how Buddhism traveled
the ancient highways of commerce
while many religions followed the sword
Buddhism followed the merchant's caravan
trade routes became Buddhism's superhighways
especially the vast network we now call the Silk Road
connecting China to Central Asia
India the Middle East and eventually Europe
let me take you to Dunhuang
China around the year 600 CE
a weary merchant caravan arrives at the oasis
after weeks crossing the Taklamakan Desert
their camels laden with silk and spices
destined for Persia the desert crossing has been brutal
sandstorms
bandits and the constant threat of death by thirst
but here at the edge of China
something remarkable greets them
a complex of caves carved into cliff faces
inside
magnificent Buddha statues reach toward the ceiling
walls covered in vibrant paintings
depicting the Buddha's life
the travelers find not just shelter
but a place to deposit valuables
exchange currency receive medical care
and restore their spirits
before the next leg of their journey
a local monk approaches the lead merchant
offering tea they share no common language
yet through translation
the merchant hears teachings that make sense to him
regardless of his culture or background
the focus on ethical business practices
on reducing suffering on finding inner peace
amid the chaos of desert crossings
this speaks to his daily reality
before departing the merchant leaves
a generous donation to expand the cave complex
ensuring future travelers will find the same refuge
scenes like this played out again and again
across Asia's trade routes
as historian Jerry Bentley noted
Buddhism traveled the Silk Roads
in the wallets and saddle bags of merchants
not on the backs of warriors
Buddhism offered practical benefits
for traveling merchants its emphasis on ethical conduct
created trust between trading partners
its monastery networks provided safe places to rest
store goods and exchange currency
and its universal principles
worked across different cultures
and languages
Buddhism also excelled at cultural adaptation
unlike religions that demanded exclusive allegiance
Buddhism allowed practitioners to maintain
local customs alongside Buddhist practice
the Buddhist concept of upaya
or skillful means gave missionaries flexibility
they could present Buddhism differently
depending on the audience
emphasizing philosophical aspects for the educated
meditation for the spiritually inclined
ethical teachings for rulers
and devotional practices for common people
Buddhism's journey along trade routes
demonstrates how ideas can spread without conquest
but what happened when those ideas
encountered established religions
and deeply rooted belief systems
the story of these encounters
reveals Buddhism's unique flexibility
when Buddhism encountered other belief systems
it typically sought harmony rather than conflict
but the outcomes varied dramatically
Buddhism's encounter with Islam proved more complex
and sometimes tragic Arab armies
conquering Central Asia
in the 7th and 8th centuries
encountered flourishing Buddhist civilizations
monasteries crumbled libraries burned
the magnificent Bamiyan Buddhas in Afghanistan
destroyed by the Taliban in 2001
were first damaged during these early Muslim conquests
why did Buddhism disappear from these regions
not because Buddhists fought and lost holy wars
but because Buddhist institutions
couldn't survive without royal patronage
the new Islamic rulers
naturally favored their own faith
throughout Southeast Asia
a different story unfolded
when Buddhism met indigenous animist traditions
and Hinduism remarkable synthesis occurred
Thai monks perform ceremonies honoring local spirits
in Myanmar Nat worship continues alongside Buddhism
on islands like Java and Bali
Hindu and Buddhist elements blend seamlessly
in China Buddhism encountered Confucianism and Taoism
two sophisticated philosophical systems
deeply embedded in Chinese culture
Buddhist missionaries responded not with force
but with skilled translation
they used Taoist terms to explain Buddhist concepts
making ideas like emptiness
sunyata
accessible through comparison with Taoist non action
Wu Wei
the result was a fascinating philosophical dialogue
Buddhism influenced Chinese thought
while being transformed into distinctively
Chinese schools like Chan Zen
Buddhism's journey to the west
represents another fascinating chapter
when Buddhist texts first reached Europe
in the 19th century they influenced philosophers
like Schopenhauer and Nietzsche
unlike earlier religious encounters
Buddhism entered western consciousness
primarily as philosophy rather than competing religion
in the 20th century figures like Alan Watts
DT Suzuki
and later
the Dalai Lama presented Buddhism to western audiences
not as a conversion target
but as a complementary practice
many Westerners today practice Buddhist meditation
while maintaining their original religious identity
a pattern of adoption rather than conversion
that mirrors Buddhism's historical spread in Asia
this pattern of adaptation rather than confrontation
characterized Buddhism spread
it preferred dialogue over debate
inclusion over exclusion and synthesis over conquest
but this peaceful history
makes the exceptions all the more jarring
because there have been cases
where Buddhism has been linked to violence
and extremism cases we need to examine honestly
if Buddhism promotes non violence so strongly
how do we explain Buddhist monks
calling for violence against Muslims
in Myanmar
or Sri Lankan Buddhists attacking Tamil Hindus
now to be clear
these violent voices do not represent all of Buddhism
far from it
across the world most Buddhist monks
teachers and practitioners
remain deeply committed to compassion
peace and non harming
what we're examining here is how any tradition
no matter how peaceful
can be distorted when it becomes fused with fear
power or nationalism
let's start with Myanmar
where nationalist Buddhist monks led by Ashin Wirathu
have fueled violence against Rohingya Muslims
Wirathu
once called the Buddhist bin Laden by time magazine
founded the 9 6 9 movement to boycott Muslim businesses
his inflammatory speeches
characterize Islam
as an existential threat to Buddhism
his rhetoric helped spark violence
that forced over 700,000 Rohingya to flee Myanmar
since 2017 in what the UN has described as
a textbook example of ethnic cleansing
these monks didn't chant for peace
they chanted for purity they didn't disarm delusion
they re armed it
they didn't follow the Buddha's path of non attachment
they clung desperately to nationalism
they didn't seek to end suffering they perpetuated it
this isn't Buddhism as the Buddha taught it
it's Buddhism hijacked by the very forces
it was designed to overcome fear
attachment and delusion
when Buddhist nationalists claim
Buddhism will disappear if we don't defend it
they directly contradict the Buddha's teaching
that hatred does not cease by hatred
but only by love
this is an eternal rule as the Dalai Lama said
regarding Myanmar Buddha would have definitely
helped the Rohingya Muslims
he would not discriminate
these cases of Buddhist nationalism can't be understood
without colonial context
Myanmar and Sri Lanka experienced British colonization
that privileged certain ethnic groups
and religions over others
creating lasting social divisions
Japanese militarism emerged as a response to western
imperial dominance in Asia
colonial powers often used religious differences
to implement divide and rule strategies
hardening boundaries between groups
that had previously coexisted
when these countries gained independence
religious nationalism became a way to assert
post colonial identity
against perceived foreign threats
the exceptions we examined Myanmar
Sri Lanka wartime Japan
all involved Buddhism
becoming entangled with nationalism
this fusion of religious and national identity
creates a dangerous dynamic
a perceived threat to the nation
becomes a threat to religion
and vice versa
these exceptions
don't disprove Buddhism's peaceful track record
they highlight what happens when any belief system
even one founded on non violence
becomes entangled with nationalism
and identity politics
the Buddha's teachings
included a built in solution to such distortions
the practice of meditation itself
which creates internal conditions for peace
while other religions pray for peace
Buddhists train their minds for it
this isn't just spiritual talk
it's practical psychology backed by modern science
at Buddhism's core lies a simple but profound insight
violence begins in the mind with thoughts of anger
hatred and division so peace must begin there too
in the Buddha's words
all that we are arises with our thoughts
with our thoughts we make the world
let's try a brief experiment right now
just for 20 seconds notice your breathing
feel the sensation of air
entering and leaving your nostrils
when your mind wanders
and it will gently bring it back to your breath
that pause
that was a seed of peace in that space no war can grow
what you just experienced
is the foundation of Buddhist meditation
creating awareness of your mental processes
now imagine
extending this ability to moments when anger arises
you'd notice the anger but wouldn't be controlled by it
this simple practice
scaled across millions of practitioners
creates a fundamentally
different relationship to conflict
than faith's focus
primarily on belief
Buddhist meditation
directly addresses the root causes of aggression
it doesn't just tell you to be peaceful
it trains your brain to
respond differently to provocations
modern neuroscience echoes what monks intuited
centuries ago
regular meditation physically changes the brain
in ways that reduce aggression
neuroscientists at the university of Wisconsin
measured brain activity in experienced meditators
they found increased activity
in areas associated with positive emotions
and reduced activity in aggression related areas
even in war zones meditation creates islands of peace
during Cambodia's bloody civil war
monk Maha Ghosananda
led peace walks through active combat areas
teaching meditation to villagers
caught in the crossfire
one refugee described the impact
before meditation
when I thought of the Khmer Rouge killing my family
I wanted to take revenge after meditation
I still see my family killed
but I don't feel the same hatred
this transformation
from vengeful victim to peaceful survivor
represents Buddhism's most profound gift to humanity
not just a philosophy
but a practical path from hatred to healing
this built in technology for peace
gives Buddhism a unique advantage
in preventing violence
it doesn't just prohibit aggression
it systematically uproots its psychological causes
after thousands of years through empires and upheavals
Buddhism spread without swords
but what can this ancient strategy teach us now
in a world still addicted to conflict
first
ideas spread better through attraction than coercion
Buddhism didn't conquer half of Asia with armies
it won hearts and minds by addressing real
human suffering
second
Buddhism shows the power of adapting to local cultures
without compromising core principles
Buddhism didn't demand that Chinese
people stop being Chinese
or Tibetans abandon their cultural identity
it offered tools
that could work within existing frameworks
third Buddhism demonstrates that focusing on practice
rather than belief creates more stable foundations
instead of demanding allegiance to unprovable claims
Buddhism offers techniques
you can verify through personal experience
fourth Buddhism reveals
the danger of mixing spiritual traditions
with national identity
when spiritual practices become markers of national
or ethnic identity
the universal message gets corrupted into an us
versus them mentality
fifth Buddhism shows how internal transformation
precedes external peace
the Buddhist approach
recognizes that social change begins
with individual minds now
imagine if the world's most entrenched conflicts
were approached not with flags or faith
but with one guiding question
how do we reduce suffering
of course these conflicts are incredibly complex
rooted in history identity
trauma and pain on all sides
we're not here to take political stances
or simplify them but from a Buddhist lens
we can ask how might a different kind of thinking
focused on reducing suffering
rather than proving who's right
shift the conversation
take for instance
the longstanding conflict between Israelis
and Palestinians both sides claim exclusive
divine rights to the same land
what if instead
they followed the Buddha's approach of non
attachment to views
what if they prioritized reducing suffering
over establishing who has the right claim
or consider Ukraine and Russia
a conflict partly fueled by competing
historical narratives and identity claims
a Buddhist approach would ask
how can we minimize suffering right now
rather than who is historically right
perhaps most importantly
Buddhism demonstrates that peace isn't just a goal
it's a strategy
the Buddha taught that means and ends are inseparable
peaceful ends require peaceful means
violent methods
inevitably corrupt even the noblest objectives
in a world
still torn by religious and ideological conflicts
Buddhism's peaceful spread
reminds us that the most powerful revolutions begin
not with swords but with insights
ideas once carried in begging bowls
now shape entire nations not by force but by awakening
now
that you've seen how Buddhism spread across continents
without holy wars
I invite you to experiment with these principles
in your own life try a simple 5 minute meditation
notice how your mind works when you're angry
see if creating space between emotion and action
changes your responses to daily frustrations
you don't need to become Buddhist
to benefit from these insights
the Buddha's approach to peace works
regardless of your beliefs
if you found this exploration valuable
please hit the like button
and subscribe to Buddha's wisdom
for more videos
that bring ancient wisdom to modern challenges
in the comments I'd love to hear your thoughts
have you experienced the peace that meditation brings
do you see parallels between Buddhist spread
and other peaceful movements
until next time
may you find peace within yourself first
and help create it in our troubled world
thanks for watching Buddha's wisdom
I'm Matt and I'll see you in the next video
stay curious stay kind
and may your insight be your revolution
peace is the highest bliss
the Buddha