imagine a religion that challenges the
very idea of
God a tradition that says the path to
Enlightenment lies not in divine
intervention but in our own hearts and
Minds well buckle up because that's
exactly what Buddhism proposes and it
sparked some serious controversy over
the centuries what's up wisdom Seekers
Matt here and today we're embarking on a
journey to the heart of one of the most
provocative questions in spiritual
history why don't Buddhists believe in
[Music]
God now before we dive in let me be
clear this video isn't about pushing any
agenda or disrespecting anyone's beliefs
Buddhism is all about free inquiry and
questioning everything even its own
teachings so whether you're a devout
believer a hardcore skeptic or just
curious about different perspectives
you're in the right
place our mission is to to explore to
challenge our assumptions and to open
our minds to new possibilities you ready
let's
go first off let's define our terms when
we say God we usually mean an all
powerful all- knowing Creator who rules
the universe right well here's the thing
the Buddha himself never really focused
on this idea he was more interested in
solving the problem of human suffering
uffing in the Here and Now not
speculating about ultimate origins in
fact when asked about the nature of God
and the universe the Buddha often
remained silent saying these questions
were irrelevant to the path of
Liberation fast forward a few centuries
and we find most Buddhist Traditions
embracing a non-theistic
worldview now this doesn't necessarily
mean they're atheists some Buddhists
believe in various deities and
supernatural beings but these are seen
more as simp symbolic representations of
enlightened qualities not as all
powerful creators so why the departure
from the Creator God idea well at its
core Buddhism is all about
self-empowerment the Buddha taught that
every single one of us has the innate
wisdom and compassion to free ourselves
from suffering we don't need to rely on
any external savior or deity the key to
Liberation lies within it's like having
a superhero hiding inside us just
waiting to be
Unleashed this idea of radical person
personal responsibility is a total game
Cher it means that our happiness and
spiritual growth are in our own hands we
can't just pray or make offerings and
expect some Divine being to solve our
problems the Buddha's final words were
be a lamp unto yourself in other words
trust your own wisdom question
everything and don't blindly follow any
leader or doctrine but wait it gets even
more interesting Buddhists also believe
in karma and rebirth the idea that our
actions have consequences that shape our
future experiences both in this life and
Beyond it's like a cosmic game of cause
and effect and here's the kicker there's
no need for a Divine judge or Heavenly
accountant keeping score we're the ones
who set our own destiny in motion
reaping what we sow this concept of
Karma ties into another core Buddhist
teaching the idea of nonself or an Nat
buckle up because this one's a doozy
basically Buddhism says that everything
including our sense of self is
impermanent and constantly changing
there's no fixed Eternal Soul that was
created by some Divine being instead
we're more like ever shifting streams of
thoughts feelings and
experiences if this sounds trippy you're
not alone philosophers have grappled
with this idea for centuries but the
Buddha's point was that clinging to a
false sense of self is a major source of
suffering by letting go of our ego and
embracing the flow of change we can find
true Freedom now all of this might sound
pretty abstract and intellectual but the
Buddha was all about direct experience
he didn't want us to just take his word
for it he wanted us to taste the truth
for ourselves that's why Buddhism places
so much emphasis on meditation and
mindful living by observing our own
minds and cultivating awareness we can
cut through the Illusions and discover
the ultimate nature of reality
and that's the Crux of the matter
Buddhists believe that the highest truth
is beyond words Concepts and even
beliefs it can only be known through
direct Insight so rather than arguing
about the existence of God Buddhism
invites us to embark on a personal
journey of
self-discovery it's like a spiritual
treasure hunt with the Ultimate Prize
being the realization of our own
boundless wisdom and compassion this
emphasis on Direct experience over
belief has led to some pretty radical
developments in Buddhist history take
the story of the Buddha's disciple
saruta one day a Wandering aesthetic
challenged saruta saying you Buddhists
don't believe in God so your path is
incomplete saruta replied friend even if
a Creator God exists that's no reason to
abandon the Buddhist path we follow the
Buddha's teachings because we've seen
for ourselves that they lead to peace
and Liberation not because of Blind
Faith or consider the kalas sua a famous
Buddhist scripture where the Buddha
tells a group of Skeptics not to blindly
believe anything even his own teachings
he urges them to question investigate
and test the truth for themselves don't
go by reports by Legends by Traditions
by scripture by logical conjecture by
inference by analogies by agreement
through pondering views by probability
or by the thought this monk is our
teacher when when you know for
yourselves that certain things are UNH
wholesome wrong and bad then give them
up and when you know for yourselves that
certain things are wholesome and good
then accept them and follow
them wow we've covered a lot of ground
today the Buddhist perspective on God
might be controversial but it challenges
us to rethink our assumptions about
spirituality instead of relying on
external saviors or abstract beliefs
Buddhism urges us to look within to
question question deeply and to trust
our own
experience whether you agree with these
ideas or not you got to admit that's a
pretty bold and empowering approach of
course this is just a taste of the rich
dialogue between Buddhism and theism and
hey don't just take my word for it I
encourage you to investigate these ideas
for yourself with an open and critical
mind so my fellow truth Seekers what do
you make of all this do you find the
Buddhist perspective intriguing
challenging or maybe even
liberating let me know in the comments
and if you enjoyed this exploration be
sure to hit that like button and
subscribe to Buddha's wisdom for more
mind expanding
content remember the Ultimate answers
aren't found in any holy book or YouTube
video they're waiting to be discovered
in the depths of your own awareness so
keep questioning keep practicing and
Trust in the power of your own wisdom
stay curious stay compassionate and I'll
see you on the next adventure