pause this video right now
I'm serious hit pause now
close your eyes and put your hand on your chest
feel what's there
you feel that that restless energy
that low grade anxiety humming in the background
that need for something
anything to make you feel complete
that's fire
and it's been burning inside you your entire life
most of us mistake that burn for drive or stress
we call it motivation or being human
they're wrong 2,500 years ago
a man named Buddha discovered this fire
burning inside himself
figured out how to extinguish it completely
and then taught 1,000 other people to do the same thing
in real time with one speech
what's up wisdom seekers
Matt here and for the next 20 minutes
I'm going to walk you through that exact speech
not so you can learn about it
but so you can experience it right now on yourself
by the end the fire may still flicker
but it won't run the show ready
here's how he pulled it off
before we get into Buddha's story
we need to map your personal fire
because his teaching only works
if you're honest about what's actually burning
so here's what I want you to do
as I describe each fire
notice if it flares up in your body
fire No. 1 the craving fire
think about your phone right now
when was the last time you checked it
feel that urge to look that's craving fire
it burns every time you want something you don't have
fire No. 2 the rejection fire
think about someone who hurt you
someone who didn't give you what you deserved
feel that heat rising in your chest
that's rejection fire it burns every time
reality doesn't match your expectations
fire No. 3
the confusion fire
think about your future
all those decisions you need to make
all that uncertainty feel that anxious buzzing
that's confusion fire
it burns every time you don't know what's real
or what to do next
these three fires
they're what Buddha called the fires of lust
hatred and delusion and they've been burning
inside humans for thousands of years
the question isn't whether you have these fires
you do the question is
are you ready to see them clearly
because that's exactly what happened
on a Hillside in ancient India
when Buddha delivered the most psychologically
devastating speech in human history
imagine this
you're sitting on a raw Hillside in the Ganges Basin
the air is thick with smoke from dying fire alters
around you sit 1,000 men
who've spent their entire lives
believing that external fire rituals could save them
they weren't stupid
they were the spiritual elite of ancient India
the Kassapa brothers Uruvela
Nadi and Gaya commanded armies of devoted followers
who genuinely believed their teachers
had achieved enlightenment
but here's what's wild they had the exact same fires
burning inside them that you do
Uruvela Kassapa burned with spiritual pride
his followers burned with
the need for approval from their guru
with fear
that they'd wasted their lives on the wrong path
with confusion about what was actually true
the only difference between you and those 1000 monks
is that
they thought external fire rituals would save them
you think external achievements will save you
same burning different alters
Buddha looked at this crowd and realized something
you can't put out internal fire by worshipping
external fire you can only put it out
by seeing it for what it really is
so he gave them a teaching
that would shatter everything
they believed about themselves
starting with the fire they could actually see
Buddha's voice cuts through the Hillside silence
he's calm almost clinical
like a doctor naming symptoms
now I want you to imagine he's talking directly to you
because he is
they expected hymns to sacred flame
he turned the spotlight on their nervous systems
stop look at your eyes right now
how much have you used them today
to consume content to compare yourself to others
to search for something that will make you feel better
your eyes aren't just seeing
they're burning with the fire of craving
every time you scroll you're feeding the flames
Buddha goes deeper it's not just what you see
it's how your mind processes what you see
the split second when your brain decides
I want that or I hate this or why can't I have that
that's the burning
your tongue
burning with words you wish you could take back
words that came from fire not wisdom
and here's the big one
your thoughts themselves are on fire right now
as you're listening to this
part of your mind is probably burning
with the need to check your phone
or wondering if this is actually going to help
or judging yourself
for having these problems in the first place
that's mind fire
the running commentary the endless wanting
the never ending story of not enough
Buddha asks
and here's where it gets real
check in with your body right now
do you feel it
that low level burning that never quite goes away
that's not anxiety that's not stress
that's not just life
that's the fire of constant wanting lust
constant rejecting hatred and constant confusion
delusion burning through every moment of your existence
Buddha is pointing directly at the fire in your chest
right now and saying there
right there that's not life
that's suffering
and you have the power to see it clearly
but here's the key that those 1,000 monks discovered
seeing thus the instructed
noble disciple grows disenchanted with the burning
becomes dispassionate toward it
and through dispassion finds freedom
you don't fight the fire you don't feed the fire
you simply see it for what it is
become disinterested in it and watch it burn itself out
according to the Pali Canon
here's what happened next
but let me tell you what this actually felt like
imagine you've been carrying a 100 pound backpack
your entire life
you've gotten so used to the weight
that you forgot it was there
and then suddenly someone points to it and says
you can set that down now
that's what happened on that Hillside
one monk later described it as
the moment he realized
he didn't have to be afraid of his own thoughts anymore
another said it felt like waking up from a nightmare
he didn't know he was having
they weren't fighting their minds
they weren't suppressing their desires
they simply saw the burning clearly
and stopped being burned by it
the fire was still there
but it lost its power to consume them
now here's what I want you to do right now pause
notice the heat in the chest
the pull in the gut
feel that burning in your chest again
but this time
instead of trying to fix it or get rid of it
just see it see how it wants your attention
see how it promises
that if you just scroll one more time
buy one more thing achieve one more goal
it will finally be satisfied
see how it lies the fire doesn't want satisfaction
it wants fuel and every time you feed it
it gets stronger but when you see it clearly
when you become genuinely disinterested in its promises
something shifts the fire is still burning
but you're not burning with it
that's your fire sermon moment right here right now
those 1,000 monks didn't just have a nice
spiritual experience and go back to their old lives
they developed a practice
a way to see fire clearly every single day
here's how you do it
step 1 name the fire
when that burning starts in your chest
don't distract yourself don't feed it
name it craving fire
rejection fire
confusion fire
step 2 feel where it burns
where exactly do you feel it
in your body chest
throat stomach
just notice
don't try to change it
step 3 see what it wants
what is this fire trying to get you to do
check your phone buy something
start an argument get someone's approval
see the wanting clearly
step 4 become dispassionate
this is the key you don't fight the fire
you don't feed it you
become genuinely uninterested in what it's promising
like watching a movie you've seen a thousand times
step 5 watch it burn out without fuel
fire dies when you stop feeding craving
it fades when you stop feeding rejection
it dissolves when you stop feeding confusion
clarity appears
this isn't theory this is the exact method Buddha used
the same one that liberated 1000 people simultaneously
and it works right now on you
most people think Buddha's fire
sermon was his final word on liberation
it wasn't after this mass awakening
Buddha gave those 1,000 monks a follow up teaching
that completely flipped everything
they thought they knew about enlightenment
he taught them that even clinging to the one who sees
clearly is a subtle burn
that even clinging to enlightenment must be abandoned
that the deepest freedom comes
when you realize there was never anyone there
to be burned in the first place
the follow up teaching
that made even these newly enlightened monks
question everything
they thought they knew about freedom itself
later traditions
built whole schools on the implications
of what came next and that is a story for another night
but right now you have everything you need
the fire is visible the method is clear
the only question is
whether you're ready to stop being consumed by flames
that exist only in your mind
notice any shift you just experienced
the same teaching that transformed 1,000 people
2,500 years ago
if this shifted something in you
subscribe and turn on notifications
we're diving deep into practices that actually change
your life not just your thoughts
comment below with one word
describing the fire that burns strongest in you
right now let's see it clearly together
and if you wanna know
what Buddha's most radical teaching was
the one that makes even enlightenment look like another
trap that's up next
until then remember
you're burning but you don't have to be consumed
the fire has no power over you once you see it clearly
peace