okay picture me trying to walk through a wall right now
ouch solid wall right
wrong
scientists just proved that this solid wall
and everything else around you
is basically a grand illusion
and guess who called this thousands of years ago
yep Buddha himself
was dropping quantum physics knowledge
while people were still figuring out
which berries wouldn't kill them
hey everyone
Matt here and I promise
I didn't hit my head too hard on that wall
today's revelation is going to mess with your brain
way more than any wall collision
remember last month when we talked about
Einstein's secret connection to Buddhism?
that was just the appetizer
today we're serving the main course
and trust me
reality itself is on the menu
see those tiny particles that make up everything
they're basically acting like my little sister
completely changing their behavior
the moment someone watches them
no joke actual scientists are scratching their heads
because particles
straight up decide to do different things
just because we're looking
Buddhist masters weren't just sitting under trees
looking peaceful
they were basically quantum physics prophets
describing this exact weird behavior
centuries before
we had microscopes powerful enough to see it
in the next few minutes you'll discover
why Einstein freaked out about these discoveries
why Schrödinger
had to drag his poor cat into this mess
and
why these invisible particles prove that your mind is
basically a reality bending superpower
no I'm not quoting Doctor Strange
this is actual science
meeting ancient wisdom in the most incredible way
and now let me show you
the experiment that made Einstein lose his mind
imagine two identical particles
seemingly simple right
well what happens next is so bizarre
it made even Einstein himself say
what the quantum!
okay
he didn't exactly say that
but what you're about to see
made the world's greatest physicist
question everything he knew about reality
let's start with
the weirdest experiment in scientific history
the one that still makes
physicists wake up in a cold sweat
remember in the matrix
when Neo sees reality isn't actually real
well this experiment makes that look like a
kid's magic trick
imagine shooting tiny particles at a wall
with two slits in it behind the wall
there's a screen that shows where these particles land
now if I threw tennis balls at these slits
we'd get exactly what you'd expect
two neat strips where the balls went through
but when scientists did this with quantum particles
something impossible happened
instead of two strips
they got this weird striped pattern
like waves on a beach
when two ripples meet
they create these amazing interference patterns
you know when you drop two rocks in a pond
and the ripples cross each other
making that cool diamond shape
that's exactly what these particles were doing
except they were single particles
each particle went through both slits at the same time
and then interfered with itself
if you're thinking "that's not how reality works"
you're right
that's exactly what Einstein said
he was so disturbed by this randomness
in quantum mechanics that he famously declared
he believed there had to be some hidden rules
making everything predictable
in fact this experiment made him so uncomfortable
he spent years trying to prove it wrong
here's where it gets proper weird
scientists thought let's watch these particles
to see which slit they actually go through
and this is when reality broke
the moment they observed the particles
the pattern disappeared
just by watching
they changed how the particles behaved
consider the implications
these tiny particles know when we're watching them
well
it's not that these particles know in a conscious sense
but their behavior changes based on measurement
suggesting a fundamental link
between observation and reality
it's like reality
itself only decides what to do when someone's watching
just like those agents in the matrix
popping into existence when someone looks
and hey
if you're into how the matrix and Buddhism connect
stick around we've got a mind bending episode
coming up in our pop culture series about exactly that
scientists tried to outsmart these particles
they waited until after
the particles went through the slits
to measure them
guess what happened
the particles somehow changed their past behaviour
it's like
they knew they were going to be measured in the future
and retroactively decided how to behave
this is called the delayed choice experiment
and it challenges
our understanding of cause and effect
imagine deciding to record a basketball game
after it's already finished
and the players somehow change their moves
based on your choice to watch later
that's the delayed choice experiment in action
but we're not done yet see
light does this too sometimes it acts like a wave
making these interference patterns
other times
it behaves like tiny particles called photons
it's literally both at the same time
until we look at it
this made Einstein pull his remaining hair out
he called it spooky action at a distance
now flashback thousands of years
Buddhist masters were teaching that reality isn't fixed
until it's observed a concept called Pratityasamutpada
or dependent origination
in the Yogacara school of Buddhism
they specifically taught that consciousness
and perceived reality are inseparable
that nothing exists independently of the observing mind
they said
the observer and the observed can't be separated
everyone thought they were speaking in metaphors
turns out they were describing quantum physics
before we even had a word for it
ready to go even deeper
because what you just learned is only the beginning
and what comes next
will make this look like child's play
so if particles change when we look at them
what does that mean for everything around us
take a second and look at your surroundings
that chair your phone
maybe a coffee mug they're all made of particles
and get this
according to quantum physics
none of it exists
in a definite state until someone observes it
sounds crazy right
scientists call this the observer effect
let's break it down with the most famous
and controversial thought experiment ever
Schrödinger's cat picture this
a cat is sealed in a box with a device
that has a 50% chance of releasing deadly poison
according to quantum physics
until someone opens that box and looks inside
the cat exists in both states simultaneously
alive and dead
I know pretty dark for a physics lesson
but stay with me
Schrödinger created this thought experiment
to show how ridiculous quantum mechanic seemed
how could something be in two opposite states at once
but here's the plot twist
he accidentally proved
quantum physics was even weirder than anyone thought
Einstein hated this so much
he spent years arguing about it with his friend
Niels Bohr he famously said
"do you really believe the moon isn't there
if you're not looking at it"
he also wrote "I like to think the moon is there
even if I am not looking at it"
Poor Einstein the universe turned out to be
way stranger than even he could imagine
but this isn't just theory anymore
in groundbreaking 2021 experiments at TU Delft
scientists created a quantum drum
the width of a human hair
that existed in two states simultaneously
both vibrating and still
this wasn't just theoretical anymore
they actually achieved quantum superposition
with an object large enough to see with a microscope
they've also shown that
atoms won't decay until someone observes them
it's like reality itself is camera shy
this discovery revolutionizes our understanding
in the Lankavatara Sutra
one of Buddhism's most profound texts
Buddha explains that the world we see
is created by our consciousness
he teaches that objects don't have a fixed
independent existence
they only become real when our mind observes them
he even used the metaphor of waves
emerging from an ocean of possibilities
exactly like what quantum physicists call
the wave function collapse
and it goes even deeper
The Avatamsaka Sutra describes a reality
where every particle contains all other particles
exactly like quantum entanglement
the Heart Sutra's famous phrase
perfectly describes quantum field theory's discovery
that particles are just excitations
in underlying fields these aren't vague similarities
the texts describe specific phenomena
that quantum physics wouldn't confirm for millennia
now some physicists and scholars argue
these parallels might be oversimplified
they point out that quantum mechanics is about specific
mathematical models and experimental observations
while Buddhist teachings focus on human experience
and the nature of consciousness
while the similarities are striking
it's important to understand
they developed in very different contexts
with different goals
let's try something together
close your eyes for a moment
now open them
according to quantum physics
everything you see just collapsed into reality
from an infinite sea of possibilities
just like Buddha described
consciousness isn't just observing reality
it's participating in creating it
but if our minds have this much power of a reality
what else are they capable of
well that's exactly what we're about to find out
remember our electron going through two slits at once
that was just the beginning
scientists decided to try something even crazier
they fired one single electron at the slits
just one and somehow
that single electron
created an interference pattern with itself
it's like one person high fiving themselves
from multiple directions at once
this broke physics so badly
that scientists had to come up with a whole
new interpretation the Copenhagen interpretation
basically they said
reality exists as a cloud of possibilities
until consciousness collapses it into one outcome
but many scientists hated this idea
why?
because it suggests consciousness
itself might be the foundation of reality
let me say that again
your consciousness might be creating reality
not in some woo woo way
but according to hardcore physics mathematics
this is called the quantum measurement problem
and it's driving physicists nuts
see no one can explain how observation collapses
quantum possibilities into reality
they know it happens they can measure it
but they can't explain why
now ancient Buddhist masters like Nagarjuna
weren't just theorizing about this
they were demonstrating it
in the sacred texts there are accounts of masters
who could alter physical reality
through the power of their consciousness
people thought these were just spiritual stories
until quantum physics showed that consciousness
really does affect physical reality
modern day Buddhist masters
like the
Dalai Lama aren't surprised by quantum physics at all
during a mind science conference in 2015
when physicists explained quantum non locality to him
he smiled and said
"in Buddhist philosophy
particularly in the Madhyamaka view
we find detailed explanations of how things arise
through interdependence
and the way things exist only through designation
rather than from their own side"
the scientists were stunned
here was centuries old wisdom
describing their cutting edge discoveries
think this is all theoretical
the quantum observer effect
is already revolutionizing technology
quantum computers use this principle to solve problems
regular computers can't handle
scientists are developing quantum encryption
that's impossible to hack
because the very act of observing the data changes it
even medical imaging is being transformed by quantum
sensors
that can detect diseases earlier than ever before
want to experience this quantum weirdness yourself
try this focus intensely on any object near you
really look at its details
now realize
those particles you're looking at
are actually undefined
until your consciousness interacts with them
you're not just observing reality
you're participating in creating it moment by moment
but if consciousness can collapse
quantum possibilities into reality
there's an even more fundamental question
we need to ask
what exactly is this reality that we're collapsing
the answer reveals a truth so profound
that it challenges everything we think we know about
the physical world
here's a fact that will mess with your head
if you took all the actual solid matter in your body
and squished it together removing all the empty space
you'd be smaller than a grain of rice
that's right 99.99% of you is literally nothing
but how can this be true
pick up something solid feels real right
well here comes the quantum plot twist
what we think of as solid matter
is actually just forces pushing against each other
like when you try to push two magnets together
you feel something solid
but there's literally nothing between them
so what's really there
scientists call them quantum fields
think of it like a video game
the entire game world is just ones and zeros
until the computer
processes them into what looks like solid objects
our reality works the same way
these quantum fields are like the game's code
constantly creating and destroying particles
making what we think is solid matter
these quantum fields are everywhere
creating what we think is solid matter
that coffee cup you're holding
it's actually the electromagnetic field
pushing against the electron fields in your hand
your car isn't a solid object
it's countless quantum fields
dancing together to create the illusion of solidity
even light isn't just waves or particles
it's ripples in the electromagnetic field
like waves on an invisible ocean
and this is where Buddhism drops the mic
2500 years ago Buddha taught about sunyata emptiness
this doesn't mean nothing exists
but rather
that everything we perceive as solid and independent
is actually made up of interconnected
ever changing parts just as quantum physics reveals
particles as waves of probability
rather than fixed entities
Sunyata teaches that reality is fluid
dependent on our perception and interactions
monks were laughed at for centuries for saying this
now
quantum physics is proving they were right all along
think about your favorite game character
they seem solid on screen
they can jump fight
collect items but zoom in close enough
and what do you find just pixels
zoom in further just electrical signals
that's exactly how our reality works
what feels solid is actually mostly empty space
filled with probability waves
let's get personal for a second
your body your bones
everything you think is solid
is actually more like a hologram
made of quantum fields
you're not sitting on a chair right now
you're floating on a force field
of quantum possibilities
and those atoms making up your body
they're not even in one place at a time
and just when you thought it couldn't get weirder
remember how we said
quantum particles only become definite when observed
well
this means your entire body only takes definite form
because consciousness is observing it
without observation
you'd be a cloud of quantum possibilities
but if everything is empty
if nothing is truly solid
then what's really real
the answer to that is about to turn
everything you know about reality
completely upside down
if reality is empty and nothing is solid
how does anything work at all
well Buddha didn't just tell us
everything was empty he gave us the source code
five fundamental laws
that control everything in the universe
the five Niyamas
first is Utu Niyama the physical laws
when you drop your phone gravity pulls it down
but at the quantum level
those same laws let particles tunnel through barriers
and appear in multiple places simultaneously
it's why your GPS needs quantum corrections
to stay accurate
then there's Bija Niyama
Bija Niyama governs biological systems
remember how we said observation changes reality
it's why plants know which way is up without eyes
using quantum processes in their cells
it's how monarch butterflies navigate
using quantum
entangled molecules as internal compasses
living things are quantum observers
constantly collapsing wave functions
creating reality through interaction
just like our double slit experiment showed us
No. 3 is Kamma Niyama and no
it's not just about good and bad karma
it's about quantum cause and effect
when paired electrons remain connected across galaxies
they're demonstrating this law
your actions literally
create quantum ripples that affect the entire universe
even Einstein called this spooky
see
Citta Niyama explains consciousness and quantum observation
it's why double slit experiments change
based on measurement every choice you make
collapses infinite possibilities into one reality
you're doing it right now as you watch this video
Buddha taught that mind and matter aren't separate
that consciousness shapes reality
2,000 years later
quantum physics proved this with the observer effect
coincidence I think not
finally there's Dhamma Niyama
the fundamental nature of reality itself
remember that quantum field creating your coffee cup
that same field extends through the entire universe
nothing exists in isolation
everything is connected through these quantum fields
exactly as Buddha taught
here's the fascinating part
while these parallels are compelling
we should approach them with both excitement
and careful consideration
some scientists argue that quantum physics
and Buddhist wisdom though both profound
might be describing different levels of reality
the quantum world operates by precise
mathematical rules
while Buddhist insights come from deep meditation
and philosophical analysis
maybe the truth lies in understanding both perspectives
each valuable in its own way
rather than trying to make them exactly the same
so what does this mean for you
everything you see everything you touch
every moment of your life
is running on the same principles
you're not just living in reality
you're actively participating in creating it
your consciousness isn't just observing the universe
it's part of the code that makes it real
and if you understand this
if you really get what this means
everything changes
because once you know the code
once you see how reality really works
you can never look at your world the same way again
these aren't just cool facts
understanding quantum reality
can transform how you approach everyday challenges
when you're stuck on a problem
remember quantum superposition
multiple solutions can exist simultaneously
until you observe them
feeling disconnected
quantum entanglement shows us
were fundamentally connected to everything around us
worried about making the wrong choice
every decision you make
is literally creating one reality
from infinite possibilities
just like quantum observation collapses
probability waves into definite states
ready for the final revelation
because what comes next will show you how to
use this knowledge to transform your entire reality
so here's where everything comes together
remember that wall I tried to walk through at the start
well now you know it's not really solid
nothing is
reality isn't fixed it's a dance between consciousness
and quantum possibilities
you're not just a passive observer in this universe
you're an active participant in creating reality
every time you focus your attention
every time you make an observation
you're collapsing quantum possibilities into
actual reality
just like those ancient Buddhist masters understood
think about what this really means
your consciousness isn't just along for the ride
it's fundamental to how reality works
those quantum particles that empty space
those probability waves
they're all waiting for you to interact with them
to make them real
want to experience this power
close your eyes for a moment
now open them
everything you see
just emerged from an infinite sea of possibilities
because your consciousness interacted with it
you just participated in creating reality
and you do this every single moment of every day
the ancient Buddhist weren't just being metaphorical
when they said the mind creates the world
they were describing the deepest truth about reality
that science has ever discovered
and now you know it too
so what are you going to do with this knowledge
how will you use your reality shaping consciousness
will you stay trapped in old patterns of thinking
or will you embrace your role
as an active creator of reality
if you want to explore more
amazing connections between modern science
and ancient Buddhist wisdom
hit that subscribe button and the notification bell
because trust me what we cover today
is just the beginning of how weird reality gets
until then remember
you're not just watching reality unfold
you're helping create it
and that that changes everything
see you in the Quantum Realm