[Music]
what if the Greatest Story Ever Told has
a missing chapter that could change
everything we know about history and
spirituality imagine Jesus the central
figure of Christianity traveling across
Asia learning from Buddhist monks and
gaining wisdom in the mystical lands of
India sounds unbelievable
right but what if there's more to this
story than meets the eye stick around as
we unravel the mystery of Jesus's Lost
Years and explore the mind-bending
theory that connects him with ancient
Buddhist teachings hey there curious
minds Matt here from Buddha's wisdom our
comment sections been buzzing with talk
about Jesus in India our previous videos
was Jesus a bodhisatwa and why Buddhists
don't believe in God sparked some
intriguing
discussions So today we're exploring
further into this fascinating topic
here's the deal young Jesus vanishes
from the Bible story and reappears at 30
ready to change the world but where was
he was he trekking across Asia mastering
meditation or inventing ancient
superfoods some folks Think Jesus might
have hit the Silk Road for a spiritual
Adventure in India soaking up Buddhist
wisdom sounds wild right or does it
we're about to explore this internet
breaking Theory that's got everyone
talking grab a snack and get comfy we're
on a journey that's part ancient mystery
part spiritual exploration and 100%
mindbending now before we jump in Let's
Get Serious for a moment this video
explores theories and ideas not
established historical facts we're
discussing Concepts some might find
controversial so keep an open mind our
goal isn't to challenge or change
anyone's beliefs we're exploring
interesting ideas gaining traction
online what we're about to discuss is
speculation based on various sources
some not accepted by mainstream
historians or religious
Scholars approach this information
critically do your own research and draw
your own
conclusions respecting diverse beliefs
and promoting understanding is key if
this topic grabs you consider it a
starting point for further learning not
a definitive
answer chapter 1
The Missing Years of
Jesus all right let's set the stage for
our historical mystery we're talking
about Jesus of Nazareth the central
figure of
Christianity the gospels give us a
detailed account of Jesus's birth and
early childhood we hear about the manger
the wise men and even a 12-year-old
Jesus impressing Scholars at the temple
Luke
24647 tells us after 3 days they found
him in the temple courts sitting among
the teachers listening to to them and
asking them questions everyone who heard
him was amazed at his understanding and
his
answers but then radio silence it's like
someone hit the pause button on Jesus's
story we go from this Prodigy kid to
nothing zip
NADA the gospels skip ahead and suddenly
we're dealing with a 30-year-old Jesus
fast forward about 18 years and Jesus is
back on the scene he's getting baptized
by John in the River Gathering disciples
and kicking off his ministry Matthew
3:13 picks up the story then Jesus Came
From Galilee to the Jordan to be
baptized by John but what about those
Missing
Years that's a long time to be off the
grid especially for someone so
important this Gap in Jesus's timeline
has puzzled Scholars theologians and
curious minds for centuries we're
talking about the formative years of his
life
his teens and 20s for most of us that's
when we figure out who we are and what
we want to do with our lives it's when
we form our beliefs challenge our
assumptions and start to see the world
differently so what was Jesus up to
during this crucial
period chapter 2 the Buddhist connection
Theory now here's where things get
really interesting some people suggest
that during these Lost Years Jesus might
have traveled far beyond the borders of
Judea they proposed that he journeyed
East possibly as far as India where he
encountered Buddhist teachings and
philosophy I know what you're thinking
Jesus in India come on Matt it sounds
like the plot of a Dan Brown novel right
but hang on because this Theory isn't as
new or as crazy as you might think it's
been around for over a century and while
it's certainly not mainstream it's
captured the imagination of many SCH and
spiritual
Seekers this Theory first hit the scene
in a big way back in
1894 a Russian journalist named Nicholas
novich claimed he'd found ancient
Tibetan Scrolls that told the story of
St Issa supposedly another name for
Jesus according to novich these Scrolls
described isa's journey to India and his
studies there of course nich's claims
were met with more than a few raised
eyebrows many scholars called BS and
some still do
but the idea stuck around popping up
again and again over the years fast
forward to Modern Times And this
theories got new life thanks to the
internet and some popular
documentaries the BBC's Jesus in India
from 2008 brought the idea to a whole
new audience it's like the theory got a
Netflix reboot and people are binging
it Chapter 3 The Legend of St
Issa let's talk about the Legend of St
Issa it's like the ancient world's
version of a viral story spreading
across continents and captivating
imaginations for centuries so who's this
Issa character well according to some
Eastern Traditions Issa is another name
for Jesus but this isn't the Jesus you
might be familiar with from Sunday
school this is Jesus The Traveler the
Seeker the student of Eastern wisdom The
Story Goes that Issa AK Jesus spent his
lost years wandering through India and
Tibet soaking up knowledge like a
spiritual sponge he supposedly studied
with Buddhists Hindus and other Eastern
sages learning their ways and
teachings now here's where it gets
really interesting there are actually
some ancient texts that mention this Isa
figure one of the most famous is the
bavishya pirana an ancient Hindu text it
talks about a prophet named isami sounds
a lot like Jesus Messiah doesn't it who
came from the West
but wait there's more some folks point
to Tibetan manuscripts that allegedly
tell the tale of isa's travels and
studies these texts describe Isa
learning from Buddhist monks debating
with Hindu priests and even challenging
the cast system it's like Jesus was on
some kind of spiritual backpacking trip
collecting wisdom instead of
souvenirs another intriguing piece of
evidence comes from the Natan namavali a
collection of Hindu texts these texts
refer to a figure named Issa who
traveled and lived in India according to
the nathali Issa studied with Hindu and
Buddhist sages adopting their teachings
and
philosophies the Nathan mavali describes
Issa as a wise and enlightened figure
who sought spiritual knowledge in the
East this aligns with the idea that
Jesus could have traveled to India
during his Lost Years absorbing the rich
spiritual traditions of the
region these references in the naam of
vol add another layer of credibility to
the theory
they suggest that there were indeed
ancient accounts of a figure resembling
Jesus spending time in India learning
from the great spiritual masters of the
time adding another fascinating layer to
this story is the tradition of the
Apostle Thomas visiting India modern
Syrian Christians of Kerala who
represent a significant Christian
population in India believe that Thomas
the disciple who famously questioned
Jesus's resurrection traveled to India
in ad 52 and baptized their
forefathers this tradition is supported
by various historical and religious
accounts the belief that Thomas
established Christian communities in
Kerala suggest early and direct
interactions between Christianity and
India this connection further supports
the plausibility of Jesus or his early
followers having knowledge of Indian
spiritual
Traditions these texts along with the
bisha piran Tibetan manuscripts and the
traditions of apostle Thomas build a
compelling narrative they weave together
a story of a young Jesus traveling far
from home seeking wisdom in the East and
returning with teachings that would
later resonate deeply with both eastern
and western
philosophies before we dive into the
theories let me share a quick personal
story when I first heard about the
possibility of Jesus traveling to India
I was skeptical too but then I
remembered a time when I took a
spontaneous trip seeking something I
couldn't quite Define
that Journey opened my mind to New
Perspectives and philosophies I never
considered before it made me think if a
regular guy like me could have such a
transformative
experience why not
Jesus it's chapter 5 the Kashmir
connection all right folks we're about
to get into one of the wildest parts of
this Theory the cashmir connection it's
like the season finale cliff of the
Jesus in India Saga so picture this
Jesus doesn't survive the crucifixion
plot twist and decides to retire in
Kashmir yeah you heard that right
Kashmir that beautiful mountainous
region between India and
Pakistan at the heart of this theory is
a shrine in Sagar kashmir's largest city
it's called the rosabal or the Tomb of
Jesus local tradition says It's the
final resting place of a prophet named
yuz Asaf now some people believe yuz
Asaf was another name for Jesus the tomb
itself is pretty unassuming a simple
building with a grave inside but it's
become a major attraction for Spiritual
tourists and curiosity Seekers It's like
the D Vinci Code but with more mountain
views and fewer European art museums now
you might be wondering what's the
evidence for this well supporters of the
theory point to a few things they talk
about local legends that have been
passed down for Generations they mention
ancient texts that supposedly reference
Jesus life in cashmir some even claim
there are similarities between Kashmir
and ancient Israeli Customs one of the
most intriguing bits of evidence is a
pair of carved Footprints near the
tomb Believers say these Footprints show
marks of crucifixion wounds it's like a
spiritual version of those Hollywood
handprints but way older and way more
controversial
chapter 6 from Scrolls to
screens let's dive into how this theory
has captured imaginations in books and
on screens it's like a historical
mystery that's gone viral across
different
media first let's talk documentaries the
BBC's Jesus in India from 2008 was a
game changer they sent a crew trekking
through India and Tibet exploring
ancient monasteries and texts it was
like Indiana Jones meets religious
studies minus the boulder chases then
we've got the history channels the Lost
Years of Jesus from
2007 part of their decoding the past
Series this one dug into various
theories about Jesus's Missing Years
with the India connection taking Center
Stage Discovery Channel jumped on the
bandwagon with Jesus in Kashmir the Lost
Tomb in
2007 this one zeroed in on that
mysterious tomb in serenar we talked
about earlier think CSI ancient Kashmir
with researchers playing historical
detectives now why did these
documentaries blow up well they took
this Fringe Theory out of Dusty academic
circles and beamed it into living rooms
worldwide suddenly dinner table
conversations were less about what's for
dessert and more about whether Jesus
went on a gap year to India but the
small screen isn't the only place this
Theory's been Making
Waves let's hit the books shall we it
all kicked off with Nicholas novices the
known life of Jesus Christ back in
1894 this book was like a bomb in the
world of religious studies novich
claimed he'd found ancient Tibetan
Scrolls telling the tale of Jesus or Isa
in
India talk about a plot twist but here's
the kicker no one's ever found these
Scrolls again convenient
right fast forward to 1908 and we've got
Levi H dowling's the Aquarian Gospel of
Jesus the Christ This Book takes nich's
idea and runs with it describing Jesus
supposed travels through India Tibet and
Persia in Vivid detail it's like a
spiritual travelog minus the Instagram
posts in more recent times hoger cursed
and published Jesus lived in India in
1981 this book became the modern Bible
pun intended for the Jesus in India
Theory compiling various evidence and
arguments it's become the goto source
for anyone wanting to dive deep into
this idea and let's not forget Elizabeth
Clare Prophets The Lost Years of Jesus
from
1984 this book explores various theories
about jesus' life between ages 12 and 30
reading like a historical detective
novel piecing together Clues from across
cultures these books and documentaries
aren't just Gathering dust on shelves or
in streaming cues they've sparked
debates inspired further research
and got people looking at familiar
stories in completely new ways they've
created a whole subgenre of spiritual
historical speculation but here's the
million dooll question are these sources
legit well that's where things get
tricky mainstream Scholars often
criticize these works for lack of solid
evidence they point out inconsistencies
question the authenticity of sources and
raise eyebrows at some of the more
dramatic
claims but here's the thing whether
these books and documentaries are are
historically accurate or not they've had
a real impact they've got people
thinking about religious history in new
ways challenging assumptions and opening
Minds to new
possibilities it's a reminder of the
power of media and literature they can
shape how we see the world challenge our
beliefs and Inspire us to explore beyond
our usual boundaries so while we might
not want to take these sources as gospel
pun intended again they're definitely
worth a look if you're curious about
this Theory
who knows maybe diving into one of these
books or watching one of these
documentaries will spark your own
journey of Discovery just remember to
pack your critical thinking skills along
with your
Curiosity on chapter 7 teachings across
borders now let's get to the juicy part
comparing Jesus's teachings with
Buddhist ideas it's like we're setting
up a philosophical boxing match but
instead of throwing punches they're
throwing
wisdom first up we've got the golden
rule Jesus said do to others what you
would have them do to you Buddha's take
consider others as
yourself it's like their Cosmic twins
separated at Birth preaching the same
message of treating others right then
there's the whole deal with materialism
Jesus was all about it is easier for a
camel to go through the eye of a needle
than for someone who is Rich to enter
the kingdom of God meanwhile Buddha's
over here saying the root of suffering
is attachment both of them are basically
telling us to cool it with the shopping
spree and focus on what really matters
let's talk about inner peace Jesus drops
this gem the kingdom of God is within
you Buddha's not far off with peace
comes from within do not seek it without
it's like they both saying hey stop
looking for happiness in your Instagram
likes and start looking inside yourself
now on to forgiveness Jesus is famous
for saying turn the other cheek Buddha's
spin hatred does not cease by hatred but
only by love they're both pushing this
radical idea of breaking the cycle of
Revenge with some good oldfashioned
forgiveness but wait there's more some
Scholars argue that these similarities
aren't just coincidences they suggest
that Jesus might have directly
encountered these Buddhist teachings
during his Lost Years integrating them
into his own philosophy
consider the concept of compassion both
Jesus and Buddha emphasize the
importance of compassion towards others
Jesus's parable of the Good Samaritan
teaches us to help others regardless of
their background while Buddha's
teachings encourage boundless compassion
for all
beings the practice of mindfulness and
meditation is another intriguing
parallel while not explicitly mentioned
in the New Testament the idea of quiet
reflection and prayer is Central to
Jesus teachings simp similarly
meditation is a core practice in
Buddhism promoting inner peace and
Enlightenment moreover the notion of
selflessness and service to others is
deeply embedded in both
Traditions Jesus washed the feet of his
disciples teaching humility and service
Buddha's teachings also emphasize the
importance of serving others and living
a life free from selfish
desires these striking similarities
suggest a potential exchange of
ideas could Jesus have been inspired by
Buddhist teachings during his
travels the parallels in their messages
certainly give weight to this
fascinating
Theory chapter 8 the Skeptics corner all
right let's pump the brakes for a second
and look at the other side of the coin
it's time to put on our skeptic hats and
see what the scholars have to say about
this whole Jesus in India Theory first
off mainstream historians and biblical
Scholars aren't exactly jumping on this
bandwagon they're more likely to give it
the side eye than a thumbs up why well
they point out that there's a glaring
lack of solid historical evidence it's
like trying to prove you had a pet
dinosaur as a kid without any photos
bones or really big
Footprints many experts argue that if
Jesus had made such an epic journey to
India surely someone would have written
about it at the
time we're talking about a pretty big
deal here not exactly something you'd
forget to
mention yet the Gospels and other early
Christian writings are silent on this
supposed Asian
Adventure then there's the issue of
timing some Scholars say the timeline
doesn't add up they argue that Jesus
likely spent his youth in Nazareth
learning the Family Trade of carpentry
it's not like he could hop on a plane
for a quick trip to India we're talking
about a long dangerous Journey that
would have taken
years let's not forget about language if
Jesus had studied in India wouldn't he
have picked up some Sanskrit or poly yet
the gospels show him speaking Aramaic
and possibly some Greek or Hebrew no
sign of him dropping any Buddhist lingo
now about those similarities between
Christian and Buddhist teachings many
scholars say these can be explained
without Jesus taking a trip to India
they point out that some of these ideas
were already floating around the
Mediterranean world at the time it's
like how you and your friend on the
other side of the country might both be
into the same Tick Tock Trend ideas can
spread without Direct
contact all right folks we've been on
quite the journey today haven't we we've
explored ancient texts peaked into
Tibetan monasteries and even checked out
a tomb in Kashmir all to chase down this
wild idea that Jesus might have been
channeling his inner Buddha during those
mysterious Lost Years so what do we make
of all this well here's the
deal we can't say for sure if Jesus has
ever set foot in India or studied
Buddhism the evidence isn't there to
make that claim but you know what that's
okay because sometimes the value is in
the questions we ask not the answers we
find this whole Theory whether you buy
it or not gets us
thinking it makes us look at familiar
stories from new angles it reminds us
that history is complex full of
mysteries and possibilities we might
never fully un
rvel and isn't that kind of awesome it
also shows us how ideas can cross
borders and cultures in surprising ways
whether it's through ancient trade routs
or modern-day YouTube videos human
beings have always been sharing and
adapting each other's thoughts and
beliefs it's like we're all part of this
giant centuries long group chat of
ideas now I'm not here to tell you what
to believe that's your
call but I do hope this little
Expedition into the land of Whata if
has got your mental gears turning maybe
it's made you curious to learn more
about different religious Traditions or
perhaps it's inspired you to dig deeper
into history's Unsolved Mysteries so
here's my challenge to you keep
exploring keep questioning whether it's
this Theory or any other aspect of
history or religion that piques your
interest don't be afraid to dive in read
books watch documentaries talk to people
with different perspectives be curious
but also be critical look for evidence
not exciting stories and hey why not
start right now drop a comment below
with your thoughts on this Theory do you
think there might be something to it or
is it an interesting what if scenario
maybe you've got your own theory about
what Jesus was up to during those Lost
Years share it if you enjoyed this
mind-bending journey don't forget to hit
that like button it helps more people
find our videos and join in on these
fascinating discussions
and if you want to keep exploring the
wild world of religious history and
philosophy with us smash that subscribe
button and ring the notification
Bell remember folks history isn't
memorizing dates and names it's about
exploring the big questions challenging
our assumptions and Imagining the
possibilities so keep asking those
questions keep seeking that knowledge
and who knows maybe you'll be the one to
uncover the next big his IAL
mystery this is Matt from Buddha's
wisdom signing off until next time keep
your mind open and your curiosity fierce