[Music]
hey there wisdom Hunters Matt here today
we're uncovering the hidden influences
that molded the Buddha's teachings
before he became the enlightened one
sidartha Gama was a Seeker driven by
questions that still keep us up at night
in his quest for truth sidartha
encountered five remarkable sages from
ancient India a time when spiritual
exploration and philosophical debate
flourished each left an indelible mark
on his thinking ultimately leading to
the birth of Buddhism as we know it
we'll explore these pivotal encounters
revealing how ancient Indian wisdom
converged in sidarthur's mind you'll see
how he learned questioned and ultimately
transcended his teacher ideas it's like
a spiritual detective story and trust me
the plot twists are
mind-bending our journey begins with a
master of meditation Who challenged
everything sidartha thought he
knew let's explore how this encounter
shaped the path to
Enlightenment Sara's first stop on his
spiritual journey led him to Alara Kama
a renowned meditation Master picture a
Serene Forest Clearing where arara sat
surrounded by devoted students his
reputation for achieving extraordinary
States Of Consciousness Drew Seekers
from far and wide think of his him as
the Tony Robins of ancient India minus
the fir walking Alara taught sidartha
the art of deep concentration known as
Janna in p a state of deep mental
absorption where the Mind becomes still
and
focused this wasn't your average close
your eyes and think happy thoughts
meditation alara's technique allowed
practitioners to reach the realm of
nothingness a state of consciousness so
profound it made your typical Daydream
look like a kid's coloring book alara's
teaching gave sidartha the ability to
enter these profound meditative states
with intense focus and Clarity where the
mind could become completely still
absorbed in deep
concentration however alara's approach
focused primarily on mental discipline
and achieving these Altered States Of
Consciousness rather than addressing the
deeper existential questions sidartha
was wrestling with imagine sidartha
cross-legged eyes closed his mind
becoming still as a mirror-like lake
under alara's guidance he learned to
peel away layers of thought until
reaching a state of pure awareness it
was groundbreaking stuff for the young
Seeker like discovering you can change
the channel on reality it was like
sidartha took the red pill of meditation
seeing How Deep The Rabbit Hole of
Consciousness goes when sidartha
mastered the technique Alara reportedly
said to him your mind gatama is like a
polished gem clear unblemished and
capable of reflecting the deepest truths
you have achieved what many seek but few
attain talk about a five-star
review but here's where things get
interesting despite this High Praise
something nagged at sidartha this state
of nothingness impressive as it was
didn't answer his fundamental questions
about suffering and
Liberation it was like mastering a skill
without understanding the bigger
picture alara's teachings showed him how
to control the mind but not how to free
it completely from
suffering but sidartha wasn't satisfied
even after mastering alara's teachings
the key to Liberation still eluded him
in a bold move that would change the
course of his journey sidartha thanked
arara for the lessons and decided to
walk away in search of deeper
answers it was a crucial moment sidartha
realized that while deep concentration
was valuable it alone wasn't the key to
ultimate
truth sometimes you've got to know when
to fold them and when to walk away even
in the spiritual
Casino alara's influence on Buddhism
massive the Janna sidartha learned
became an integral part of Buddhist
practice but the Buddha would later
teach them as tools not ends in
themselves a stepping stone to deeper
insights it's like learning to make the
perfect pizza dough only to realize
you're actually after the secret sauce
of
Enlightenment after parting ways with
Alara Kalama sidartha sought out udaka
raputa a teacher known for his Mastery
of even more advanced meditative States
uda's ashram buzzed with an air of
mystery and profound spiritual
exploration it was like the Hogwarts of
meditation minus the flying broomsticks
while Alara had taught sidartha how to
focus and control the mind uda's
teachings went even further exploring
more subtle and refined States Of
Consciousness UDA introduced sidartha to
a state beyond the realm of nothingness
the realm of neither perception nor
non-perception if that sounds
mind-bending it's because it is this
state pushed the very limits of human
consciousness teetering on the edge of
experience itself it's like trying to
taste the color n or smell silence wrap
your mind around
that under uda's guidance sidartha
learned to refine his awareness to an
incredibly subtle degree it was like
tuning a radio to pick up the faintest
signal from the cosmos or trying to hear
a pin drop in a
library on the
moon udaka impressed by sidartha Swift
progress reportedly told him your mind
young Seeker is like the vast Sky
boundless and clear you've reached a
pinnacle few have glimpsed stay and
teach alongside IDE me for you have
matched my understanding talk about a
job offer you don't get every day but
sidartha while grateful felt a familiar
restlessness despite these advancements
sidartha realized that even this Ultra
refined State of Consciousness as
extraordinary as it was didn't address
the fundamental problems of existence
birth aging death and
suffering while Alara had shown him how
to enter deep states of concentration
and udaka had revealed even more
profound meditative Realms neither path
provided the Ultimate answers to Life's
biggest questions it became clear that
even these extraordinary states were not
the end goal but part of the journey in
a pivotal moment sedara realized that
even this rarified state was still
within the realm of conditioned
existence it wasn't the ultimate
Liberation he sought with respect and
gratitude he Bid Farewell to aaka
determined to find a path Beyond even
this subtle
realm our boy sidartha was playing
spiritual Hopscotch and he wasn't about
to stop until he reached the cosmic
Finish Line oda's teachings weren't in
vain though they showed sidartha the
furthest reaches of concentrated
meditation and helped him understand the
limits of perception itself these
insights would later inform the Buddha's
teachings on the nature of Consciousness
and the path to True
Liberation it's like learning to build a
rocket ship not because you want to go
to the Moon but because you're aiming
for the
Stars while sidartha never directly
studied under mahavira their paths and
ideas intersected in fascinating ways
mahavira the founder of jism was
revolutionizing spiritual practice in
Ancient India at the same time sidartha
was on his quest think of him as the
Steve Jobs of spirituality if Steve Jobs
was into extreme minimalism and never
wearing clothes
mahavira's path was one of extreme
asceticism imagine a man who renounced
not just wealth and comfort but even
clothing mahavira believed that the path
to Liberation lay in strict nonviolence
and the complete eradication of karma
through severe austerities it's like
trying to win a cosmic game of Limbo by
seeing how low you can go sidartha
during his wandering years encountered
Jane monks and their practices although
mahavira and sidartha never met directly
Jane aestheticism had a strong influence
on the spiritual environment at the time
sidartha observed how Jen practitioners
pushed their bodies to the absolute
limit fasting for weeks meditating in
the scorching Sun even plucking out
their hair by The Roots the Jen approach
emphasized that Liberation lay an
extreme discipline over the body for a
while sidartha adopted similar practices
testing whether physical denial could
lead to ultimate truth a g monk once
told said artha the body is a vessel of
suffering only by breaking its hold can
we free the soul each moment of pain is
a step towards
Liberation it's like trying to escape a
prison by digging a tunnel with a spoon
painful slow and maybe not the best
approach for a Time sidartha embraced
this radical path pushing his body to
the brink of death through fasting and
extreme meditation but unlike mahavira
sidartha ultimately rejected this path
as too
extreme he realized that while these
practices could demonstrate control over
the body they did not provide freedom
from the cycle of suffering it turns out
starving yourself isn't the fast track
to Enlightenment who
knew yet mahavira's influence on
Buddhism is
undeniable the concept of ahimsa which
means nonviolence and respect for all
living things became a corner Stone of
Buddhist ethics the idea that our
actions have consequences Karma the
universal law of cause and effect became
Central to both jism and Buddhism it's
like mahavira and sidartha were
spiritual DJs mixing similar tracks but
producing very different Tunes Sara's
encounter with giant ideas led him to a
crucial realization the middle way
between Indulgence and extreme
asceticism he saw that torturing the
body didn't Liberate the mind mind this
Insight was key in shaping the Buddhist
path of moderation and
mindfulness sometimes the secret to life
isn't going to extremes it's finding
that sweet spot in the middle like the
perfect bite of a
[Music]
sandwich let's turn our attention to
capila the OG of dualism this guy never
met sidartha directly but his ideas were
like a philosophical earworm in Ancient
India impossible to ignore capila the
found of the Samia School of philosophy
proposed a radical idea the universe
consists of two fundamental
realities prreti or the physical world
nature or matter and
perusia which refers to Pure
Consciousness or
Spirit imagine a world split into the
dancer and the dance forever intertwined
yet fundamentally separate it's like
trying to separate the Netflix from the
chill
technically possible but where's the fun
in
that this dualistic view challenged
prevailing Notions of a single unified
reality it suggested that our suffering
stems from confusing these two
principles mistaking the changes of the
material world prti for the nature of
our true unchanging Consciousness
perusia it's like getting upset when
your favorite character dies in a TV
show you're not the character you're the
Watcher sidartha never studied directly
under capila but the Samia school's
ideas were influential in the
philosophical debates of his time a
Wandering philosopher echoing kila's
teachings once told
sidartha see the world as a grand play
Young Seeker you are the Silent Witness
not the actor caught in the drama
Liberation comes from recognizing this
eternal
separation imagine being told you're not
the star of your own life story but the
audience talk about an existential plot
twist sidartha grappled with these ideas
they offered a compelling explanation
for The Human Condition and a potential
path to Freedom the concept of detached
observation would later influence
Buddhist mindfulness practices like
observing your thoughts and emotions
without identifying with them it's like
capila handed sidartha the spiritual
equivalent of 3D glasses suddenly
everything looked
different however since dartha
ultimately diverged from kila's strict
dualism he saw that while distinguishing
between awareness and its objects was
useful true Liberation comes from
understanding their interdependence not
their absolute
separation it's like realizing that
while the ocean is different from the
waves you can't have one without the
other kila's influence can be seen in
buddhism's analytical approach to
understanding reality the Buddhist
concept of namarupa meaning
name and form Echoes samia's dualism but
with a crucial
difference Buddhism sees name mental
aspects and form physical aspects as
interconnected parts of experience not
separate
realities sidartha took capa's idea and
gave it a remix turning philosophical
heavy metal into spiritual Jazz this
encounter with samya philosophy
sharpened Sara's analytical skills and
deepened his understanding of the
mindbody
relationship it set the stage for his
own nuanced view of reality which would
become a Cornerstone of Buddhist
philosophy sometimes you need to learn
the rules before you can break them and
break them sidartha
[Music]
did now let's talk about yaj navalia the
OG spiritual Rebel this guy predated
sidartha by several centuries but his
ideas were like a philosophical Time
Bomb just waiting to explode in
sidarthur's
mind yaj navalia was one of the most
prominent figures in the aphotic
tradition which focused on seeking the
Ultimate Reality Brahman and
understanding the nature of the self
Atman yajia boldly challenged the rigid
Orthodoxy of his time proposing that
true understanding comes not from
rituals or scriptures but from direct
insight into the nature of self and
reality imagine a man standing before a
gathering of Scholars
boldly declaring that their cherished
beliefs might be missing the Mark it's
like walking into a Star Wars convention
and suggesting that maybe just maybe
Star Trek is
better
scandalous in one famous debate yaj
navalia reportedly said the self is not
this not that it cannot be grasped by
thought yet it is that by which thought
is known it is the Unseen Seer the
unheard hearer the unknown
try putting that on a bumper
sticker this idea of an ineffable
experiential truth Beyond conceptual
understanding deeply resonated with the
Indian spiritual tradition it set the
stage for seda's own emphasis on Direct
experience over Blind Faith or
intellectual
speculation it's like yaj navalia was
saying don't just read the menu taste
the food although yavalia lived
centuries before sidhartha the
upanishadic tradition he shape laid the
groundwork for some of sidharth's key
insights the upanishads with their focus
on the nature of Consciousness and the
Ultimate Reality were philosophical
challenges that sidartha would wrestle
with on his path to
Enlightenment the concept of Atman the
Eternal self and its relation to Brahman
the Ultimate Reality was a puzzle
sidartha engaged with
deeply however sartha eventually
rejected the notion of an eternal
unchanging self Atman in favor of his
revolutionary teaching of anata which
means
non-self the idea that there is no
permanent unchanging Essence in living
beings while the upanishad sought to
identify a Transcendent permanent self
sidartha realized that true Liberation
came from seeing the impermanent
everchanging nature of all things
including the self it's like yaj navalia
handed sidartha a Rubik's cube of the
Soul Tri to solve but oh so satisfying
when you
do while sidartha diverged from the
upano view of the self yaj Nalia's
method of rigorous inquiry and emphasis
on Direct realization became Central to
the Buddhist approach the Buddha's
famous injunction to be a lamp unto
yourself Echoes yaj Nalia's call for
personal investigation of truth it's
like yaj navalia was the spiritual
equivalent of your cool Uncle who tells
you to question everything even him
yajin Nalia's Legacy in Buddhism can be
seen in the emphasis on meditation and
introspection as means of understanding
reality his questioning Spirit lives on
in the Buddha's encouragement to test
and verify teachings through one's own
experience in a way yajnavalkya gave
sartha permission to think outside the
box and boy did he run with
it all right folks we've reached the
main event the grand finale the
spiritual knockout punch Buddha's
breakthrough picture sidartha now in his
early 30s sitting beneath the bod tree
he's absorbed the wisdom of India's
greatest sages pushed his body to its
limits and explored the furthest reaches
of Consciousness yet the ultimate truth
still eludes him it's like he's played
every level of the spiritual video game
but the final boss just won't go
down in this moment sidartha makes a
radical decision in instead of looking
outward to teachers or inward to extreme
states of mind he simply observes
reality as it is he watches his breath
notices Sensations in his body and sees
thoughts arise and pass away it's like
he discovered that the ultimate cheat
code was simply to be here now as the
night deepens sidharth's awareness
sharpens he begins to see the
interconnected nature of all
things the boundaries between self and
other mind body start to
dissolve in this Clarity he utters words
that would echo through
history Wonder of Wonders all beings are
already enlightened yet they don't
realize it they chase after fleeting
pleasures and run from imagined fears
failing to see the radiant awareness
that's always
present with this Insight sidartha
becomes the Buddha the awakened one he
realizes that the truth he sought isn't
found in escaping the world or in losing
oneself in Altered States it's in fully
embracing and understanding the nature
of reality itself it's like he spent
years searching for his glasses only to
realize they were on his head the whole
time the Buddha's breakthrough
synthesizes and transcends the teachings
of his
predecessors from arara and udaka he
keeps the practice of meditation but
reframes it as a tool for insight not an
end in
itself for mahavira he retains the
emphasis on ethics but rejects extreme
asceticism capa's analytical approach
finds new expression in the Buddha's
detailed examination of experience and
yavalia emphasis on Direct realization
becomes Central to the Buddhist path but
the Buddha goes beyond all of these his
middleway avoids the extremes of
self-indulgence and self-denial the
middleway became the One path to rule
them all guiding Seekers through the
spiritual landscape of ancient India his
teaching of non-self challenges both the
materialist and eternalist views of his
time and His Four Noble Truths offer a
pragmatic approach to addressing
suffering that's neither fatalistic nor
overly
optimistic it's like he took all the
ingredients his teachers gave him and
cooked up a completely new dish
Enlightenment
surprise in this breakthrough the
wandering Seeker sidartha fulfills his
quest becoming the
Buddha and in doing so he opens a path
that countless others would follow
seeking their own breakthrough to
Lasting Peace and Freedom talk about a
plot twist the student becomes the
teacher and the rest as they say is
history all right truth Seekers we've
reached the end of our Whirlwind tour
through the Buddha spiritual
education let's bring it all back home
shall we these ancient sages Alara udaka
mahavira capila and yavalia might seem
like characters from a spiritual soap
opera set in a galaxy far far away but
their quest for understanding The Human
Condition that's as relevant today as a
smartphone at a dinner table think about
it don't we still grapple with the same
fundamental questions we seek peace in a
chaotic World yearn for meaning in our
lives and strive to understand our place
in the
universe the Buddha's Journey influenced
by these great thinkers offers us a road
map for our own
Explorations it's like they left us a
spiritual GPS mind is the annoying
recalculating voice but here's the
kicker the Buddha didn't just rehash old
ideas he took the best of what he
learned tested it against his own
experience and emerged with something
revolutionary his message the power to
find truth lies within each of us it's
like he was saying hey you've got the
answers inside you no need to download a
spiritual app so what does this mean for
you right here right now let's break it
down down first it's an invitation to
explore just as the Buddha learned from
various teachers we too can draw wisdom
from diverse sources whether it's
meditation philosophy science or art
remain open to insights wherever they
appear it's like being at a cosmic
Buffet try a little of everything but
maybe skip the month-old potato salad of
outdated
dogmas second it's a call to question
the Buddha didn't accept teachings BL L
and neither should we he learned to test
the limits of each teacher's wisdom and
move Beyond them when
necessary test ideas against your own
experience does it ring true does it
help reduce
suffering that's the litmus test it's
like being a spiritual mythbuster don't
just believe it test it finally it's an
encouragement to forge your own path the
Buddha's breakthrough came when he
stopped following others and trusted his
own Insight your breakthrough might come
in a similar way remember the Buddha
didn't find Enlightenment by scrolling
through Instagram or binge watching
Netflix though who knows maybe that's
your path remember the Buddha once said
do not go upon what has been acquired by
repeated hearing nor upon tradition nor
upon rumor nor upon what is in a
scripture nor upon surmise nor upon an
axiom nor upon specious reasoning nor
upon a bias towards a notion that has
been pondered over nor upon another
seeming ability nor upon the
consideration the monk is our
teacher when you yourselves know these
things are good these things are not
blamable these things are praised by the
wise undertaken and observed these
things lead to benefit and happiness
enter on and abide in
them in other words don't just take my
word for it or anyone else's for that
matter the Buddha was basically saying
don't believe it just because I'm
rocking this cool robe and Serene smile
test it out
yourself so as we close this chapter I
challenge you what wisdom will you seek
what questions will you ask and what
path will you
forge the Journey of discovery that
began with those ancient sages continues
with you the Breakthrough they saw is
still possible today are you ready to
find it Enlightenment isn't just for
robed guys sitting under trees it's for
all of us whether we're stuck in traffic
binging on pizza or trying to figure out
why our cat keeps knocking things off
the
table The Game of Life is a foot and
you're the main player so go ahead take
what you've learned and level up your
existence and hey if you found this
journey through the Buddha's spiritual
education enlightening pun totally
intended don't forget to like subscribe
and hit that notification Bell who knows
your next step step on the path to
Enlightenment might just be a click
away until next time this is Matt
signing off stay curious stay
questioning and above all stay awesome
namaste