the Buddha was born a Hindu prince
raised in Hindu traditions
and yet created a philosophy that challenged
fundamental Hindu beliefs
some Hindus even consider Buddha an Avatar of Vishnu
two ancient spiritual paths
one embracing the eternal self
the other rejecting it entirely
what if the path to enlightenment
requires abandoning our most cherished belief
how did these traditions diverge
and why do millions still debate
which path leads to true liberation
welcome to Buddha's wisdom
I'm Peter and today
we're exploring the fascinating
relationship between Hinduism
and Buddhism
two spiritual traditions that shaped the east
and now captivate the west
while they share geographical origins
and certain practices their core philosophies
reveal dramatically different visions of reality
suffering and liberation
my own journey with these traditions began 20 years ago
when I stumbled into a Hindu temple in southern India
mesmerized by the rituals and devotion
years later a 10 day
silent Buddhist meditation retreat
showed me a completely different approach to spiritual
practice the contrast between these experiences
sparked questions I'm still exploring today
I've spent years studying these traditions
and what fascinates me most
isn't just their philosophical differences
but how they've shaped the lives of billions
across history
whether you're meditating in a yoga class
or practicing mindfulness for stress reduction
you're touching practices from these ancient
wisdom traditions
think of them as spiritual siblings
raised in the same household
but taking very different paths in life
one embraces the divine in countless forms
while the other as we discussed in a previous video
questions whether gods matter at all
one celebrates the eternal soul
while the other considers this our greatest delusion
the Dhammapada one of Buddhism's most revered texts
states
meanwhile the Hindu Bhagavad Gita teaches
these contrasting views
reflect the fascinating tension
between these traditions
that continue to guide billions of people worldwide
together we'll uncover the surprising connections
and profound differences between these traditions
whether you're new to eastern philosophy
or have practiced meditation for years
this exploration
will deepen your understanding of both paths
and perhaps your own spiritual journey
let's start at the beginning
not just the beginning of Buddhism
but the vibrant world that shaped it
picture northern India 2,500 years ago
bustling trade routes connecting diverse kingdoms
forests filled with spiritual seekers
and marketplaces echoing with philosophical debates
Hinduism though it wasn't called that yet
had already existed for thousands of years
the ancient Vedic traditions featured elaborate rituals
a complex pantheon of gods and a rigid social structure
this was the world Siddhartha Gautama was born into
you might remember how the sheltered
prince of the Shakya clan
left his palace in what is now Nepal abandoning
luxury to seek deeper truths
he was raised as a Hindu educated in Hindu scriptures
and expected to follow Hindu customs
the religious texts he studied
the Vedas and Upanishads
shaped his understanding of the world
the Upanishads were particularly significant
these philosophical texts
questioned the ritualistic aspects of Vedic religion
and explored profound concepts
like Brahman the ultimate reality
and Atman the eternal self
one famous passage from the Chandogya Upanishad
declares Tat Tvam asi
you are that meaning your true self
is one with the ultimate reality
despite his privileged upbringing
or perhaps because of it
Siddhartha began questioning these traditions
after witnessing sickness
old age and death beyond his palace walls
he abandoned his royal life
to seek answers to suffering
what's fascinating
is that Buddha didn't set out to create a new religion
he was simply a Hindu seeker
following established practices of his time
he studied with prominent Hindu teachers
mastered meditation techniques
and practiced extreme asceticism
starving himself nearly to death
in pursuit of enlightenment
when these approaches failed him
he developed a middle way
between indulgence and asceticism
sitting beneath the Bodhi Tree
he attained enlightenment
and began sharing his insights
Buddha's teachings
weren't a complete rejection of Hinduism
but rather a reform movement within it
he accepted many Hindu concepts like karma
rebirth and the goal of liberation from suffering
but he radically reinterpreted others
he rejected the authority of the Vedas
questioned the caste system
and denied the existence of an
eternal soul for many Hindus
these were revolutionary even heretical ideas
this rejection of caste hierarchy
planted seeds for social reform
that would flower centuries later
while orthodox Hinduism maintained the Varna system
movements within Hinduism eventually challenged rigid
caste divisions too
the medieval Bakti movement saw Hindu saints
like Mirabai and Kabir
declare that devotion transcended birth status
today both traditions
continue wrestling with Equality and inclusion
though from different starting points
Buddhism's foundational challenge to social hierarchy
versus Hinduism's gradual reform from within
as the Buddhist scholar Richard Gombrich puts it
the Buddha was a radical critic of brahmanical religion
but worked with its concepts
doing what we might call judo with ideas
rather than wrestling with them
this context helps explain why Buddhism
eventually faded in India
while flourishing elsewhere
imagine walking through ancient Nalanda University
in the 5th century where Hindu and Buddhist
scholars debated in packed halls
one tradition survived in its homeland
adapting and evolving
while the other spread its influence across Asia
transforming cultures from Sri Lanka to Japan
as we'll discover throughout this video
Hinduism proved remarkably adaptable
even incorporating aspects of Buddhist thought
while reasserting traditional beliefs
the relationship between these traditions
remains complex to this day
with some Hindus claiming Buddha as their own
while maintaining fundamentally
different views about the nature of reality
and the path to spiritual freedom
now that we understand their shared beginnings
let's explore the most profound
philosophical divide between them
the question of whether we have an eternal soul
at the heart of Hindu philosophy
lies a profound concept Atman
the eternal unchanging self or soul
this isn't just another teaching
for Hindus
it represents the fundamental truth of existence
The Brihadaranyaka Upanishad
one of Hinduism's oldest texts
declares
this short but powerful
statement encapsulates a central Hindu belief
that our true self Atman
is identical with the ultimate cosmic reality Brahman
for Hindus recognizing this truth
that your innermost essence is divine and eternal
leads to spiritual liberation
your body may die but your soul continues its journey
through many lifetimes
until it realizes its divine nature
and merges with the cosmic whole
now the Buddha took this foundational concept
and did something radical
he didn't just modify it he completely rejected it
the concept of emptiness lies at Buddhism's core
the radical idea that reality lacks inherent
independent existence
this principle extends to our sense of self
the Buddha taught Anatta no self
declaring that what we experience as a permanent "I"
is actually an illusion
the Buddha said in the Samyutta Nikaya form feeling
perception
mental formations and consciousness are not self
if they were self they would not lead to affliction
and it would be possible to control them
saying let these be thus
let these not be thus
but since they are not self
they lead to affliction
and it isn't possible to control them
so what are we according to Buddhism
if not an eternal soul
we're a temporary collection of five aggregates
form sensation perception
mental formations and consciousness
all constantly changing
arising and dissolving like waves on water
this creates Buddhism's famous rebirth paradox
how can rebirth occur without something being reborn
the Buddha offered a practical answer
what continues is not a soul but causal connections
imagine lighting one candle from another
the flame continues
but no unchanging essence transfers between them
it simply cause and effect
flowing from moment to moment
life to life one moment conditions the next
one life influences the next
without requiring a permanent self to bridge them
like a river that maintains continuity
while constantly changing
our consciousness streams Onward
shaped by our actions
but never fixed as a permanent entity
this difference isn't just academic
it completely transforms how each tradition approaches
spiritual practice
if you follow Hindu teachings
your goal is to realize your true nature
to understand that
beneath your changing thoughts and feelings
exists an eternal divine essence
meditation and yoga serve to peel away the layers
obscuring the self knowledge
but if you practice Buddhism
you meditate
to see through the illusion of a permanent self
to recognize that what you call I is actually a process
not a thing there's no unchanging core to discover
only the liberating recognition
that the self you've been defending
promoting and worrying about
doesn't actually exist in the way you thought
the implications are enormous
consider how we respond to insults
if someone criticizes you
a Hindu perspective might suggest
they're not criticizing my true self
only my temporary physical or mental attribute
meanwhile a Buddhist view might be
who exactly is being insulted here
there's no permanent me to be offended
just temporary thoughts and feelings
arising in response to words
both approaches can reduce suffering
but through completely different understandings
of reality
consider how differently followers might approach grief
when a loved one dies a Hindu might find comfort
knowing their eternal soul continues its journey
a Buddhist might focus on accepting impermanence
as the nature of all things
same human experience
completely different frameworks for processing it
this philosophical divide created practical differences
too Hinduism developed elaborate rituals
to purify and protect the soul in its journey
Buddhism seeing no soul to protect
focused instead
on practices to see through the illusion of permanence
interestingly both traditions
eventually developed similar meditation techniques
despite their different philosophies
a Hindu might meditate to discover the Atman within
while a Buddhist might use almost identical practices
to confirm no Atman exists at all
this tension between self and no self
appears in how each tradition views enlightenment
for Hindus
moksha means the liberation of the individual soul
and its reunion with Brahman
for Buddhists Nirvana
involves
extinguishing the very illusion of a separate self
is one view right and one wrong
that's not for me to say
but understanding this fundamental difference
helps explain why
despite their common origins and similar practices
these traditions
developed such distinct approaches to spiritual life
and while this philosophical divide might seem abstract
it leads directly to different understandings of gods
worship and the role of devotion in spiritual life
which brings us to our next chapter
enter a Hindu temple
and you might encounter hundreds of deities
colorful multi armed figures
representing different aspects of the divine
Krishna playing his flute
Ganesha with his elephant head
Kali with her necklace of skulls
this rich pantheon reflects a core Hindu belief
that the ultimate reality
Brahman manifests in countless forms
as the Rig Veda Hinduism's oldest text states
"Ekam Sat Vipra Bahudha Vadanti"
truth is one the wise call it by many names
for Hindus these deities aren't separate gods
but various expressions of a single divine reality
like how white light splits into many colors
through a prism
now walk into a traditional Buddhist temple
and you'll find a very different scene
in early Buddhism you wouldn't see gods at all
just images of the Buddha
and symbols like the Dharma wheel
why
because the Buddha considered questions about deities
largely irrelevant to ending suffering
when asked about the existence of gods
the Buddha often remained silent
or redirected the conversation
one famous text the Tevijja Sutta
shows the Buddha responding to questions
about reaching union with Brahma
a creator god by saying
none of the brahmins has seen Brahma face to face
so their teaching is baseless
the Buddha didn't explicitly deny God's existed he
acknowledged various devas
or divine beings but considered them temporary
residents of higher realms
still caught in the cycle of rebirth
still subject to suffering
still lacking true wisdom
unlike the omnipotent creator god of other traditions
Buddhist devas are more like longer lived
more powerful versions of humans
this difference affects how followers approach
spiritual practice
Hinduism embraces bhakti devotional worship
as a primary path to liberation
by loving and surrendering to a chosen deity ishta-devata
devotees can transcend ego
and realize their unity with the divine
Buddhism meanwhile
emphasizes personal effort and insight
the Buddha said in his final teaching
be a lamp unto yourselves
be your own refuge hold fast to the truth as a lamp
hold fast as a refuge to the truth
this difference extends to ritual practice itself
Hinduism preserved elaborate ceremonies
requiring precise execution
fire offerings mantra recitation
and life cycle sacraments performed by trained priests
early Buddhism by contrast
streamlined ritual elements
focusing on ethical conduct and meditation
rather than complex ceremonies
the Buddha often critiqued empty ritualism
without understanding
when a brahmin described elaborate fire rituals
the Buddha responded
that the true sacred fire was the disciplined mind
and true offerings were virtuous actions
this practical approach made Buddhism accessible beyond
priestly circles though later
Buddhist traditions
would develop their own ritual complexities
this doesn't mean Buddhists never pray
or engage in devotional practices
as Buddhism spread across Asia
it incorporated local deities
and developed devotional elements
in pure land Buddhism for
instance devotees call upon Amitabha Buddha
for rebirth in his paradise
and in Tibetan Buddhism
deities serve as meditation focal points
embodiments of qualities practitioners seek to develop
even the Buddha's status evolved
though he never claimed to be divine
and explicitly identified as a human teacher
many Buddhists came to Revere him as something beyond
ordinary humanity this parallels
how certain Hindu traditions view great sages
and teachers in Mahayana Buddhism
the concept of Buddhahood
expanded to include multiple Buddhas
across time and space
remember our video who is Maitreya
this tradition of future Buddhas
creates an interesting parallel with Hindu avatars
divine beings who manifest in different forms
throughout cosmic cycles
some Hindu traditions even incorporated the Buddha
himself as the ninth Avatar of Vishnu
as we discussed in our video
this creative theological move
effectively claimed Buddhism as a subset of Hinduism
though with the ironic twist
that this Avatar supposedly taught false doctrines
to test the faithful or mislead demons
during medieval India
an extraordinary convergence occurred
both traditions developed tantric practices
with striking similarities
despite their different philosophical foundations
both traditions used visualization of deities
as a spiritual technique
though with different ultimate goals
so while Hinduism might be described as polytheistic
monotheistic or even henotheistic
depending on the tradition
and Buddhism might range from non theistic
to practically polytheistic
these labels oversimplify
complex approaches to divinity
what matters most isn't just whether gods exist
but how concepts of the divine
shape our understanding of
suffering and liberation
which brings us to the heart of both traditions
and our next chapter
life hurts this simple truth
forms the foundation of both Hindu
and Buddhist thought we all experience physical pain
heartbreak loss and eventually death
but why must we suffer
and can we ever truly overcome it
both traditions address these questions
but with different diagnoses and prescriptions
let's start with their shared concepts
before exploring their distinct approaches
both Hinduism and Buddhism
recognize the cycle of rebirth Samsara
where beings move through repeated lives
according to their karma as we explained in our video
Samsara explained
this isn't a single life followed by heaven or hell
but an ongoing process spanning countless existences
the Hindu text Bhagavad Gita describes it
just as a person casts off worn out garments
and puts on others that are new
even so does the embodied soul
cast off worn out bodies
and take on others that are new
similarly both traditions
view karma as the moral law of cause and effect
actions create consequences
that shape future experiences
either in this life or beyond
Karma isn't punishment or reward from a deity
but an impersonal cosmic principle like gravity
it simply works
but despite these similarities
the traditions diverge in how they understand
suffering's root causes and ultimate solutions
for Hinduism suffering stems from ignorance
avidya of our true nature as eternal atman
we identify with our temporary bodies and minds
rather than recognizing our divine essence this
misidentification causes attachment
which leads to suffering
when impermanent things inevitably change
the Hindu solution is moksha
liberation
achieved by realizing your identity with Brahman
this can happen through multiple paths
Jnana yoga knowledge
Bhakti yoga devotion
Karma yoga selfless action
or Raja Yoga meditation
the Upanishads declare
the knower of Brahman becomes Brahman
Buddhism as covered in our video
about the four noble truths
frame suffering through the four noble truths
First life contains suffering dukkha
second suffering stems from craving and attachment
third suffering can end by eliminating its causes
fourth the eightfold path leads to suffering cessation
the Buddha taught in the Dhammacakkappavattana Sutta
this is the noble truth of suffering
birth is suffering aging is suffering
illness is suffering death is suffering
union with what is displeasing is suffering
separation from what is pleasing is suffering
not to get what one wants is suffering
notice the key difference
while Hinduism sees suffering as
resulting from not knowing our true self
Buddhism considers the very belief in a permanent self
as the problem we suffer
because we cling to a self
that doesn't exist in the way we think
these divergent perspectives create distinct
meditative approaches
Hindu yogis often direct attention inward
to discover the silent witness behind thoughts
the unchanging I am presence
Buddhist practitioners train to observe all experiences
as flowing processes noting how sensations
emotions and thoughts continuously emerge
change and dissolve without a permanent center
even their ultimate goals differ subtly
Hindu moksha typically means liberation from rebirth
with the soul reuniting with Brahman
Buddhist Nirvana also ends rebirth
but without a soul merging with anything
it's simply the extinction of the causes of suffering
the Buddha described Nirvana by what it's not
there is monks an unborn unbecome
unmade unfabricated
if there were not that unborn unbecome unmade
unfabricated there would not be the case
that escape from the born become made
fabricated would be discerned
both traditions
develop sophisticated meditation techniques
for achieving these goals
Hinduism gave us yoga not just physical postures
but a comprehensive system for stilling the mind
Buddhism contributed mindfulness and Vipassana
practices now popular worldwide
what's remarkable is how these distinct philosophies
often led to similar ethical teachings
both emphasize nonviolence
ahimsa truthfulness
nonstealing and compassion for all beings
the Buddhist metta loving kindness meditation
parallels Hindu practices of universal love
so while their metaphysical frameworks differ
both traditions
offer practical methods for reducing suffering
and cultivating greater awareness and compassion
approaches that continue to influence millions of lives
today
both Hinduism and Buddhism began in the same region
but their journey since then
reveal a fascinating contrast
Buddhism largely vanished from its birthplace
by the 12th century while spreading across Asia
Hinduism remained rooted in India
until global migration carried it worldwide
today these ancient traditions face modern challenges
and influence contemporary culture in surprising ways
Buddhism entered western awareness in the 19th century
first through scholarly translations
then as a philosophical alternative to Christianity
by the 1950s writers like Alan Watts and Jack Kerouac
popularized Zen Buddhism among counterculture circles
the Dalai Lama's exile from Tibet in 1959
brought Tibetan Buddhism global attention
and by the 21st century mindfulness meditation
stripped of religious elements
had entered mainstream health care
education and corporate settings
Hinduism's western journey followed a different path
Swami Vivekananda introduced Hindu philosophy
at the 1893 World Parliament of religions
in Chicago
later yoga
originally one branch of Hindu spiritual practice
transformed into a global fitness phenomenon
the Beatles'interest in Transcendental meditation
in the 1960s sparked
wider curiosity about Hindu meditation techniques
but these traditions didn't just spread
they transformed
Western Buddhism often emphasizes meditation
and psychology while downplaying rebirth and cosmology
western yoga frequently focuses on physical postures
with little reference to its spiritual roots
these adaptations have created misunderstandings
many Westerners practice mindfulness
without realizing its Buddhist origins
or attend yoga classes
without knowing their performing postures
developed for spiritual awakening
meanwhile both traditions
continue evolving in their Asian heartlands
in Thailand
socially engaged Buddhism addresses contemporary issues
like environmentalism and economic inequality
in India Hindu traditions respond to modernization
while maintaining ancient practices
perhaps most interesting
is how these traditions
have begun to influence each other again
some modern Hindu teachers incorporate
Buddhist mindfulness practices
alongside traditional devotions
Buddhist centers occasionally
offer yoga classes that connect postures to meditation
and western spiritual seekers
often blend elements from both traditions
attending Vipassana retreats one month
and Hindu kirtan the next
is this cultural appropriation
or the natural evolution of spiritual traditions
there's no simple answer
both religions have historically
absorbed influences from cultures they encountered
academic scholar of religion
Thomas Tweed
suggests religions are not static entities
but cultural flows that constantly cross boundaries
perhaps what we're seeing is simply the latest chapter
in a conversation between these traditions
that began with the Buddha himself
what's certain is that both Hinduism and Buddhism
offer profound insights for our modern world
techniques for managing stress
philosophical frameworks for understanding immanence
ethical systems
that extend compassion beyond human boundaries
to include all life
as we discussed in what if Buddha was a Hindu God
all along
the relationship between these traditions
remains complex
some Hindus still view Buddhism as a reformed
branch of their own tradition
most Buddhists maintain their distinct identity
while acknowledging their Hindu roots
but beyond theological debates
both traditions address our universal
human need to understand suffering
and find greater peace and meaning
whether through devotion to divine forms
or mindful awareness of present experience
both offer paths to greater wisdom and compassion
the Dalai Lama often states
my religion is kindness this sentiment
simple yet profound
perhaps
captures what's most valuable in both traditions
regardless of their metaphysical differences
after exploring these two magnificent
spiritual traditions
I keep returning to one fundamental question
what does their relationship reveal
about the nature of truth itself
the Buddha and Hindu sages sought the same goal
ultimate truth that liberates
from suffering yet they reached different conclusions
one saw an eternal self identical with cosmic reality
the other saw no permanent self at all
can both be right
this paradox challenges our binary thinking
perhaps these traditions offer complementary
rather than contradictory insights
different facets of a reality
too vast for any single perspective
to capture completely
consider this thought experiment
what if the Buddha were alive today
encountering modern Hinduism and Buddhism
would he recognize either
as capturing his original intent
would he see them as different languages
describing the same spiritual landscape
or as fundamentally different paths
the ancient Hindu text
Rigveda provides a clue with its famous line
truth is one the wise call it by many names
this suggests that ultimate reality
transcends our conceptual frameworks entirely
perhaps both Buddhism and Hinduism are fingers
pointing at the moon
useful indicators but not the moon itself
this brings us to what scholars call
the two truths doctrine
a concept found in both traditions
there's conventional truth
how things appear and ultimate truth
how things actually are both perspectives are necessary
like how physics needs both
Newtonian mechanics for everyday calculations
and quantum mechanics for deeper understanding
Hindu texts describe this dual perspective
through the concept of Maya
the world is both real and unreal simultaneously
the Katha Upanishad states
what is here is also there
what is there is also here
whoever sees difference here goes from death to death
similarly the Buddhist Heart Sutra declares
form is emptiness
emptiness is form suggesting
apparent contradictions
resolve at deeper levels of understanding
I've come to believe we're asking the wrong question
when debating which tradition is correct
the deeper wisdom might lie
not in choosing between self and no self
but in understanding how these concepts shape
our moment to moment experience of being alive
modern practitioners
often find value in both approaches
using Hindu devotional practices to open the heart
and Buddhist mindfulness to see through delusion
rather than conflicting
these practices can complement each other
creating a more complete spiritual tool kit
what matters most isn't theological purity
but practical results
do these teachings help us suffer less
do they make us more compassionate
do they bring greater clarity and peace
as one ancient story tells us
a group of blind men encountered an elephant
each touched a different part tusk
trunk leg
tail and declared the elephant to be like a spear snake
pillar or rope each was partially right
based on their limited perspective
yet none grasped the whole elephant
perhaps Hinduism and Buddhism
are touching different aspects of truth
their differences don't invalidate either
but remind us that reality exceeds
our ability to conceptualize it completely
and that might be the most valuable lesson of all
in a world
increasingly fragmented by ideological divisions
these ancient traditions remind us that
contradictory truths can coexist
whether you're drawn to the Hindu
recognition of your divine nature
or the Buddhist insight that all things
including the self are impermanent processes
both paths lead toward freedom from suffering
if this exploration has opened new perspectives for you
help us continue these philosophical journeys
by subscribing to Buddha's wisdom
and hitting the notification bell
which aspects of these traditions
speak to your own experience
have certain practices from either path
transformed your understanding
share your story in the comments below
and let us know what other spiritual dialogues
you'd like us to explore in future videos
until next time
may you find wisdom on whatever path calls to you