[Music]
Tick Tock Tik Tock do you hear that it's
the sound of your life Precious Moments
slipping away as you hold on to grudges
and resentment but what if I told you
there's a way to stop the clock and
reclaim your time what if forgiveness
could be your key to unlocking a life of
Joy freedom and Endless
Possibilities hey there my fellow wisdom
Seekers It's your favorite Enlightenment
Enthusiast Matt here to take you on a
wild and transformative Journey Through
The Art of
forgiveness welcome to another episode
of Buddha's wisdom where we'll be
swapping our Grudge filled baggage for a
first class ticket to inner
peace now I know what you might be
thinking forgiveness been there done
that bought the T-shirt but trust me
this isn't your typical self-help
Spiel we're about to dive head first
into the science of resentment uncover
the secrets of letting go
and even put our forgiveness skills to
the test with a daring realworld
challenge in this episode we'll explore
the transformative power of forgiveness
through a unique lens we'll explore the
transformative power of forgiveness from
a unique
angle understanding the mind-boggling
science behind grudges sharing hilarious
and relatable stories and embarking on a
thrilling forgiveness field trip to put
our Newfound skills into action but
that's not all
along the way we'll be building our very
own forgiveness tool kit packed with
practical tips and techniques to help us
navigate even the toughest grudges and
resentments so if you're ready to let go
of the past embrace the present and
create a future filled with boundless
joy and possibilities then you've come
to the right place join me on this Epic
Quest for inner peace and together we'll
unlock the life-changing magic of
forgiveness
before we dive into the nitty-gritty of
forgiveness let me tell you a little
story about my former self you see I
used to be known as The Grudge Guru I
was the master of holding on to
resentment nurturing it like a precious
bonsai tree if someone wrong me I would
add them to my mental Grudge list vowing
never to forget or forgive their
transgression I thought I was protecting
myself building a fortress of
righteousness around my heart but in
reality I was only imprisoning myself in
a cage of my own making my grudges
became my constant companions Whispering
bitter thoughts in my ear and tainting
every interaction with suspicion and
anger it wasn't until a particularly
painful betrayal that I hit my Breaking
Point a close friend someone I trusted
deeply had spoken ill of me behind my
back when I found out I was consumed
with rage and hurt I spent days plotting
my revenge fantasizing in about the
perfect comeuppence but then something
unexpected happened in the midst of my
rumination I caught a glimpse of myself
in the mirror I hardly recognized the
person staring back at me my face was
contorted with anger my eyes Hollow and
lifeless I realized that my grudge had
turned me into someone I no longer
wanted to
be that moment was a turning point for
me I knew I needed to find a way to
break free from the prison of my own
resentment and that's when I stumbled
upon the teachings of the Buddha in the
Buddha's wisdom I found a radical new
approach to dealing with hurt and
betrayal the Buddha taught that holding
on to anger is like grasping a hot coal
with the intent of throwing it at
someone else you are the one who gets
burned forgiveness on the other hand is
like releasing that coal allowing
yourself to heal and move
forward it was a revelation for me I
realized that forgiveness wasn't about
condoning the other person's actions or
forgetting the pain they caused it was
about choosing to let go of the burning
coal of resentment so I could free
myself from suffering of course this
realization didn't magically erase all
my grudges overnight forgiveness is a
skill that requires practice and
patience but with each small Act of
forgiveness I felt a little lighter a
little more at peace and that my friends
is how the grudge Guru began began his
transformation into the Forgiveness
fanatic it's been a wild and bumpy ride
full of challenges and setbacks but
along the way I've discovered the
life-changing power of forgiveness so if
you're ready to join me on this journey
from resentment to Freedom buckle
up in the next few minutes we'll explore
the science of why forgiveness is so
hard and I'll share some practical tools
to help you start your own forgiveness
practice let's do this
before jumping into the Practical
strategies for forgiveness let's take a
moment to understand why letting go of
resentment can be so
challenging turns out there's some
fascinating science behind our Grudge
holding Tendencies you see when someone
wrongs us our brain's threat detection
system goes into high alert our amydala
the part of the brain responsible for
processing emotions sounds the alarm
triggering a Cascade of physiological
responses
our heart rate increases our muscles
tense up and our body is flooded with
stress hormones like cortisol and
adrenaline in the short term this stress
response can be adaptive helping us to
defend ourselves against potential
threats but when we hold on to
resentment long after the initial
offense our brain can get stuck in a
loop of rumination and
negativity Studies have shown that
ruminating on past grievances activates
the same neural Pathways as physical
pain in other words every time we Replay
that hurtful scenario in our mind we're
essentially reliving the pain over and
over again it's like picking at a scab
we may feel a temporary sense of
satisfaction but in the long run we're
only prolonging the healing
process moreover chronic resentment can
have serious consequences for our
physical and mental health holding on to
anger and stress has been linked to a
weakened immune system high blood
pressure and an increased risk of heart
disease it can also contribute to
anxiety depression and difficulty in
forming healthy
relationships but here's the good news
just as our brains can get stuck in a
negative feedback loop we also have the
power to rewire them for forgiveness and
resilience by practicing forgiveness we
can activate the parts of our brain
associated with empathy compassion and
positive emotions in fact research has
shown that forgiveness can have a
profound impact on our well-being people
who practice forgiveness support lower
levels of stress anxiety and depression
as well as Greater Life satisfaction and
emotional
stability forgiveness has even been
linked to improved cardiovascular health
and a stronger immune system so while
forgiveness may not come naturally to us
it's a skill that we can cultivate
through practice and
intention by understanding the science
behind resentment and its impact on our
minds and bodies we can find the
motivation to let go of our grudges and
Embrace a more forgiving
mindset it's time to talk about the
Practical tools for cultivating
forgiveness I like to call this our
forgiveness toolkit a collection of
strategies and practices that can help
us work through even the most stubborn
grudges the First Tool in our kit is
what I call the acknowledge empathize
release
framework this three-step process is a
powerful way to work through resentment
and find our way to forgiveness step one
acknowledge this means taking an honest
look at our pain and the impact it's had
on our lives it's about validating our
own feelings without judgment or blame
we might say something like I was really
hurt when my friend betrayed my trust it
made me feel angry sad and scared to be
vulnerable
again step two
empathize this is where we try to see
the situation from the other person's
perspective now this doesn't mean
condoning their behavior or excusing
their actions but it does mean
recognizing that they too are human
beings with their own struggles and
limitations we might say I can imagine
that my friend was going through a tough
time and wasn't thinking clearly when
they acted that way they're not a bad
person even though their actions caused
me
pain step three release this is where we
make the choice to let go of our
resentment and move forward it's about
recognizing that holding on to anger is
only hurting ourselves and that
forgiveness is a gift we give to
ourselves we might say I'm choosing to
release my anger towards my friend I
forgive them not because they deserve it
but because I deserve peace I'm letting
go of this burden so I can move forward
with my
life now I know this process is easier
said than done that's why our
forgiveness toolkit also includes some
practical exercises to help us work
through each step for the acknowledged
step we might try journaling about our
feelings or sharing our story with a
trusted friend the act of putting our
pain into words can be incredibly
validating and healing for the
empathized step we might try a loving
kindness meditation where we cultivate
compassion for ourselves and others we
might also try to imagine the other
person's perspective and consider the
ways in which their own pain or fear
might have contributed to their actions
and for the release step we might try a
ritual of Letting Go like writing a
letter of forgiveness and burning it or
visualizing ourselves releasing a
balloon filled with our
resentment remember forgiveness is a
process not a ontime
event it's okay if it takes time and
it's okay if we need to repeat these
steps multiple times the important thing
is that we're taking action to free
ourselves from the burden of resentment
get ready to flexx those forgiveness
muscles and watch your world
transform now that we've got our
forgiveness toolkit in hand it's time to
take this show on the road welcome to
the Forgiveness field trip where we'll
be putting our Newfound skills to the
test in the wild world of everyday
annoyances and interpersonal
conflicts our first stop on the
Forgiveness field trip is the land of
minor irritations you know those little
things that aren't necessarily a big
deal but can still get under our skin
and fester into full-blown resentment if
we're not careful for example just the
other day I was at the grocery store
minding my own business when a fellow
Shopper rammed their cart into the back
of my heels now in the past I might have
spun around and given them a piece of my
mind but armed with my forgiveness tool
kit I took a different
approach first I acknowledged my own
pain and frustration
ouch that really hurt and I feel annoyed
that this person wasn't being more
careful then I tried to empathize with
the other person's
perspective maybe they're having a
really stressful day or they're
distracted by something going on in
their life they probably didn't mean to
hurt
me finally I made the choice to release
my
resentment I'm going to choose to let
this go I don't need to hold on to this
minor annoyance and let it ruin my day
and you know what it worked instead of
stewing in my anger I was able to shrug
it off and move on with my shopping it
may seem like a small victory but these
little acts of forgiveness can add up to
a much more peaceful and positive
outlook on life but the Forgiveness
field trip isn't just about the small
stuff we'll also be tackling some bigger
challenges like forgiving a friend who
let us down or working through a
long-held family Grudge I'll be honest
these ones can be a lot tougher it's one
thing to let go of a fleeting annoyance
but it's another thing entirely to
forgive someone who's caused us deep
pain or
betrayal but here's the thing the
process is the same no matter how big or
small the
offense we start by acknowledging our
own pain and the impact it's had on our
lives we try to empathize with the other
person's perspective even if we don't
agree with their actions and finally we
make the choice to release our
resentment and move forward it's not
easy and it's not always quick forgiving
a major betrayal can be a long and
winding road with plenty of setbacks and
detours along the way but every step we
take towards forgiveness is a step
towards our own healing and
Liberation and that's what this
forgiveness field trip is all about
learning to navigate the twists and
turns of forgiveness in the real world
it's about building our forgiveness
muscles one minor IR irritation and
major conflict at a
time the road to Freedom Starts
Now I want to share with you a profound
moment that changed the course of my own
Journey it was a realization that hit me
like a bolt of lightning a forgiveness
Epiphany that shifted my entire
perspective on what it means to let go I
was in the middle of a particularly
challenging forgiveness practice working
through some deep Ed resentment towards
a family member who had hurt me in the
past I had been dutifully following the
steps of the Forgiveness
toolkit acknowledging my pain trying to
empathize with their perspective and
making the choice to release my
anger but something still felt stuck no
matter how many times I went through the
motions I couldn't seem to find that
sense of freedom and peace that I was
seeking and then in the midst of a quiet
meditation session it hit me
forgiveness isn't about the other person
at all it's about me it's about my own
healing my own Liberation from the
chains of
resentment you see I had been
approaching forgiveness as a sort of
transaction I thought that if I forgave
this person it would somehow erase the
pain they had caused me or make them see
the error of their ways but in that
Moment of clarity I realize that
forgiveness is not a bargaining chip
it's a gift that we give to ourselves
regard of how the other person
responds this realization brought to
mind a powerful story from the Buddha's
life one day the Buddha was traveling
through a village when an angry man
approached him and began to hurl insults
and accusations at him the Buddha
remained calm and composed listening
patiently to the man's TI raade when the
man had finished the Buddha simply asked
if someone offers you a gift and you
refuse to accept it to whom does the
gift belong
the man was puzzled but answered it
would still Belong To The Giver the
Buddha smiled and said in the same way I
do not accept your anger and insults
they remain with
you this story illustrates the profound
truth that forgiveness is not about
changing the other person or erasing the
past it's about choosing to release the
burden of resentment that we carry so
that we can move forward with Grace and
ease when we forgive we're not saying
that what happened was okay or that the
other person is off the hook we're
simply recognizing that holding on to
anger and bitterness is a heavy load
that we no longer wish to Bear we're
choosing to set ourselves free to
reclaim our own peace and happiness
regardless of what the other person does
or doesn't do this forgiveness Epiphany
was a turning point for me it shifted my
focus from trying to change the other
person to taking responsibility for my
own healing it allowed owed me to
approach forgiveness with a sense of
empowerment and
self-compassion rather than a sense of
obligation or guilt and the amazing
thing is when we approach forgiveness
from this place of self-love and inner
Freedom it has a ripple effect that
extends far beyond our own lives when we
model forgiveness and compassion we
Inspire others to do the same we create
a world where healing and Reconciliation
are possible where cycles of anger and
retaliation can be broken by the power
of the human spirit so I invite you to
reflect on your own forgiveness Epiphany
what might it mean for you to approach
forgiveness as a gift to yourself rather
than a demand on others how might this
shift in perspective change the way you
navigate the challenges and conflicts of
your life let's keep this wisdom close
to our hearts forgiveness is not about
them it's about us it's about our own
Freedom our own healing our own infinite
capacity for love and compassion and
that my friends is a truly revolutionary
act forgiveness is a deeply personal
Journey a choice we make to free
ourselves from the burden of resentment
and anger but the impact of forgiveness
doesn't stop there when we Embrace
forgiveness as a way of life it creates
a ripple effect that touches everyone
around us and even has the power to
transform society as a whole think about
it every time we choose to respond
respond to a hurt or conflict with
compassion and understanding rather than
anger and retaliation we're sending a
powerful message out into the world
we're saying that there's another way a
path of healing and Reconciliation that
doesn't perpetuate cycles of violence
and harm and the amazing thing is this
message has a way of spreading of
inspiring others to choose forgiveness
in their own lives it's like dropping a
pebble into a pond the ripples start
small but they keep growing and
expanding touching everything in their
path we see this ripple effect in action
every time a public figure chooses to
forgive someone who has wronged them or
when a community comes together to heal
after a
tragedy these acts of forgiveness may
start with one person but they have the
power to shift the entire culture
towards greater compassion and
understanding one powerful example of
this is the story of the Forgiveness
project a uk-based organization that
collects share stories of forgiveness
from around the world one of their most
famous stories is that of azim kamisa a
man whose son was killed by a teenage
gang member in a senseless act of
violence despite his unimaginable grief
and anger azim chose to forgive his
son's killer and even reached out to the
young man's grandfather to start a
foundation dedicated to ending youth
violence through their work azim and his
foundation have touched countless lives
inspiring young people to choose
nonviolence and fostering healing and
Reconciliation in communities torn apart
by conflict azim's choice to forgive
didn't just transform his own life it
created a ripple effect of compassion
that continues to spread to this day and
this is just one example among many from
restorative justice programs that bring
victims and offenders together to heal
to Grassroots movements for peace and
Reconciliation in war torn countries the
power of forgiveness is being harnessed
to create real tangible change in the
world so my friends as we continue on
this journey of forgiveness let's not
underestimate the impact that our own
choices can have every time we choose to
forgive to respond with compassion and
understanding we're not just healing
ourselves we're contributing to a global
shift towards a more peaceful more
compassionate world it's not always easy
and it's not always quick but the
Forgiveness ripple effect is real and
it's powerful
and it all starts with us with the
simple but revolutionary choice to let
go of our resentment and embrace a new
way of
being so let's dream big my fellow
forgiveness
revolutionaries let's imagine a world
where forgiveness is the norm where
conflicts are resolved with empathy and
understanding where cycles of violence
and retaliation are replaced by cycles
of healing and
Reconciliation it may seem like an
Impossible Dream but every great change
starts with a single Ripple the
revolution Starts
Now now it's time to take this journey
to the next level it's time to put all
of our Newfound wisdom and skills into
practice and create some serious
forgiveness momentum out in the world
and that's where the Forgiveness
challenge comes
in here's how it works I challenge each
and every one of you to commit to a
daily forgiveness practice for the next
30 30
days it doesn't have to be big or
complicated it can be as simple as
taking a few deep breaths and silently
offering forgiveness to someone who's
hurt you in the past or practicing a
loving kindness meditation to cultivate
compassion for yourself and others the
key is to make forgiveness a regular
part of your daily routine like brushing
your teeth or getting in your daily
steps by committing to this practice
you'll be strengthening your forgiveness
muscles and creating a powerful habit of
letting go and moving
forward and here's the best part you
don't have to do this
alone I invite all of you to join our
online forgiveness Revolution Community
where you can share your progress get
support and encouragement from others
and even Inspire someone else to take on
the challenge with your own forgiveness
stories imagine the collective impact we
could have if hundreds or even thousands
of us were all practicing forgiveness
every single day imagine the ripples of
compassion and healing that would spread
out into the world touching lives and
transforming communities in ways we
can't even begin to
imagine and who knows maybe your own
forgiveness Journey will be the spark
that ignites a global movement of
compassion and
Reconciliation maybe your story will be
the one that inspir someone else to
choose forgiveness over resentment peace
over conflict love over fear
so my friends are you ready to take on
the Forgiveness
challenge are you ready to join the
ranks of the Forgiveness
revolutionaries and help create a world
where forgiveness is the norm not the
exception if so I invite you to take
that first step today make a commitment
to yourself to your own healing and
freedom to practice forgiveness every
day for the next 30 days share your
pledge with our online community and
let's cheer each other on as we embark
on this transformative journey
together remember forgiveness isn't
about perfection it's about progress
It's about showing up for yourself and
others with an open heart and a
willingness to let go so be kind to
yourself take it one day at a time and
Trust in the power of small consistent
actions to create big meaningful change
and as you go forth on this forgiveness
challenge always remember forgiveness is
a choice a gift and a revolutionary act
by choosing forgiveness you're not just
changing your own life you're helping to
heal the world one compassionate ripple
at a
time so let's do this my Brave and
beautiful forgiveness Warriors let's
show the world what the power of
forgiveness can do the challenge starts
now are you
in well my friends we've reached the end
of our forgiveness journey together and
what a journey it's been we've laughed
we've cried we've faced our deepest
grudges and come out the other side
stronger wiser and more compassionate
than ever before as I look back on my
own path from Grudge Guru to forgiveness
fanatic I'm filled with a sense of
gratitude and
awe gratitude for the teachings of
forgiveness that have transformed my
life in ways I never could have imagined
and awe at the incredible power we all
have within us to Choose Love over fear
peace over conflict Freedom over
resentment but here's the thing my wise
and wonderful friends this journey
doesn't end here in fact it's just the
beginning because the real work of
forgiveness doesn't happen in a YouTube
video or a social media post it happens
out there in the world in the choices we
make and the actions we take every
single day so as we come to the end of
our time together I want to leave you
with a few parting words of encour
encouragement and
inspiration first and foremost remember
that forgiveness is a journey not a
destination it's not about achieving
some state of perfect peace and
Tranquility but rather about committing
to the Daily practice of letting go
again and again and
again there will be days when
forgiveness feels impossible when the
hurt and anger feel too deep to overcome
but in those moments remember that you
have all the tools and wisdom you need
to keep moving forward
remember the power of acknowledging your
pain extending empathy and compassion
and making the choice to release your
resentment remember that every small Act
of forgiveness is a victory a step
towards your own healing and freedom and
most importantly remember that you are
not alone on this journey you are part
of a global community of forgiveness
revolutionaries all working together to
create a world of Greater compassion
understanding and peace so reach out for
support when you need it share your own
stories and wisdom with others and never
underestimate the power of your own
ripples to create
change and now my friends it's time for
me to pass the torch to you because the
real forgiveness Revolution doesn't
start with me it starts with each and
every one of you so here's my challenge
to
you take the Forgiveness toolkit we've
built together and put it into practice
every single day make forgiveness a
non-negotiable part of your daily
routine whether it's through meditation
journaling or simply pausing to extend
compassion to someone who's hurt you
share your journey with others whether
it's through our online community or in
your own personal
circles Inspire others with your stories
of forgiveness and transformation and
invite them to join the revolution with
you and most importantly never give up
on the power of forgiveness to change
lives and transform the
world keep spreading those ripples of
compassion one act of forgiveness at a
time and Trust in the incredible impact
you can
have so my wonderful friends this is
Matt signing off for
now it's been an absolute honor and joy
to be your guide on this forgiveness
journey and I can't wait to see where
your own path takes you remember
forgiveness isn't about them it's about
you it's about your own Freedom your own
healing your own boundless capacity for
love and
compassion so keep choosing forgiveness
every single day keep being a
revolutionary of love in a world that so
desperately needs it and always always
stay curious stay compassionate stay
courageous because that my friends is
the True Heart of wisdom until next time
keep shining your beautiful light in the
world the Forgiveness Revolution starts
now and it starts with you Namaste my
amazing beings of love and light keep on
forgiving on