what if I told you that
the moment someone becomes enlightened
it's said their voice can echo through mountain valleys
a skeletal green figure moments
away from being destroyed by supernatural demons
suddenly opens his mouth and sings words so powerful
they transform terror into wisdom
this isn't background meditation music
this is the sound of a soul
breaking free from the darkest karma imaginable
today we witness the most intense
spiritual breakthrough ever recorded
and discover why
Milarepa's songs are still chanted in Tibetan
monasteries 1,000 years later
can poetry really become the path to enlightenment
can a voice change an entire civilization
you're about to find out
welcome back to Buddha's wisdom
I'm Matt
and we're diving into the heart of the most impossible
redemption story in Buddhist history
last episode ended with the ultimate cliffhanger
Milarepa facing supernatural demons
in what could be his final test
three years in what he called the Green Nettle Cave
a body turned the color of Jade
from eating nothing but stinging weeds
and now
spiritual forces that could destroy him completely
remember how we followed his path
from mass murderer to broken hermit
35 people killed with black magic
then years of brutal training under Marpa
the translator tower after tower
built and demolished until his hands bled
tonight
determines whether someone who's committed mass murder
can actually achieve complete enlightenment
legends condense years of spiritual practice
into this dramatic night of transformation
what you're about to witness created one
of Tibet's greatest masters
a figure whose spontaneous songs would heal communities
inspire generations
and prove that no darkness is too deep for redemption
over the next 25 minutes
you'll witness the exact moment darkness becomes light
you'll hear the first words of what would
become known as the hundred thousand songs of Milarepa
and you'll understand why they called him
the singing Saint but first
we need to see if he survives the night
the demon surrounded Milarepa like a supernatural storm
eyes blazing with accumulated fury
claws extended like knives
ready to tear apart this skeletal figure
who dared face the weight of mass murder
his verses recall what happened next
as completely unexpected
instead of fighting or fleeing
Milarepa stood up from his meditation posture
looked directly at these manifestations
of his worst karma
and spoke words that changed everything
you are not my enemies
he said to the terrifying figures surrounding him
you are my teachers
the demons paused confused by this response
Tibetan elders still say that Milarepa
then did something that defied every survival instinct
he opened his arms as if welcoming beloved friends
and continued speaking to these supernatural forces
his voice grew stronger with each word
for years I've tried to run from you through meditation
through cave retreats
through making my body green with nettles
but you've been waiting patiently
to teach me the most important lesson of all
one account describes the lead demon
the one wearing the face of his uncle's wedding guests
stepping closer with claws raised
and what lesson is that it demanded
Milarepa's response
preserved in the hundred thousand songs
created the transformation that made him legendary
the moment he spoke these words
his disciples later told something miraculous happened
the demons began to dissolve
not destroyed by force but transformed by recognition
as Milarepa accepted complete
responsibility for his actions
without defending himself
without making excuses
the supernatural manifestations of his guilt
began changing into something else entirely
oral traditions tell us them becoming dakini wisdom
beings who dance in the spaces between thoughts
teachers who appear in frightening forms
to guide students toward enlightenment
and then
according to monasteries that still preserve this tale
something even more extraordinary occurred
words began flowing from Milarepa's mouth
not planned speech not memorized prayers
but spontaneous poetry
that seemed to come from awakened consciousness itself
in his hundred thousand songs
Milarepa actually recorded this pivotal moment
legends imagine him singing lines like in the sky
of mind clouds gather and disperse
but the sky itself remains unchanged
in the ocean of consciousness
waves rise and fall
but the water itself is never disturbed
Tibetan valleys still echo with stories of his voice
carrying impossible distances
through the mountain passes
reaching Marpa's house miles away
waking sleeping villagers
with words that seemed to heal
something broken in their hearts
when dawn broke over the mountains
one song remembers that Marpa
the translator appeared at the meditation site
he took one look at his transformed student
and smiled for the first time in years
the killer is dead he reportedly said
what remains is a master
Milarapa no longer green and skeletal
but somehow radiant despite his physical condition
bowed to his teacher and sang another spontaneous verse
three years of caves and years of towers
all preparing for this single night
when the student finally disappears
the teacher's work is complete
Tibetan monasteries still chant this story
of the moment
Milarepa achieved what Buddhism calls rigpa
direct recognition of the awakened state
that had always been present
beneath the layers of guilt and suffering
but his transformation was about to
become even more extraordinary
because when consciousness awakens completely
it cannot help but sing
his poetry describes what happened
after his enlightenment
as unlike anything in Buddhist history
most realized masters teach through explanations
through guided meditation
through philosophical discussions
Milaripa's awakened consciousness expressed itself
through spontaneous songs
that seemed to heal whatever they touched
what made his songs different from ordinary poetry
each verse emerged directly from the enlightened state
addressing the exact
spiritual needs of whoever was listening
unlike written teachings
that speak generally to all readers
milaripa songs seemed to know the specific pain
each person carried
villagers described incredible stories
about the power of his voice
when he sang near a mountainside scarred by landslides
new vegetation began growing from damaged rock
when his songs echoed through valleys
even the wind seemed to pause and listen
but his voice carried something
deeper than supernatural power
it carried the sound of a soul that had faced its worst
karma accepted it completely
and transformed it into compassion
can you imagine what that sounds like
the voice of someone who's been to hell and back
who's carried the weight of 35 murders
and emerged not bitter but overflowing with love
the ultimate test came when word reached the community
still traumatized by memories of the supernatural storm
that had killed 35 wedding guests
years earlier
when residents recognized this transformed figure
as the sorcerer who had caused their suffering
they were terrified some fled
others grabbed weapons
children hid behind their parents
this skeletal green
tinged figure looked like what villagers called
a hungry ghost
a spirit of someone who had died with terrible karma
and couldn't find peace
instead of defending himself or making excuses
monasteries preserve the story of Milarepa
sitting in the village center
and beginning to sing about the nature
of forgiveness
his voice according to those who heard it
carried a quality that made anger impossible
to maintain
not because he was using
some kind of supernatural charm
but because genuine remorse
has a sound that hearts recognize instantly
one of his most famous verses
actually recorded in his hundred thousand songs
captures this moment
then legends
imagine him singing directly about their shared pain
villagers described weeping as they listened
not from sadness but from a deep healing
they couldn't explain the sound of his voice
the obvious sincerity of his remorse
the genuine transformation they could see and feel
gradually melted years of accumulated grief and anger
by the end of his songs
the community that had feared him for years
was asking for his teachings
can you imagine that moment
the people whose relatives you murdered
asking you for spiritual guidance
the transformation had to be complete authentic
undeniable
but the most extraordinary encounter was still coming
when Milarepa
finally returned to visit his mother and sister
the reunion seemed impossible
after everything that had happened
his mother
who had demanded he learn black magic for revenge
took one look at her transformed son and collapsed
she recognized immediately what her anger had created
and what it had ultimately become
his verses recall her
confessing her role in turning him into a killer
begging forgiveness
for her part in the deaths of 35 innocent people
Milarepa's response as preserved in his collected songs
demonstrates the complete transformation
from vengeful sorcerer to enlightened master
his sister Peta
who had watched him transform from beloved brother
to mass murderer to enlightened Yogi
finally found peace with the impossible journey
they had all survived
she later told people that her brother's voice
had changed completely
where once it carried hatred and magical power
now it overflowed with a tenderness
that could heal ancient wounds
this was the moment that marked
Milarepa's true emergence
as a spiritual master not when he defeated demons
but when he healed the hearts of those he had harmed
most
the songs were beginning to spread throughout Tibet
and they would change everything
over the next several years
Tibetan valleys remember Milarepa
leaving Marpa's guidance to begin legendary wandering
throughout the most remote regions of the plateau
the high passes were treacherous
where wind could freeze breath in your lungs
and thin air made every step a struggle
winter storms could trap travelers for months in caves
barely large enough for survival
yet in these impossible conditions
Milarepa thrived
unlike conventional Buddhist teachers
who established monasteries
Milarepa became known for appearing
wherever suffering needed healing
often in places so isolated
that finding him required genuine spiritual dedication
his teaching method was revolutionary
rather than formal dharma talks
he would assess each person's specific spiritual needs
and sing spontaneous verses
that addressed their exact situation
the silence of high
mountain caves carried an otherworldly quality
when wind stopped howling and snow ceased falling
the stillness was so profound
it seemed to press against your eardrums
in these moments of absolute quiet
his voice would emerge
like sunlight breaking through storm clouds
one song remembers a wealthy merchant
who climbed dangerous mountain passes
searching for milarepa
the merchant had everything material
comfort could provide but felt completely empty inside
when he finally found Milarepa
meditating in a cave
barely large enough for one person
frost coating the stone walls
breath visible in the frigid air
the merchant offered gold and jewels
in exchange for teachings
for a long moment
only the sound of wind outside broke the cave silence
then Milarepa's voice filled the space
as preserved in his collected verses
we hear Milarepa responding with lines like
you carry treasures up the mountain
seeking something you already possess
the wealth you seek cannot be bought
it can only be recognized
look at this cave
nothing here belongs to me yet I lack nothing
what would you trade for
a single song that could heal your emptiness
one disciple's account says
that the merchant left his material wealth in the cave
return to his valley
and began living with a simplicity and contentment
that amazed everyone who knew him
but
not everyone was ready for Milarepa's radical message
when his growing reputation attracted attention
from established religious authorities
they questioned whether this wandering
cave dweller could really possess genuine
spiritual attainments
a renowned scholar monk arranged a formal challenge
expecting to expose what he assumed
was superficial realization
the scholar posed complex
philosophical questions about emptiness
and meditation stages
Milarepa's response was unexpected
he began singing verses
that directly demonstrated the understanding
being tested
you ask about emptiness
as if it were separate from form
but look at this monastery
solid walls built from empty space
the scholar who had come to expose Milarepa as a fraud
instead requested teachings from him
perhaps the most significant challenge
came from followers of Bon
Tibet's ancient pre Buddhist tradition
who claimed his powers were simply
continuation of black magic
monasteries still chant Milarepa's response
demonstrating complete transformation
from sorcerer to saint
rather than displaying supernatural abilities
he invited his challengers to examine his motivation
his challengers
became some of his most devoted students
this pattern defined his wandering years
the master
who had once used supernatural power for revenge
now used awakened abilities
solely for healing and teaching
after years of wandering
Tibetan elders still say that Milarepa's reputation
transcended religious boundaries
and touched every level of society
communities throughout the region
began requesting visits from the singing yogi
his influence spread
not through institutional authority
but through transformed lives
that served as living testimonies to his teachings
oral traditions recall villages
where his brief visits left lasting changes
communities divided by old feuds
found reconciliation
after hearing his verses about forgiveness
regions plagued by natural disasters
reported improved conditions after his presence
but what made his influence unique was its authenticity
unlike religious authorities
who demanded respect based on position
Milarepa's authority came entirely from the obvious
genuineness of his transformation
people could see that this was someone
who had genuinely walked the path
from darkness to light
his scarred hands told the story of years
building towers for Marpa
his lean frame and traces of green coloration
preserved evidence of cave years
sustained by nettles
his eyes carried the depth of someone
who had faced the worst karma imaginable
and emerged victorious
one song preserves accounts of hardened criminals
abandoning violence
after hearing his verses about karma
wealthy merchants gave away fortunes
after his songs
revealed the emptiness of material accumulation
scholars burned books and sought direct experience
after his poetry showed them the limitations
of intellectual understanding
these transformations happened spontaneously
not through lengthy instruction or formal ceremonies
but through immediate recognition of awakened
consciousness expressing itself through song
his disciples told of a particularly moving encounter
with a young woman
who had lost her entire family to disease
leaving her consumed by anger
at the apparent injustice of existence
the old songs recall Milarepa finding her
preparing to throw herself from a cliff
choosing death over continuing to live with such pain
he didn't try to talk her out of suicide
or offer philosophical explanations
instead
he sang about his own journey from despair to awakening
she stepped back from the cliff
and eventually found her own path to healing
this story echoes the deeper pattern
we saw in his family reunion
showing how genuine transformation
creates ripples of healing
that touch everyone around it
the killer who became a saint
the destroyer who became a healer
the voice of hatred that became a song of compassion
as the oral traditions still preserved records
Milarepa actually wrote
legends imagine him
adding verses that capture his essential message
your worst mistakes can become your greatest teachers
your deepest darkness can birth your brightest light
nothing is wasted everything serves the path
the singing saint had emerged from
the depths of karma
to prove that redemption is possible
for anyone willing to face their actions completely
accept responsibility without excuses
and trust
the transformative power of awakened consciousness
by this time his voice was known throughout Tibet
students were beginning to gather around him
the foundations were being laid for what would
become one of Buddhism's most influential lineages
and his greatest adventures were still ahead
the wandering yogi
was about to become something even more extraordinary
can you imagine
the courage required to face your worst mistakes
accept complete responsibility
and transform them into wisdom
that's the question
Milarepa's story asks every one of us
what impossible transformation awaits
on the other side of your deepest regrets
the singing saint who emerged from darkness
to become Tibet's beloved master
proves that no one is beyond redemption
no mistake is too great no fall is too deep
if Milarepa's journey from killer to saint
has moved you if you believe transformation is possible
even after the worst failures
then subscribe and stay with us
because next week we meet his most famous disciples
witness the establishment of the Kagyu lineage
and discover how a wandering
yogi became one of history's most influential teachers
what songs would you sing if you achieved enlightenment
leave a comment below
sometimes the path to healing begins with admitting
we need it
to be continued in Part 4 the great Yogi