[Music]
hey what's up wisdom Seekers Matt here
from Buddha's
wisdom last time we dove into the first
five chapters of the DAP and you all
loved
it today we're continuing our journey
with chapters 6 through 10 just like
before I'll read these powerful verses
on interrupted letting this ancient
wisdom speak directly to you ever wonder
how to tell who's truly in a world full
of fake gurus or what real freedom feels
like not the Instagram version but the
Deep unshakable kind the Buddha's got
answers that will completely change how
you see things you know those moments
when one sentence hits harder than an
entire book that's exactly what we'll
explore in the chapter on
thousands and just wait until we get to
the parts about how tiny choices create
massive ripples in our lives the best
part these teachings aren't just ancient
philosophy their practical wisdom that's
been tested for over two Millennia they
worked then they work now and they'll
probably still work when we're all
riding flying cars so find a quiet spot
take a deep breath and let's dive into
these transformative teachings together
no fluff no modern spin just pure
uninterrupted wisdom that's as relevant
today as it was 2,500 years ago
[Music]
chapter 6 shows us what true wisdom
looks like in action the Buddha teaches
us how to recognize and learn from Wise
people and how wisdom transforms every
aspect of Our
Lives should one find a wise critic to
point out faults and give valuable
advice let one follow such a sage as one
would a guide to Hidden
Treasure it is always better never worse
to cultivate such Association
let them advise instruct and discourage
one from
wrongdoing such a person is truly dear
to the good though not to the
evil do not associate with evil friends
do not associate with mean people
associate with good friends associate
with noble
people one who drinks deeply of the
Dharma lives happily with a peaceful
mind the wise one always Delights in the
dharm taught by the noble
ones irrigators guide the water
Fletchers shape the arrow Carpenters
bend the wood the wise control
themselves just as a solid rock Remains
unshaken by the wind so too the wise
remain unshaken by Praise or
blame like a deep lake clear and
unruffled the wise become tranquil after
hearing the
dharm good people give up everything the
peaceful do not prattle about Pleasures
whether touched by happiness or by
sorrow the wise show neither Elation nor
depression neither for one's own sake
nor for the sake of another does a wise
person do any wrong he does not desire
son wealth or Kingdom by doing wrong he
does not seek his own success by unfair
means such a one alone is virtuous wise
and
righteous few among men are those who
cross to the further Shore the rest the
bulk of men only run up and down the
hither bank but those who practice
according to the well expounded Dharma
will cross the realm of death so
difficult to
[Music]
cross chapter 7 reveals the state of one
who has reached the highest goal in
Buddhism the ARA
these verses paint a picture of complete
freedom and peace that comes from
letting go of all
attachments there's no more suffering
for one who has completed the journey
who is free from sorrow who has freed on
on all sides who has thrown off all
shackles the mindful exert themselves
they are not attached to any home like
swans that abandon the lake they leave
home after home
[Music]
behind those who do not accumulate and
are wise regarding food whose object is
the void the unconditioned freedom their
track cannot be traced like that of
birds in the
air one whose Corruptions are destroyed
who is free from attachment to food
whose object is the void the
unconditioned freedom their path cannot
be traced like that of birds in the air
even the gods hold dear the Wise One
whose senses are subdued like horses
well trained by a charioteer whose pride
is destroyed and who is free from the
Corruptions like the earth a balanced
and well-disciplined person resents
nothing they are comparable to a pillar
of stone like a pool free from mud for
such a one there is no more wandering in
samsara
calm is their mind calm is their speech
calm is their action who rightly knowing
are wholly freed perfectly tranquil and
wise the person who is free from
gullibility who knows the uncreated who
has severed all ties removed all
Temptations renounced all
desires that person is truly great
whether in Village or Forest whether in
Valley or on Hill wherever arahats dwell
that spot is
delightful delightful are the forests
where worldlings find no pleasure there
the passionless Will Rejoice for they
seek no sensual
[Music]
Pleasures chapter 8 teaches us about
what really counts in life using the
number thousand as a power metaphor the
Buddha shows us how one moment of true
wisdom is worth more than a lifetime of
thoughtless
actions better than a thousand useless
words is one useful word hearing which
one attains
peace better than a thousand useless
verses is one useful verse hearing which
one attains
peace better than reciting a 100
meaningless verses is the reciting of
one verse of Dharma hearing which one
attains
peace though one may conquer a thousand
times a thousand men in battle yet he
indeed is the noblest Victor who
conquers
himself self-conquest is far better than
the conquest of others not even a god an
angel Mara or Brahma can turn into
defeat the victory of a person who is
self- subdued and ever restrained in
conduct
month after month for a thousand years
one may make offerings with a thousand
coins yet if only for a moment one pays
homage to a person perfected in
meditation that homage is better than a
century of
sacrifice though for a hundred years one
may tend the sacrificial fire in the
forest yet if only for a moment one pays
homage to a person perfected in
meditation that omage is better than a
century of
sacrifice whatever gifts and oblations
one seeking Merit might offer in this
world for a whole year all that is not
worth 1/4 of the Merit gained by
revering the upright
ones for one who always honors and
respects the elders four blessings
increase long life Beauty happiness and
strength
better than living a hundred years
immoral and uncontrolled is living one
day virtuous and
meditative better than living a 100
years unwise and uncontrolled is living
one day wise and
meditative better than living a 100
years idle and weak in energy is living
one day strenuous and
Resolute better than living a hundred
years not seeing the rise and fall of
things
is living one day seeing their rise and
fall better than living a hundred years
not seeing the deathless state is living
one day seeing the deathless
state better than living a 100 years not
seeing the Supreme truth is living one
day seeing the Supreme
[Music]
truth chapter 9 Dives deep into
understanding evil not to scare us but
to help us recognize and avoid harmful
actions the Buddha shows us how small
wrong choices can have big consequences
and how we can protect ourselves through
mindful
living make haste in doing good restrain
your mind from
Evil he who is slow in doing good his
mind Delights in
evil should a person commit evil let him
not do it again and again let him not
find pleasure therein for painful is the
accumulation of
evil should a person do good let him do
it again and again let him find pleasure
therein for Blissful is the accumulation
of
good even an evil person may enjoy
happiness as long as their evil deed
does not ripen but when their evil deed
ripens then the evil person sees their
evil Deeds
even a good person may suffer when their
Good Deed has not ripened but when it
ripens then the good person sees the
good
results think not lightly of Evil saying
it will not come to me drop by drop is
the water pot
filled likewise the fool Gathering it
little by little fills himself with
evil think not lightly of good saying it
will not come to me drop by drop is the
water pot filled likewise the wise man
Gathering it little by little fills
himself with
good just as a traiter with a small
escort and great wealth would avoid a
perilous route or just as one Desiring
to live avoids poison even so should one
shun
evil if on the hand there is no wound
one may carry even poison in it poison
does not affect one who is free from
wounds for one who does no evil there is
no
ill like fine dust thrown Against the
Wind evil falls back upon that fool who
offends an inoffensive pure and
Guiltless
person some are born in the womb the
wicked are born in Hell The Devout go to
heaven the stainless pass into
nibana neither in the sky nor in mid
ocean nor nor by entering into Mountain
cffs nowhere in the world is there a
place where one may escape from the
results of evil
Deeds neither in the sky nor in mid
ocean nor by entering into Mountain cffs
nowhere in the world is there a place
where one will not be overcome by
[Music]
death chapter 10 explores how we create
suffering for ourselves and others the
Buddha teaches us about the universal
human wish to be happy and free from
harm helping us understand why
compassion is the wisest
Choice all tremble at punishment all
fear death drawing the parallel to
yourself neither kill nor get others to
kill all tremble at punishment life is
dear to all drawing the parallel to
yourself neither kill nor get others to
kill whoever seeking his own happiness
hurts with the rod others who also
desire happiness will not find happiness
after
death whoever seeking his own happiness
hurts not with a
rod others who also desire happiness
will find happiness after
death speak not harshly to anyone for
those thus spoken to might retort indeed
angry speech hurts and retaliation May
overtake you
if like a broken gong you Silence
Yourself you have approached nabana for
vindictiveness is no longer in
you just as a cow herd drives the cattle
to pasture with a staff so do old age
and Death Drive the life force of
beings when the fool commits evil Deeds
he does not realize their nature the
witless man is tormented by his own
Deeds like one burnt by fire
he who inflicts violence on those who
are unarmed and offends those who are
inoffensive will soon come upon one of
these 10
states sharp pain or disaster bodily
injury serious illness or derangement of
Mind trouble from the government or
grave charges loss of relatives or loss
of wealth or houses destroyed by
ravaging fire upon dissolution of the
body that ignorant man is born in
Hell neither going about naked nor
matted locks nor filth nor fasting nor
lying on the ground nor smearing oneself
with ashes and dust nor sitting on one's
heels can purify a mortal who has not
overcome
doubt even though he be well attired yet
if he is poised calm controlled and
established in the Holy life having set
aside violence towards all all beings he
truly is a holy man a renunciate a
monk only rarely is there a man in this
world who restrained by modesty avoids
reproach as a thoroughbred horse avoids
the
whip like a thoroughbred horse touched
by the whip be strenuous be filled with
spiritual yearning by faith and moral
Purity by effort and meditation by
investigation of the truth by being rich
in knowledge and virtue and by being
mindful destroy this unlimited
suffering irrigators regulate the rivers
Fletchers straighten the arrow shaft
Carpenters shape the wood the wise
control
themselves and there you have it wisdom
Seekers five more powerful chapters from
the dapada each verse is like a key to
understanding our ourselves better and
living more mindfully remember these
teachings aren't just ancient wisdom
they're practical tools for Modern
Life think about how many times you've
faced situations like the ones described
in these
verses next week Peter and I will break
down everything we just covered making
it super relevant for your daily
life plus I'll be back with more
chapters of pure dap
readings if any verse particular L spoke
to you today share your thoughts in the
comments
below I love hearing how these teachings
connect with your lives this is Matt
from Buddha's wisdom and I'll catch you
in the next one stay curious stay wise