[Music]
[Applause]
ever wondered what happens after we die
in Buddhism the concept of hell is
anything but ordinary imagine waking up
one morning and realizing that your
entire life has been a series of
missteps and poor choices you're
suddenly faced with the unsettling
thought that your actions might have
some serious consequences in the
afterlife enter the concept of Buddhist
hell
a topic that's sure to raise some
eyebrows and get those mental gears
turning now I know the word hell can be
a bit of a buzzkill but trust me when I
say that the Buddhist version is far
from your typical fire and brimstone
nightmare in fact it's a fascinating and
complex concept that ties into the very
core of Buddhist teachings about Karma
rebirth and the nature of
suffering before we jump head first into
this intriguing topic allow me to extend
a warm welcome to all our viewers both
old and new I'm Matt one half of the
Buddha's wisdom team and along with my
fellow wisdom Seeker Peter I'm here to
explore the profound insights of
Buddhism so are you ready to have your
preconceptions about hell turned upside
down we're about to unravel the
mysteries of Buddhist hell and discover
how this ancient concept can actually
shed light on our modern lives get ready
for some mindbending Revelations a
Sprinkle of humor and maybe even a
newfound appreciation for the
complexities of The Human
Experience let's
go all right let's take a step back and
set the stage for our exploration of
Buddhist hell to really understand this
concept we need to touch on a couple of
fundamental Buddhist principles first up
we have Karma the idea that our actions
have consequences that can Ripple out
across
lifetimes if you missed previous video
on Karma don't worry you can click the
link below to catch up trust me it's a
game changer next we have the concept of
rebirth or samsara this is the belief
that we're not just one and done when it
comes to living instead we're caught in
an ongoing cycle of birth death and
rebirth with our Karma influencing the
nature of each new
existence again if you need a refresher
check out Peter's awesome video on
samsara it's like a crash course in
Buddhist Phil philosophy think of karma
as a cosmic scorecard and samsara as an
endless game of
rebirths now here's where it gets juicy
according to Buddhist teachings there
are six main Realms into which we can be
reborn picture a cosmic game of roulette
except instead of landing on red or
black you could end up as a Heavenly
being a human an animal a Hungry Ghost
and aura or Titan or you guessed it in
one of the hell realms
now before you start having nightmares
about eternal damnation let me clarify
something
important the Buddhist hell Realms are
not like the fiery infernos you might
have heard about in other religious
traditions in Buddhism hell is more like
a temporary timeout a place where you
experience the consequences of your
negative actions until your karma runs
its course so yes the hell Realms are
definitely not a vacation destination
but the good news is that in Budd ISM
nothing lasts forever not even the most
intense
suffering with the right actions
intentions and mindset it's always
possible to break free from the cycle of
rebirth and set your sights on a better
future okay so now that we've covered
the basics let's get into the
nitty-gritty of Buddhist hell in
Buddhism the hell Realms are
collectively known as nraa and they're
not just one size fits all there are
multiple multiple hell Realms each with
its own unique brand of suffering now
before we dive into the specifics it's
important to note that the descriptions
of the hell Realms can vary depending on
the Buddhist text in the Mahayana
mahaparinirvana Sutra for example the
hell Realms are depicted somewhat
differently compared to the Dharma
analysis treasury but regardless of the
specific details these Realms are all
situated right here on our very own
Kavala or World system according to
Buddhist cosmology
picture a cosmic layer cake with each
realm stacked on top of the other and
the hell Realms are right there at the
bottom let's start with the cold Hells
shall We There are eight great cold
Hells each with a name that will make
you want to reach for a warm blanket in
ascending order of severity we have one
arbuda the blister hell where the
intense cold causes blisters to form on
beings
bodies two Nar Buddha the burst blister
hell where the blisters burst open
causing excruciating
pain three
atata the Shivering hell where beings
shiver uncontrollably in the bitter
cold four haah Hava the lamentation hell
where beings cry out in agony from the
freezing temperatures five Hua the
chattering teeth hell where beings teeth
chatter incessantly from the
cold six utala
the Blue Lotus hell where the skin turns
blue like a lotus flower from the
extreme
cold seven Padma the Lotus hell where
the skin cracks open like a Lotus
Blossom eight mahapadma the great Lotus
hell the coldest and most severe of all
the cold Hells but wait there's more we
haven't even gotten to the hot Hells yet
like the cold Hells there are eight
major hot Hells each with its own unique
form of fiery torment one sanjiva the
Reviving hell where beings are cut
crushed or burned only to be revived and
tormented again two kalasutra the black
thread hell where beings are marked with
hot black lines and then cut along those
lines three
samata the crushing hell where beings
are crushed between massive hot
objects four rava the screaming hell
where the intense heat causes beings to
scream in
agony five maharo rava the great
screaming hell an even more intense
version of
rava six tapana the heating hell where
beings are impaled on red hot spikes
seven rapana the great heating hell and
even more severe version of
tapana eight
aaii the uninterrupted erupted hell the
deepest and most intense of all the hot
Hells now I know what you might be
thinking geez Matt this all sounds
pretty grim and you're not wrong the
naraka Realms are definitely not a walk
in the park but here's the thing in
Buddhism these hell Realms are not meant
to be taken literally they're powerful
metaphors for the suffering we can
experience in our own minds when we're
trapped in negative patterns of thought
and behavior when we're consumed by
anger hatred or greed it's like we're in
our own personal hell realm we're
tormented by our own negative emotions
unable to find peace or happiness and
just like in the nraa Realms it can feel
like there's no Escape but that's where
Buddhist practice comes in by
cultivating mindfulness compassion and
wisdom we can begin to break free from
our own mental hell Realms we can learn
to observe our thoughts and emotions
without getting caught up in them and we
can make choices that align with our
values and lead to Greater happiness and
peace so while the descriptions of the
nraa Realms might seem Intense or even
frightening they ultimately serve as a
powerful reminder of the importance of
our own thoughts actions and mind states
by taking responsibility for our own
minds and cultivating positive qualities
we can begin to free ourselves from
suffering both in this life and Beyond
so what's the point of all this why does
Buddhism emphasize these vivid
descriptions of
suffering first and foremost the hell
Realms remind us of the consequences of
our actions in Buddhism our thoughts
words and deeds impact not just
ourselves but also those around us and
the world as a whole negative actions
create the causes for future suffering
the hell Realms are not a punishment
handed down by some external Authority
but the natural result of our choices
and
behaviors just as a plant will bear
fruit according to the type of seed
planted our actions bear fruit according
to their nature these Realms also serve
as a powerful motivation for Spiritual
practice and personal
growth contemplating the suffering of
the hell Realms can develop a sense of
urgency and determination to break free
from negative thoughts and actions this
is where the Buddhist path of
mindfulness comp passion and wisdom
comes in by cultivating these positive
qualities we can begin to transform our
own minds and hearts Breaking Free from
the mental hell Realms that cause us so
much pain and
distress we can learn to respond to
challenges with greater equinity to
treat others with kindness and
understanding and to make choices that
lead to Greater peace and
happiness ultimately the purpose of the
hell Realms in Buddhism is not to scare
us or to condemn us but to wake us up to
shake us out of our complacency and
Inspire us to take responsibility for
our own minds and
actions by confronting the reality of
suffering headon we can develop the
compassion wisdom and skillful means
needed to transform that suffering and
to help others do the
same but how do we actually break free
from this cycle of suffering how do we
escape the endless round of rebirth and
find lasting peace and
happiness now for our regular viewers
this next part might be a bit of a
refresher but it's always good to
revisit the foundations of our practice
right as we've discussed many times
before the key to Breaking Free from the
cycle of suffering lies in the three
essential practices at the heart of the
Buddhist path mindfulness compassion and
wisdom these practices are like the
secret sauce of spiritual growth the
ingredients that when combined and
cultivated over time can lead us to the
ultimate goal of Enlightenment and what
is Enlightenment it's the complete
Liberation from suffering and the cycle
of rebirth a state of perfect wisdom
compassion and peace beyond all the ups
and downs of worldly
existence but as we all know this path
is not a quick fix or a Magic Bullet it
requires dedication effort and a
willingness to confront our own thoughts
emotions and behaviors with honesty and
compassion by cultivating mindfulness we
learn to observe our own experiences
with greater Clarity and
objectivity by cultivating compassion we
learn to connect with the suffering of
others and to respond with kindness and
skillful action and by cultivating
wisdom we learn to see through the
illusions of the self and the world to
understand the true nature of reality
beyond all Concepts and
categories I know many of you have heard
this before but it Bears repeating these
practices are not just abstract ideas or
lofty ideals they're practical tools
that we can apply in our daily lives
Moment by moment and the more we
cultivate them the more we begin to
experience their transformative power
the way they can help us break free from
old patterns of suffering and find
greater peace happiness and connection
in our
lives regardless of your background or
level of experience with Buddhism
remember the key to escaping the cycle
of suffering lies in the cultivation of
mindfulness compassion and wisdom it's a
journey that requires patience
perseverance and an open heart but it's
a journey that can lead to the greatest
happiness and freedom
imaginable how do these beliefs about
hell Realms in the cycle of rebirth
translate into real world Buddhist
practices one fascinating example is the
ghost Festival a traditional Buddhist
holiday observed in many Asian countries
particularly in China and
Vietnam during the Ghost Festival also
known as The Hungry Ghost Festival or
Ulen pen Festival it's believed that the
gates of hell are opened and the spirits
of the deceased are allowed to visit the
Living
World this includes not only ancestors
but also ghosts and spirits who have no
living descendants to venerate
them Buddhist practitioners and
community ities engage in various
rituals and offerings during this time
such as preparing food and drink for the
spirits burning JS paper a type of
ceremonial paper money and chanting
scriptures these practices are believed
to help alleviate the suffering of
beings in the hell Realms and to
generate Merit for both the living and
the deceased the Ghost Festival serves
as a powerful reminder of the
interconnectedness of all beings both
living and dead and the importance of
compassion and gener oity in the face of
suffering it's a time for Buddhists to
reflect on the impermanence of Life the
consequences of our actions and the
potential for spiritual growth and
Liberation so the next time you hear
about the Ghost Festival or similar
practices in Buddhist communities keep
in mind the deeper significance Behind
These rituals they're not just colorful
cultural Traditions they're a reflection
of the profound teachings on suffering
rebirth and the path to Enlightenment
that lie at the heart of
Buddhism as we explore these Concepts
it's crucial to approach them with
cultural sensitivity and an awareness of
potential pitfalls such as
orientalism orientalism as coined by
scholar Edward SED refers to the
tendency of Western cultures to view and
represent Eastern cultures in a
stereotypical exoticized or
essentialized
manner when it comes to Buddhist hell
realms there's a risk of falling into
orientalist traps such as focusing on
the most Sensational or gruesome aspects
of these teachings without proper
context or understanding it's important
to remember that Buddhist teachings on
Hell Realms are part of a complex
nuanced religious and philosophical
tradition they're not meant to be taken
literally or in isolation but rather as
part of a larger framework for
understanding suffering Karma and the
path to
Enlightenment as we explore these
Concepts let's strive to approach them
with respect curiosity and a willingness
to learn from the lived experiences and
interpretations of Buddhist
practitioners
themselves by doing so we can avoid the
pitfalls of orientalism and gain a more
authentic nuanced understanding of these
teachings and their significance in
Buddhist thought and
practice if you encounter descriptions
of Buddhist hell Realms take a moment to
critically examine how these ideas are
being presented and framed are they
being sensationalized or taken out of
context are the voices and perspectives
of Buddhist practitioners being centered
by asking these questions we can work
towards a more balanced culturally
sensitive understanding of this complex
and fascinating aspect of Buddhist
cosmology imagine realizing that the
hell Realms are not external places but
internal States we create through our
own actions and thoughts this Revelation
is empowering it means that we have the
power to change our destiny not through
fear of punishment but through
cultivating positive qualities like
compassion mindfulness and
wisdom this moment of realization can be
life-changing it's the point where
understanding transforms into action and
we see that our spiritual journey is not
about avoiding hell but about creating
Heaven within ourselves through our
daily
practices all right folks we've covered
a lot of ground today from the fiery
pits of the hell realms to the lofty
Heights of Enlightenment we've explored
the nature of suffering the consequences
of our actions and the path to
Liberation but before we wrap things up
let's take a moment to reflect on some
of the key takeaways from our
discussion remember as the Mahayana
mahaparinirvana Sutra
teaches all conditioned phenomena are
like a dream an
Illusion by understanding the
metaphorical nature of Buddhist Hells we
can better navigate our mental state
States and cultivate a life of peace and
wisdom remember that the path to
Liberation is not a one-time event or a
quick fix it's a lifelong journey of
growth learning and
transformation by cultivating the
essential practices of mindfulness
compassion and wisdom we can gradually
break free from the cycle of suffering
and rebirth and experience a deeper
sense of Peace purpose and connection
with all things and finally remember
that you're not alone on this path as a
community of spiritual Seekers We're All
in This Together supporting each other
learning from each other and inspiring
each other to keep going even when the
road gets tough so don't be afraid to
reach out to share your experiences and
to lean on the wisdom and compassion of
those around
you before we sign off for today I just
wanted to take a moment to thank each
and every one of you for being a part of
this amazing community
your presence your insights and your
commitment to the path of Awakening are
what make Buddha's wisdom such a special
place I invite you to hit that like
button and share this video with someone
who might appreciate a fresh perspective
on the
afterlife and if you're new to our
Channel be sure to subscribe and turn on
notifications so you never miss a moment
of wisdom inspiration or laughter and
hey we want to hear from you leave a
comment below and let us know your
thought thoughts on today's topic what
surprised you most about the Buddhist
conception of hell have you ever
encountered any pop culture references
to these
ideas your insights and experiences are
a gift to this community and we can't
wait to read
them until next time my friends may you
be happy may you be healthy and may you
be free from suffering and remember the
path to Liberation is not a destination
but a journey so enjoy the ride and
Trust in the
process thanks for watching everyone be
sure to join us next week for another
dose of wisdom compassion and humor and
as always May the Buddha's wisdom guide
you may the Dharma protect you and may
the sanha support you on your journey to
Awakening Namaste my friends and see you
next time on Buddha's wisdom