[Music]
3:00 a.m. phone glowing you know you
should sleep but the scroll just won't
stop does it ever feel like something
else is controlling you pulling you
deeper there's a name for this in
Buddhism a Hungry Ghost a spirit trapped
in Endless
craving imagine a being forever thirsty
but never satisfied driven mad by desire
sound familiar keep watching there's a
way out I know that late night screen
lit feeling all too well
[Music]
a few months ago I was right there
endlessly scrolling at 3:00 a.m. feeling
Hollow but unable to stop that's when
Buddha's ancient wisdom hit me in a way
I never
expected in a previous video we ventured
through the chilling Realms of Buddhist
Hells but there's another realm closer
to us a realm of hungry Ang R ghosts
unlike the Demons of Hell these ghosts
aren't locked away somewhere distant
they're already here hiding in our
habits haunting our minds like a Hungry
Ghost the untrained mind is never
satisfied with what it
has these aren't just ancient words this
is your Instagram feed at midnight your
Tik Tok binges your endless YouTube
rabbit
holes imagine being cursed with a hunger
that can never be satisfied a throat too
small to swallow a stomach too big to
fill an endless craving that drives you
mad this is what Buddha called tanha a
thirst that can never be quenched a
cycle of wanting more sound like fantasy
look around see that person who can't
stop shopping the one obsessed with
likes you right now unable to put down
your
phone you're experiencing one of
buddhism's three poisons greed or as I
like to call it the ghost of endless
craving
I'm Matt from Buddha's wisdom where we
turn ancient Buddhist teachings into
powerful tools for Modern Life this
Halloween special reveals the truth
about hungry ghosts how to spot them in
your daily life and the shocking ways
they're controlling you right
now plus a powerful story of a monk who
found the way
out your phone's glowing your ghost is
hungry ready to break
free now forget everything you know
about ghosts these aren't your sheet
wearing chain rattling Halloween
specials these are the beings Buddha
warned us about creatures trapped in a
reality of their own
Cravings remember my 3:00 a.m. scrolling
confession that night changed everything
because while staring at that endless
feed Buddha's words echoed in my mind
like a fish caught in a drying stream
mind thrashing in its thirst for
more imagine this a being with a body
the size of a house but a neck thinner
than a needle always starving Never
Satisfied even if they find an entire
ocean of water it turns to fire the
moment it touches their lips in Buddhism
this isn't just a spooky story it's one
of the six Realms we can be reborn into
if we let our Cravings control us but
here's the plot twist and I learned this
during my retreat in Thailand you don't
need to die to experience the Hungry
Ghost realm those hunger pangs they're
happening right now that endless Tik
tock scroll that's the poison of greed
those 3:00 a.m. Instagram stories that's
tanha endless thirst that Netflix
autoplay you can't resist that's the
Hungry Ghost of
entertainment that gaming achievement
you can't stop grinding for Pure ghost
energy those shopping apps you check
every hour the ghost of
materialism let me share something
personal last year I spent a lot of
money on inapp purchases games upgrades
premium features trying to fill a void
that kept getting bigger Buddha called
this the cycle of craving the more you
feed it the hungrier it
gets ancient Buddhist art shows these
creatures with bulging bellies and Tiny
mouths today that's your phone infinite
content but no amount feels like
enough these ghosts are trapped in a
nightmare Buffet surrounded by
everything they want but unable to enjoy
any of it sound famili
let's get personal for a second look at
your screen time right now go ahead I'll
wait shocking isn't it when I first
checked mine it was 9 hours 9 hours
daily that's not just fomo or bad habits
that's your Hungry Ghost mode activated
the average person spends 7 hours on
their phone daily that's 7 hours of
feeding a ghost that never gets full 7
hours of chasing likes views and
notifications that leave you feeling
emptier than
before as Buddha said desires are never
fulfilled by Indulgence think about your
last social media binge remember that
Hollow feeling after 2 hours of
scrolling that's not just boredom that's
your Hungry Ghost throwing a tantrum
because no matter how much content it
consumes it's still starving but before
you panic there's something you need to
understand about these ghosts something
I discovered after that brutal wakeup
call in Thailand something that could
flip your whole digital life upside
down let's get real about these ghost
symptoms Buddha talked about three
poisons that trap us in suffering greed
hatred and
delusion today these poisons show up as
different types of digital hunger and
trust me I've experienced all of them
first up physical hunger your your Uber
Eats history looks like a novel your
pantry is full but nothing feels right
late night snacks become a ritual during
my first Meditation Retreat my teacher
said something that hit home we're not
hungry for food we're hungry for
connection you're not feeding your body
you're feeding a ghost that's hijacked
your
Cravings Next Level emotional hunger
1,000 matches on dating apps zero real
connections 500 friends on Facebook
nobody to call at 3:00 a.m. perfect
Instagram feed empty DMS Buddha nailed
at 2500 years ago you can search the
whole world and never find anyone more
deserving of love than
yourself yet here we are swiping for
validation let me share something
uncomfortable few years ago I was
spending 6 hours a day on dating apps
six hours of swiping right on Strangers
while ignoring real connection
classic Hungry Ghost Behavior but wait
it gets deeper mental hunger Buddha
called it the monkey mind always jumping
from Branch to Branch Never Satisfied
sound familiar YouTube suggests a video
you click 3 hours later you're watching
conspiracy theories about underwater
basket weaving Netflix asks still
watching your ghost hits yes before you
can blink remember that Thailand Retreat
I mentioned no phones loud first 3 days
felt like withdrawal because it was the
three poisons were detoxing from my
system the scariest part these ghosts
team up that's right while you're Doom
scrolling with a midnight snack
listening to a podcast all three hungers
are feeding at
once in Buddhist terms you're not just
visiting the Hungry Ghost realm you're
building a vacation home there the
craving that binds us Buddha taught is
stronger than Prison Walls try putting
down your phone for an hour feel that
itch that anxiety that fomo creeping in
that's not you that's your ghost
throwing a tantrum and just when you
think you've got it under control these
ghosts start running your entire
schedule remember my 3:00 a.m. story
that was just the beginning let me show
you exactly how these hungry ghosts
hijack your
day time for some ghost hunting in your
daily routine Buddha taught that
awareness is the first step to Freedom
after my retreat I started tracking my
own ghost moments and trust me what I
discovered changed everything morning
ghost your alarm rings but before your
feet Hit the Floor your hands already
grabbed your phone fun fact monks wake
up at 4:00 a.m. and their first action
is taking three mindful breaths us
Instagram email Tik Tok Facebook Twitter
every app gets checked not because you
need to but because your ghost is
already starving the mind is everything
what you think you become Bud's words
hit different when you realize you're
becoming your
notifications work ghost that important
deadline's coming up but instead of
focusing you're checking crypto prices
every 5
minutes confession time I once lost a
writing gig because I spent the whole
day checking my crypto portfolio
the three poisons in action Greed for
gains hatred for losses delusion about
getting rich
quick lunch ghost you order food take a
photo edit it post it check likes
recheck likes forget to actually eat
your food Meanwhile your ghost is
feasting on validation and your lunch is
getting cold Buddha taught mindful
eating we practice mindless posting
social ghost Friday night you're out
with friends but your ghost keeps
yanking your attention to your pocket
remember my Thailand Story the most
powerful moment wasn't the meditation it
was having actual conversations without
phones no likes no shares just
presents bedtime ghost just one more
video one more episode
one more
scroll midnight passes 1:00 a.m. 2: a.m.
in Buddhist monasteries they say the
Hungry Ghost realm is strongest at night
looking at our phone habits they might
be on to
something weekend ghost two full days of
Freedom perfect time to hit the gym read
that book start that project
instead your ghost has other plans
before you know it you're 47 weeks deep
in your ex's new girlfriend's cousin's
Instagram as Buddha said your worst
enemy cannot harm you as much as your
own unguarded thoughts the most ruthless
part these ghosts are invisible to
everyone else nobody sees you checking
your phone under the table nobody knows
about your 2 a.m. digital binges nobody
suspects you're possessed but your
screen time numbers they tell a
different story just like my 9-hour
wakeup call these numbers don't
lie and speaking of wakeup calls there's
an ancient Buddhist story that
completely changed how I view digital
addiction you know what else doesn't lie
ancient Buddhist wisdom and there's one
story That Shook Me Harder than my own
300 a.m. Rock
Bottom the past is already gone the
future is not yet here there is only the
present moment Buddha taught this but
watch how it plays out in this
story meet ma gayana Buddha's most
gifted disciple think of him as the
ancient world's greatest
Ghostbuster during my time in Thailand
my teacher compared him to a spiritual
superhero he could read mines fly
through walls travel between Realms the
spiritual equivalent of having every
Premium app subscription blue check mark
and viral post
combined but one day he discovered
something that shattered his world his
own mother reborn in the hungry ghost
realm let that sink in the most
connected person in the spiritual World
couldn't even help his own mom every
piece of food he manifested turned to
fire in her mouth every drop of water
became acid I remember sitting in
meditation thinking about my own mom's
Facebook addiction and this story hit
differently here was the most powerful
monk in history powerless to help his
own mother just like many of us feel
powerless watching our loved on scroll
their lives away desperate he ran to
Buddha and here's where it gets real
Buddha dropped a truth bomb that
explains everything you're experiencing
right now the Hungry Ghost realm isn't
just a place it's a state of
mind one of the six Realms we create
with our own cravings and no amount of
power money or followers can free you
from it the
solution this is what blew my mind
during a retreat it wasn't meditation it
wasn't prayers it wasn't even Buddha's
direct intervention it was Community
Connection real human bonds Buddha
taught in the end only three things
matter how much you loved how gently you
lived and how gracefully you let go of
things not meant for you only when the
entire Buddhist Community came together
sharing their Merit their positive
actions their genuine concern only then
was M Galay Yana's mother mother freed
from her ghostly prison think about that
the world's most powerful monk couldn't
save one person alone but together they
changed everything just like my own
Journey it wasn't an app or a hack that
helped me Break Free it was joining a
meditation group sharing struggles
finding real connection now look at your
phone again those notifications those
likes those followers are they filling
your hunger or are they keeping you
trapped like mgal y's mother in an
endless cycle of craving but don't worry
just like buddha showed mgal Yana the
way out I'm about to show you how to
break
free Breaking Free from your Hungry
Ghost isn't about deleting all your apps
or throwing your phone into a river
Buddha never taught Extreme Measures he
taught the middle way during my retreat
I tried the whole digital detox thing
guess what happened when I got back
Ghost came back stronger as Buddha said
neither fire nor wind nor birth nor
death can erase our Good Deeds so let's
turn those ghost habits into Good Deeds
here's how first build your ghost
busting Squad remember mgal Yana's story
solo players lose this game this hit
home when I joined a meditation group
back home right now pause this video and
text three friends real friends not just
Instagram mutuals tell them you're
forming a ghost busting Squad make plans
real plans not just virtual ones my
squad we meet every Sunday no phones
just coffee conversation and occasional
crisis management your ghost hates that
stuff because it knows Community breaks
the first poison Greed for digital
validation second the two-minute ghost
test
this comes straight from Buddhist
mindfulness practice before each action
pause and
reflect every time you reach for your
phone give yourself 2 minutes just
two ask yourself Buddha's three
questions is this
necessary is this
beneficial is this just my ghost hungry
for more sounds
simple during my retreat it took me 3
days to stop reaching for my Phantom
phone your ghost will fight you on this
one because awareness breaks the second
poison
delusion third the ultimate ghost
repellent here's what really scares
hungry ghosts generosity Dana as
Buddhists call it giving sharing not
just likes and reposts real stuff help
someone share knowledge create something
valuable personal story time I used to
spend hours is making perfect Instagram
stories now I spend that time creating
videos like this one same skills
different purpose ghosts can't stand
genuine contribution it breaks the third
poison hatred or aversion to what's real
but here's the ninja move I learned from
my teacher turn your ghost habits into
human habits use that Instagram account
to share real moments not filtered
facades transform your YouTube binges
into learning session sessions convert
your Reddit scrolling into genuine
Community
participation the secret ghosts feed on
isolation they starve in connection
every real conversation every genuine
laugh every actual human moment weakens
their grip Buddha said it
best thousands of candles can be lit
from a single candle and the life of the
candle will not be shortened and those
withdrawal symptoms I mentioned earlier
they're not per perent I know because
I've been there your ghost will throw
Tantrums it will beg for attention it
will promise that the next scroll will
finally satisfy you but now you know
better because here's what M galana
really taught us even the most powerful
beings need a system a protocol a way to
maintain their freedom and that's
exactly what I'm about to show
you your ghost free PowerUp protocol
Starts Now Buddha taught that Liberation
comes in stages think of this as your
spiritual video game three levels to
break free from the Hungry Ghost realm
let me share something I learned the
hard way after Thailand I thought I was
cured then I downloaded Tik Tok game
over that's when my teacher shared
Buddha's wisdom drop by drop fills the
bucket small changes consistent practice
level one ghost
tracking know your enemy Buddha taught
your phone has has a secret weapon
screen time stats but we're going deeper
track your ghost moments in real time
when do they appear what triggers them
my ghost it loves 4 p.m. that post lunch
pre- evening slump once I knew that I
could prepare now it's meditation time
your ghost hates being watched because
awareness is cryptonite to craving level
two Freedom practices remember the six
Realms we're aiming for the human realm
balanced aware present start small set
up ghost free zones in your day here's
my routine learned from monks first hour
after waking sacred no phones just
breathing moving existing your ghost
will hate these zones at first good as
Buddha said discomfort is the gateway to
peace create a morning ritual that
doesn't involve screens could be
meditation could be push-ups could be
staring at clouds
I started with 1 minute of
meditation now 30 minutes feel
short what matters is you're choosing
reality over digital
demons level three the ultimate power
move this is where you become the Ghost
Hunter instead of the Haunted take those
ghost triggering moments and flip them
social media
craving send a text to someone you
haven't talked to in a while YouTube SP
spiral coming hit the gym instead
shopping urge clean your room remember
ma galana his power came from helping
others that's your boss level teaching
others about their ghosts because here's
the Wild Thing once you start seeing
these patterns you'll notice them
everywhere my proudest moment wasn't
deleting social media it was helping my
mom reduce her Facebook time from 6
hours to 1 just like mod gal Yana's
community we get stronger when we help
others Break Free your phone isn't
cursed your apps aren't evil as Buddha
taught it's not the objects that bind us
but our attachment to them your ghost
it's counting on your unconscious
patterns to stay alive but now you have
the power to change the
game look at your phone right now that
glow isn't just blue light it's your
ghost Spotlight but after today you're
seeing it differently aren't you
as Buddha said when the student is ready
the teacher appears maybe your ghost LED
you here for a reason let me share one
last personal story remember that 3:00
a.m. scrolling moment I mentioned that
night I hit rock bottom 9 hours of
screen time zero real
connections but that Moment of clarity
it changed everything just like mgal
found Hope in community I found mine
right here with you
next time you catch yourself scrolling
at 3:00 a.m. you'll know what's really
going
on when that notification itch hits
you'll recognize who's really scratching
that's not defeat that's awareness and
as Buddha taught awareness is the path
to
immortality think about mod
galana even with all his supernatural
abilities he needed something more
powerful than magic he needed awareness
connection community
the same things we all need in this
digital age and that's exactly what
we're building here at Buddha's wisdom a
ghostbusting community a place where
ancient wisdom meets Modern Life where
we transform hungry ghosts into
conscious creators here's your first
Power move hit
subscribe yeah I know sounds ironic but
these aren't ghost feeds these are your
weekly reminders to stay human in a
digital world turn on notifications
plot twist let's use the ghost's tools
against it drop a comment what's your
strongest ghost moment share it because
somewhere out there another viewer is
fighting the same ghost remember mgal
Yana's mother was freed through
Community Action your comment might be
someone else's
Liberation I'm Matt and remember your
ghost only has the power you give it
just like Buddha taught you are your own
master who else could be see you in the
next video Stay Hungry For Life not
likes and remember every time you choose
presents over scrolling you're not just
fighting a ghost you're Awakening a
Buddha
[Music]