have you heard about the Buddha's most
hardcore disciple get this he was a
legit serial
killer buckle up because the story of
angala is a wild ride that'll blow your
mind and change the way you think about
Redemption what's up everyone it's your
boy Matt back with another episode of
Buddha's
wisdom today we're diving into the
jaw-dropping tale of angulimala a stone
cold killer who terrorized ancient India
until a mind-blowing encounter with the
Buddha flipped his life upside down this
story is living proof that it's never
too late to turn things around no matter
how messed up your past is get ready for
plot twists life lessons and a serious
dose of
inspiration let's go picture this you're
chilling in the forests of ancient India
vibing with nature when suddenly bam a
blood curdling scream shatters your Zen
you're Frozen in fear as a terrifying
figure emerges from The Shadow
rocking a necklace made of wait for it
severed human
fingers meet angulimala the baddest
serial killer in the land but here's the
crazy thing angulimala wasn't always a
stone cold killer nope he used to be a
brilliant student named ahim Saka with a
bright future ahead of him but then his
jealous classmates played a messed up
prank convincing their teacher that ahim
Saka was trying to steal his wife the
teacher blind with rage demanded a
payment of 1,000 human
fingers talk about a twisted extra
credit
assignment consumed by betrayal and
Madness aim Saka became angulimala the
finger Garland and went on a killing
spree that made Freddy Krueger looked
like a toy he roamed the forests slaying
anyone unlucky enough to cross his path
and adding their fingers to his Grizzly
necklace the more he killed the longer
his necklace grew seriously messed up
way to accessorize if you ask me the
people were straight up
terrified no privacy and silently it
could build and build until you finally
see whoo it's taking over damn no
closure moving closer no exposure I just
want to be a loner some can't say sober
looking over other shoulders like moving
Boulders just to get out of the home it
sucks I've had enough I don't want to
feel the stuck
under the rug all my problems that I
shove I got night in my head but just
when you think this story can't get any
Wilder the Buddha himself enters the
scene one day as angulimala is about to
kill his own mother yeah it gets that
dark he spots the Buddha walking down
the road thinking he's found his final
victim angulimala charges at the Buddha
ready to add one more finger to his
collection but get this no matter how
fast angulimala runs he can't catch up
to the
Buddha it's like the Buddha's got a
force field or something angulimala the
most notorious killer around is totally
stumped exhausted and humbled angala
shouts yo monk stop right there the
Buddha cool as a cucumber replies I've
already stopped angulimala I've stopped
harming all living beings but you you're
still running wild my dude angulimala is
shook For The First Time in Forever he's
forced to face the reality of his crimes
the Buddha's words cut deep and
angulimala starts to question everything
the Buddha sensing anguli mala's inner
struggle dropped some serious wisdom
angulimala you've been trapped in a
vicious cycle of violence and suffering
causing mad pain to others and yourself
but listen up it's never too late to
change you've got the power to choose a
different path
homie as the Buddha speaks angala feels
a tital wave of emotions crashing down
on him the weight of his crimes the
Betrayal The Emptiness it all hits him
at once he looks at his grotesque finger
necklace and feels nothing but disgust
and Horror in the Buddha's eyes angula
sees a glimmer of hope a chance to break
free from the darkness that's been
suffocating him the Buddha's words echo
in his mind it's never too late to
change with shaking hands angulimala
rips the the finger necklace off and
tosses it aside shattering the symbol of
his brutal past he falls to his knees
before the Buddha tears streaming down
his face teach me Lord he whispers teach
me how to stop this
madness the Buddha places a gentle hand
on angul mala's head rise up angulimala
walk the path of the
dharm through compassion mindfulness and
wisdom you can transform your life and
find the peace you've been searching for
with tears in his eyes angula takes
refuge in the triple gem the Buddha the
dhama the Buddha's teachings and the San
the monastic Community he vows to
dedicate his life to the path of
Awakening to heal the wounds of his past
and to help others find the same Freedom
he's glimpsed in the Buddha's
presence as a symbol of his commitment
angulimala ditches his killer name and
becomes aim Saka the nonviolent one
under the Buddha's guidance he Dives
deep into the teachings of the triple
gem cultivating kindness empathy and a
sense of purpose ahim Saka commits
himself to the monastic life joining the
sanha and embracing a path of Simplicity
renunciation and spiritual growth he
shaves his head rocks the monk robes and
lives by the monastic code celibacy
nonviolence and a dedication to Inner
transformation with within the S aim
Saka finds a supportive crew of monks
and nuns who've got his back on his
journey of redemption he learns from the
wise Elders swaps stories with his
fellow monks and immerses himself in the
study and practice of the
Dharma The Road to Redemption is long
and full of obstacles but a himaka never
wavers he meditates like a boss studies
the dharm with passion and lives a life
of Simplicity and
renunciation step by step he sheds the
layers of anger guilt and delusion that
one consumed him transforming from the
inside out as aim Saka progresses on the
path of dhama his story starts to spread
like wildf fire people are mindblown to
learn that the once feared serial killer
has become a devoted monk radiating
peace and
compassion those who once trembled At
The Mention of his name now seek him out
for guidance and inspiration despite his
heavy past ahim Saka Embraces his new
role as a spiritual
guide he shares his story openly
using his own experiences to show the
transformative power of the Buddha's
teachings he becomes known for his deep
wisdom his chill Vibe and his ability to
connect with people from all walks of
life as word of aima's transformation
spreads even the king who once hunted
him becomes a huge fan and supporter the
king sees the profound change in ahim
Saka and recognizes him as a Living
testament to the Buddha's message of
forgiveness and
redemption in time ahim Saka becomes one
of the most respected and beloved
members of the San his presence is a
constant reminder that no one is beyond
the reach of the Dharma and that even
the darkest pasts can be transformed
through dedication compassion and
wisdom ahima's story becomes a Beacon of
Hope for countless others struggling
with their own demons many who hear his
tale are inspired to take a hard look at
their own lives and seek the same
freedom and peace he's found in the
Buddha's
path even today centuries after after is
passing anguli mala's Legacy lives on as
a powerful symbol of the human capacity
for Change and the Limitless potential
for spiritual
growth his story continues to inspire
truth Seekers everywhere reminding us of
the transformative power of the triple
Gem and the boundless compassion of the
Buddha's teachings so what mind-blowing
lessons can we take away from angal
Lala's Epic
Journey one no matter how far gone you
think you are it's never too late to
change if a serial killer can become an
enlightened monk you can absolutely
transform your life no matter how messed
up your past
is two violence and hatred only breed
more of the
same the only way to break the cycle is
through forgiveness compassion and peace
even when it feels
impossible three face your karma head-on
own your past actions accept the
consequences and keep pushing forward on
the path of growth and
Redemption four never underestimate the
power of a single Moment of clarity just
like angul mala's mind-blowing encounter
with the Buddha a split-second
realization can completely change the
course of your life five find your tribe
like angulimala found in the Sanaa
surrounding yourself with like-minded
folks committed to personal growth can
be a GameChanger on your journey of
transformation six
the Buddha's approach to angul Li mala's
punishment is a powerful lesson in
compassion and wisdom instead of
condemning angulimala for his crimes the
Buddha sees the potential for change
within him through compassionate
guidance and skillful teaching the
Buddha helps angala face the
consequences of his actions and
transform his life this shows us that in
Buddhism punishment isn't about getting
even it's about Rehabilitation and
transformation by treating even the most
notorious criminals with compassion and
understanding we create the conditions
for real change and
Redemption and there you have it folks
the mind-blowing story of angulam mala's
transformation from notorious serial
killer to enlightened Buddhist monk his
journey is a powerful reminder that we
all have the capacity for change no
matter how lost we might feel if
angulimala can turn his life around so
can you if this story blew your mind
smash that like like button and share
your thoughts in the comments below and
if you want more epic stories
lifechanging wisdom and the occasional
bad monk joke be sure to hit that
subscribe button and join the Buddha's
wisdom family remember stay curious stay
wise and never stop believing in your
own potential for
transformation until next time keep it
real and keep it
[Music]
peaceful