hey guys
Matt here from Buddha's wisdom
and today
I'm going to share something that blew my mind
when I first discovered it
in 1700 Japan a samurai named Yamamoto Tsunetomo
wrote something that changed history forever
after decades of serving as
one of Japan's deadliest warriors
he revealed that true power comes not from the sword
but from Buddhist wisdom but don't click away
this isn't just another history lesson
this is the true story
of how Japan's most feared warriors
discovered something incredible
the path to becoming unstoppable
wasn't through more fighting
it was through meditation and inner peace
and get this
what these legendary warriors discovered centuries ago
is so powerful the modern Special Forces
Olympic athletes
and some of the world's top performers
still use these exact same techniques today
in this video you'll discover
how Buddhist wisdom
transformed Japan's deadliest fighters
into something far more powerful
we'll explore the 7 virtues
that turned ordinary warriors into legends
the secret training methods that modern
elite forces still use
and the mind blowing way these warriors found
ultimate power through inner peace
but first we need to go back to where it all began
to a time when Japan was torn by war
and warriors were about to discover something
that would change them forever
we need to go back to the year 1191
when something incredible happened in Japan
a Buddhist monk named Eisai returned from China
but this wasn't just any monk
Eisai was a Maverick a rebel
who had traveled across dangerous seas to China twice
searching for the deepest teachings of Buddhism
in China Eisai discovered something different
from the complex
Buddhist teachings that already existed
in Japan
he found Zen a direct
practical powerful way to train the mind
he knew this could change everything
you see Japan was in chaos
the old imperial system was breaking down
and a new warrior class called the samurai
was rising to power
these samurai were the deadliest fighters
Japan had ever seen but
they were searching for something more than just
physical strength
here's where it gets interesting
when Eisai brought Zen to Japan
he didn't go to the peaceful temples of Kyoto
instead
he headed straight to Kamakura
the warrior capital
because he saw something nobody else did
he recognized that
these warriors needed more than just combat training
they needed a way to master their minds
this brings us to Kenchō-ji
now this wasn't just another temple
Kenchō-ji was the first Zen training monastery
ever built in Japan founded in 1253
by the most powerful warrior family of the time
the Hōjō clan
picture this
a massive temple complex built into the mountains
where warriors and monks trained side by side
think about how revolutionary this was
in one part of Kenchō-ji
you'd have monks sitting in complete silence
while in another samurai practiced sword techniques
but something remarkable happened when these two worlds
collided the warriors began to realize that the monks
mental training
could make them more effective in battle
the records from Kenchō-ji tell us something fascinating
these samurai discovered that through Zen practice
they could maintain absolute clarity and chaos
make split second decisions without hesitation
and develop an awareness
that seemed almost supernatural
these aren't just stories passed down
we have actual written records
The Azuma Kagami
a detailed historical chronicle from that period
documents how the Hōjō rulers
actively supported this fusion of Zen
and warrior culture
pretty cool
when history backs up these incredible tales
this combination of warrior skills and Buddhist wisdom
created something entirely new
something that would change Japanese culture forever
and lead to the development of a remarkable code
that we still study today
want to know what these warriors discovered?
let's explore
the 7 incredible virtues that became known as Bushido
the way of the warrior
so what exactly
was this code that emerged from the fusion of Zen
wisdom and warrior culture
the samurai called it Bushido
the way of the warrior
and at its heart were seven virtues
that transformed these fighters
into something far more powerful
the first virtue is righteousness or Gi
Imagine being so committed to doing what's right
that you'd give up everything to protect it
that's exactly what happened in 1701
when 47 samurai sacrificed their entire lives
to rightfully avenge their master
knowing they'd be sentenced to death for it that's Gi
I know what you're thinking Matt
are you telling me
these super serious warriors were basically ancient
Buddhist life coaches?
well
kind of
but
instead of posting inspirational quotes on Instagram
they were living these principles
with a sword at their side
then we have courage Yu
but this isn't about being fearless
the samurai new real
courage is about facing your fears and acting anyway
historical records tell us of warriors
who would meditate before battle
not to eliminate fear
but to act with clarity despite it
benevolence Jin
now this one might surprise you
these deadly warriors were expected to show compassion
and mercy
we have documented cases of samurai
protecting entire villages during wars
even when it went against their lord's orders
because jin meant using your power to help others
respect Rei
this wasn't just about bowing and being polite
it went much deeper
there are records of samurai
treating their enemies with honor
even in death
because they understood
the true power comes with deep respect for all life
honesty Makoto
the samurai believed that lying poisoned your spirit
real records from clan meetings
show how warriors would admit their mistakes
even when it meant severe punishment
because truth was more important than consequences
honor Meiyo
your reputation was everything
but not in the way you might think
it wasn't about fame
it was about being the same person in private
that you were in public living with complete integrity
no matter who was watching
and finally loyalty
Chugi
but here's the fascinating part
the samurai combined this with Buddhist wisdom
true loyalty wasn't blind obedience
it was about being loyal to your principles first
to what you knew was right
but these virtues weren't just philosophical ideas
written in ancient texts they were practical tools
that transformed every aspect of a warrior's life
and that's where our story gets even more interesting
Wanna know how they actually trained in these virtues?
how they turned these principles into real power?
let's look at the incredible ways they trained
both body and mind
now let me show you how these warriors actually trained
because what they did
was unlike anything the world had seen before
they didn't just practice sword techniques
they completely rewired their minds and bodies
let's look at something fascinating
from Yagyu Munenori's Secret Manual written in 1632
he was the sword instructor to three Japanese shoguns
and he wrote something incredible
the highest level of sword mastery
isn't about sword techniques
at all it's about achieving what they called no mind
but what exactly is no mind
imagine being so present so focused
that your body moves
before your thoughts get in the way
the samurai would spend hours in meditation
then immediately pick up their swords
they discovered that an empty mind made their reactions
lightning fast
picture trying to explain to your friends
that your new workout routine
involves sitting completely still
and emptying your mind
they probably think you're just being lazy
but these warriors knew better
it's actually harder than doing 1,000 pushups
trust me I tried both
here's a mind blowing training method they used
a warrior would sit in meditation in a temple
completely still
while behind him another samurai would wait
ready to strike with a wooden sword
the warrior wasn't allowed to move
until the exact moment of attack
this trained them to act from pure awareness
without thinking
and we have records of another incredible practice
samurai would spend hours performing the same sword cut
thousands of times but here's the key
they weren't just practicing the movement
they were learning to empty their minds
through the action making each cut
as if it were the only one that mattered
in the dojo they had the saying
think about that
these warriors figured out that the real battle
wasn't with the enemy it was with their own thoughts
their own fears their own doubts
the craziest part
modern science
is just now proving how effective these methods were
studies show that this combination of meditation
and movement literally rewires your brain
making you calmer under pressure
sharper in your decisions and faster in your reactions
and here's something wild
these exact same techniques are being used today
Navy
Seals practice meditation before high stakes missions
just like those ancient warriors
Olympic athletes
use these focusing methods to stay calm
under pressure even Silicon Valley
CEOs are taking up sword practice and meditation
talk about history repeating itself right
but
the real test of all this training wasn't in the dojo
it was on the battlefield
and what happened when these warrior monks
put their training to the test
well that's a whole other story
ready to see
how this training played out in real combat?
because the
historical accounts of what these warriors could do
are absolutely incredible
let me take us from their training methods to real
historical examples of how they use these skills
so what happened when these warrior monks
put their training to the test
the historical records tell us
some absolutely incredible stories
take the famous battle of Sekigahara in 1600
we have documented accounts of samurai
who used their Zen training
in the middle of Japan's biggest and bloodiest battle
in their writings
they describe entering a state of total clarity
even as chaos erupted all around them
these warriors could sense exactly when to move
when to strike and most importantly when to stay still
but here's an even more amazing example
in 1582
a samurai named Tadaoki Hosokawa faced an entire army
with just a handful of men
the odds were impossible but instead of panicking
historical records tell us
he sat in meditation before the battle
when he opened his eyes
he led his men with such calm precision
that they held their position for three crucial hours
saving thousands of lives
and it wasn't just in battle
we have records from the Tokugawa period
of samurai
using their Zen training in real sword duels
they describe something fascinating
the ability to read their opponent's intention
before they even moved
one account tells of a master
who won a duel without drawing his sword
he sensed his opponent's attack coming
and simply wasn't there when the strike came
but perhaps the most powerful example
comes from the writings of Miyamoto Musashi
Japan's most famous sword saint
he won over 60 duels and in his book
The Book of Five Rings he tells us his secret
the mind must be free like the surface of still water
he wasn't talking about fighting technique
he was describing the Zen state
he achieved through years of training
but
it wasn't just warriors who mastered these principles
there's this amazing story about a Zen master
named Hakuin when falsely accused of fathering a child
he simply said is that so
and took care of the baby for a year
when the truth finally came out
he returned the child with the same calm response
now that's what you call keeping your cool
the samurai weren't the only ones who could stay calm
under pressure
these weren't just isolated incidents
all across Japan
warriors who combined Zen practice with martial arts
were doing things that seemed impossible
moving with perfect timing
making decisions in split seconds
remaining totally calm in the face of death
but here's what's really interesting
the real power of their training showed up
and how they lived not just how they fought
and that brings us to our final chapter
about how these warrior monks
applied their wisdom to everyday life
wanna know how they turn these battlefield insights
into principles for daily living?
because this might be the most valuable lesson of all
let me show you why these ancient warrior monks
teachings became so powerful
in 1700 Yamamoto Tsunetomo wrote something fascinating
the way of the samurai is found in death
now that sounds pretty dark
but what he really meant was revolutionary
by accepting death
these warriors learn to live more fully
more authentically calm than ever before
let me give you a real example
from the historical records
every morning samurai would wake before dawn
they would begin their day with meditation
followed by weapons practice
but here's the interesting part
before any training
they would spend time contemplating their own death
not in a morbid way
but as a reminder to live this day with purpose
their daily routines were incredible
we have detailed records from samurai households
they would alternate between intense training
and periods of peaceful arts
from sword practice to calligraphy
from meditation to poetry
they understood something profound
true strength comes from balance
but it went even deeper than that
these warriors
applied the seven virtues to everything they did
when they prepared tea they did it with the same focus
they brought to sword fighting
when they arranged flowers
they approached it with the same discipline
as military strategy even
their everyday conversations
were guided by principles of respect
and honesty
and here's the mind blowing part
we found scrolls
describing how some samurai would spend hours
just arranging their armor
not out of vanity but as a meditation practice
every action no matter how small
was a chance to train their minds
think about it
these warriors figured out something incredible
the same principles that kept them alive in battle
made their everyday lives extraordinary
the focus that helped them face death
help them live more fully
and get this these warrior monks influenced
spread way beyond the battlefield
their
Zen practices transform Japanese culture itself
from the precise movements of the tea ceremony
to the minimalist beauty of rock gardens
even today's Japanese architecture and design
it all carries traces of this warrior monk wisdom
who knew the deadliest fighters in Japan
would end up influencing art more than war
and that that brings us to something even more amazing
because what these warrior monks discovered
centuries ago
is still changing lives today
these ancient warrior monks
discovered something timeless
something that's just as powerful today
as it was centuries ago
the ultimate strength isn't in your sword
or even in your skills it's in your mind
think about it we just witnessed
how deadly warriors
transformed into enlightened masters
how the same principles that made them unstoppable
in battle help them find inner peace
and here's the amazing thing
you can use these exact same principles in your life
today whether you're facing challenges at work
dealing with stress or just
trying to become a stronger version of yourself
the wisdom of these warrior monks shows us the way
their seven virtues their training methods
their daily practices
they all point to one simple truth
real power starts from within
and just like those ancient warriors
found their strength in Zen temples
you too can begin this journey right now today
if you wanna discover more about
the incredible wisdom of Buddhism
hit that subscribe button and join our community
drop a comment below let me know
which of the 7 virtues resonated with you the most
and don't forget to hit that bell icon
to stay updated on new videos
thanks for watching I'll see you in the next video