you're meditating peacefully under a tree
when you hear thundering footsteps
you open your eyes and there's a massive
drunk elephant charging straight at you
but here's the insane part
the person who sent this killer elephant
isn't some random enemy it's your own cousin
your childhood best friend
have you ever had family turn against you
ever wondered how far jealousy could push someone
well buckle up
and this this is just attempt number one
Meet Devadatta Buddhism's version of Judas
the disciple who turns against his master
but with three murder attempts and a body count plan
three assassination attempts
one family betrayal and a story
that'll change how you think about toxic relatives
forever
this story isn't just legend
it's recorded across multiple ancient texts
including the Vinaya Pitaka and the Cullavagga
and what it reveals about human jealousy is wild
but what Buddha did next will blow your mind
so who exactly was Devadatta
and how did Buddha's own cousin
become his deadliest enemy
two boys growing up in the same royal palace
both princes both incredibly talented
but only one gets called the Chosen One
Siddhartha you know him as Buddha was the golden child
prophecies royal treatment
everyone talking about his destiny
Devadatta?
he was just the other prince
the backup the spare
but get this
Devadatta wasn't just good at everything
he was exceptional
he could shoot arrows with deadly precision
wrestle wild animals
and had this magnetic personality that drew people to
him
ever feel like you're living in someone else's shadow
that's Devadatta's entire childhood
every single day
people talking about how special his cousin is
while he's just there now
imagine this happening in your own family
your sibling gets all the attention
all the praise all the opportunities
how would that feel
how far might that jealousy push you
fast forward Siddhartha becomes Buddha
attracts thousands of followers
kings bow down to him your childhood playmate is now
literally the most famous person alive
that kind of jealousy
it's one of the three poisons Buddha warned about greed
hatred and delusion
and Devadatta was about to drink all three
some say Devadatta even admired Siddhartha once
before the jealousy began
but jealousy was about to turn deadly
Devadatta is watching his cousin
become the world's biggest
spiritual celebrity
and the jealousy is eating him alive
but he doesn't just want to compete with Buddha
he wants him gone permanently
his first murder plot absolutely insane
ancient India no guns
no poison so what do you use to kill someone
a massive drunk elephant
Meet Nalagiri a war elephant
already aggressive already dangerous
but Devadatta takes it to the next level
he gets this beast
completely wasted on fermented rice wine
until it's stumbling around
completely out of control
then he waits
Buddha's walking through the narrow streets of Rajagaha
collecting alms completely peaceful
completely unprotected and Devadatta knows his routine
so one morning just as Buddha's walking down
this narrow street with his disciples
Devadatta releases Nalagiri
imagine this thundering noise
ground shaking people screaming
this massive
drunken elephant comes charging around the corner
trunk swinging tusks gleaming
eyes wild with rage and alcohol
Buddha's disciples they panic
they scatter they're shouting Run Buddha run
but Buddha doesn't move
he just stands there completely calm
watching this multi ton killing machine
charging straight at him
and then something impossible happens
as Nalagiri gets closer Buddha doesn't run
doesn't fight doesn't even flinch
instead he radiates pure
loving kindness directly toward this raging elephant
and Nalagiri suddenly stops
just stops right in front of Buddha
the elephant's eyes clear
the rage disappears and this massive creature slowly
gently kneels down like it's bowing
Buddha reaches out touches the elephant's trunk
speaks gently
the Dhammapada teaches :
and in that moment
Buddha didn't fight the elephant he loved him
this isn't just legend
these events are recorded in the Vinaya Pitaka
one of the oldest collections of Buddhist
monastic rules
it happened the crowd is in shock
the elephant keepers are in shock
even Buddha's disciples are stunned
but Devadatta he's furious
his perfect murder plan
just made his cousin look even more divine
but Devadatta wasn't giving up he was escalating
the elephant plan failed spectacularly
so Devadatta decides
if I can't use an animal to kill him
I'll do it myself
this time he's calculated personal
he studies Buddha's routines
looking for the perfect opportunity
he finds it on Vulture Peak
Buddha's favorite meditation spot
Buddha goes there regularly to teach
to find peace it's his sanctuary
and Devadatta is about to turn it into a crime scene
Buddha's walking up the mountain path
completely absorbed in meditation
completely trusting
Devadatta's already there
hiding behind rocks waiting
he's found the perfect boulder
massive heavy enough to crush a person instantly
positioned right above where Buddha always walks
Buddha's climbing slowly peacefully
disciples following behind
enjoying the mountain air
they have no idea that 30 feet above them
Buddha's own cousin is crouched behind a rock
hands on a boulder waiting
then Devadatta sees his chance
Buddha's directly below him
no escape route perfect positioning
Devadatta pushes this massive boulder
starts rolling bouncing
picking up speed heading straight for Buddha's head
but then something impossible happens again
just as this rock is about to crush Buddha
it hits another rock and splits perfectly in half
most of it crashes harmlessly aside
but one sharp fragment cuts Buddha's foot
drawing blood
the Cullavagga part of the ancient monastic texts
tells us this wasn't symbolic
it happened and it left a mark
so Devadata actually succeeded partially
he became the first
and only person to make Buddha bleed
but instead of celebrating
something else happens
Buddha stops looks at his bleeding foot
then looks up directly at Devadatta's hiding spot
their eyes meet Buddha's expression
isn't anger isn't fear
it's sadness pure
deep sadness like he's looking at a lost child
who's fallen so far from Grace
Buddha doesn't call out doesn't accuse
doesn't seek revenge
he wraps his foot and continues walking
like nothing happened
and this drives Devadatta absolutely insane
Buddha's complete lack of retaliation
makes him look even more petty
more evil more isolated
if he couldn't kill Buddha with rocks
he needed professionals
two failed attempts
and Devadata's running out of sanity
this time he's not going solo
he's recruiting help professional help
enter King Ajatashatru
ruler of one of India's most powerful kingdoms
Devadatta approaches him with a proposal
you control the people I'll control the monks
together we rule everything
the king hungry for absolute power agrees
but their murder plot is diabolical
they recruit an assassin with poisoned fingernails
yeah that was actually a thing
one scratch and within hours
you're dead no weapons
no obvious murder but Devadatta is paranoid
so he recruits backup assassins
if the first fails
they kill Buddha and the first assassin
if those fail more assassins kill everyone
it's like a murder pyramid scheme
the first assassin approaches Buddha
during his teaching gets close
raises his poisoned hand ready for that fatal scratch
but then something extraordinary happens
the moment this killer looks into Buddha's eyes
hears his voice
something inside him breaks
this professional murderer
throws himself at Buddha's feet
confesses everything reveals the entire plot
Devadatta the king
everyone
Buddha's response
he doesn't call for guards or demand justice
he looks at this assassin and says
your honesty has saved you
go in peace
just like that Buddha converts
a professional killer into a peaceful monk
but it gets better
all the backup assassins witness this
one by one they come forward confess
ask for forgiveness within hours
Devadatta's entire murder squad has
become Buddha's disciples
King Ajatasatru hears what happened and panics
he's just been exposed as an assassination conspirator
but Buddha sends a message
the king is forgiven let him rule in peace
no revenge no retaliation
just forgiveness
and this finally breaks something inside Devadatta
every attempt to destroy Buddha
has only made him look more divine
more worthy of worship
but if he couldn't destroy the teacher
maybe he could destroy the teaching itself
three failed assassinations
and Devadatta finally realizes
Buddha is impossible to kill
so he changes tactics
if I can't destroy the man
I'll destroy his movement
from the inside
Devadatta approaches Buddha
with improvements to Buddhism
in front of hundreds of monks
he announces stricter rules
all monks should live in forests forever
only eat begged food wear only rags
sleep under trees never eat meat
sounds holy right
but Buddha sees through this
Devadata is trying to make Buddhism so extreme
that only fanatical monks will remain
monks he can control
Buddha's response is masterful
these are good suggestions
for those who wish to follow them
but they should be optional
not mandatory
with that simple response
Buddha deflates Devadatta's power grab
but Devadatta's prepared
he's been secretly recruiting younger monks
convincing them Buddha's become too soft
too commercial
he stands up and declares Buddha's lost his way
he's too old too comfortable
I'll lead the true followers
and it works sort of
about 500 young monks follow him
impressed by his charisma and promises of pure Buddhism
imagine Buddha's heartbreak
watching his own cousin
lead away hundreds of disciples
claiming to be the real Buddhist leader
but Buddha doesn't argue doesn't fight back
he simply continues teaching
demonstrating through actions
what true Buddhism looks like
and his silence speaks louder than any argument
within weeks those 500 monks notice something
without Buddha around to compete with
Devadatta shows his true nature controlling
demanding obsessed with rules and punishment
the pure Buddhism Devadatta promised
it turns into a cult of fear
question him and you're punished
compassion gets replaced by control
one by one the monks return to Buddha apologizing
asking for forgiveness Buddha welcomes them back
no questions no punishments
no lectures
just welcome home
but for Devadatta watching his followers abandon him
this realization comes too late
the karma he's been building is about to explode
Devadatta's failed at everything
murder conspiracy
community splitting he's alone abandoned
exposed as a fraud
but the universe isn't done with him yet
according to Buddhist teachings
some actions create Änantariya karma
immediate consequences
attacking an awakened being
that's one of them
and Devadatta was about to find out why
strange things start happening
Devadata develops a mysterious illness
his body breaking down not from disease
but like his own hatred is eating him from the inside
his skin becomes covered in painful boils
his strength fails he's constantly feverish
the physical symptoms are nothing
compared to what's happening mentally
he starts having nightmares
where he's chased by the very elephants and boulders
he used against Buddha he can't sleep
can't eat can't find peace
people report supernatural events around him
ground shaking when he walks
animals fleeing plants withering in his presence
it's like the natural world is rejecting him
but Buddha knowing everything Devadatta has done
does something incredible
he visits his dying cousin
the man Devadatta tried to murder three times
walks into the room
where his cousin is being consumed by his own karma
seeing Buddha approach Devadatta panics
he knows he's dying
and his last chance for redemption is
standing right there he tries to get up
tries to bow but his body's too weak
he manages to raise his hands
and whispers with his dying breath
I take refuge in Buddha
Buddha places his hand on Devadatta's forehead
your recognition of truth creates merit
you are not completely lost
Devadatta dies right there
but with that final surrender
he creates just enough positive karma
to avoid the worst possible rebirth
but his death isn't quiet
the ancient texts say
the earth cracked open beneath him
thunder boomed flames erupted
it was like nature itself cried out
this is what happens when love turns to hate
Buddha's reaction to watching his cousin
swallowed by the earth not Celebration
not vindication grief pure heartbroken grief
he remembers the little boy
who played with him in palace court yards
taught him archery shared his royal childhood
somewhere inside that twisted man
that innocent child still existed
Buddha later tells his disciples
Devadatta was consumed by the three poisons greed
hatred and delusion but even in his final moment
he showed that awakening is possible for everyone
then Buddha says something that changes everything
Devadatta was my teacher as much as I was his
he taught me compassion by showing me hatred
patience by testing mine
forgiveness by doing the unforgivable
so what does this 2,500 year old family drama
teach us about dealing with toxic people today
first toxic people aren't born evil
Devadatta was consumed by the 3 poisons
greed for power hatred from jealousy
and delusion about his own righteousness
think about your own toxic family members
aren't they usually driven by these same forces
second fighting toxic people only makes them more toxic
every time Buddha could have retaliated
he chose compassion instead
that choice led to Devadatta's self destruction
Buddha didn't defeat his enemy
his enemy defeated himself
what would happen if you stopped fighting back
against your toxic relatives
third your worst enemies can be your greatest teachers
Buddha said Devadatta forced him to
practice compassion at the highest level
your toxic family members aren't just obstacles
they're your training ground for becoming more patient
forgiving and wise
fourth everyone has potential for redemption
even Devadatta in his final breath
found enough light to save himself from the worst fate
nobody is beyond hope
finally you can't control others actions
only your responses
Buddha couldn't stop the assassination attempts
but he could choose how to respond
with love instead of revenge
that choice made all the difference
remember what the Buddha said
hatred does not cease by hatred
but only by love that wasn't just a line
he lived it and so can we
next time someone close betrays you
remember Buddha and Devadatta
your response not their action
determines who you become
will you let their poison consume you
or will you choose the path that sets you free
choose compassion not because they deserve it
but because you do
you deserve freedom from hatred's poison
if this story changed how you think about forgiveness
or gave you tools for handling toxic people
smash that like button and subscribe
for more ancient wisdom that transforms modern lives
drop a comment who's your Devadatta
how are you choosing compassion over revenge
your story might be exactly
what someone else needs to hear
remember every time you choose compassion over revenge
you're not just changing your life
you're changing the world
one relationship at a time
thanks for watching Stay Wise and we'll see
you next time